[
  {
    "question": "When the Mach number technique (MNT) is being applied, and the preceding aircraft shall maintain a mach number equal to or greater than the following aircraft a RNAV distance based  separation minimum may be used on the same direction tracks in lieu of 10 minutes longitudinal separation minimum. The distance is :",
    "feedback": "80 NM"
  },
  {
    "question": "A circling approach is the extension of an instrument approach procedure",
    "feedback": "allowing visual circling prior to landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The transfer of an aircraft from one ATC unit to another is done :",
    "feedback": "by agreement with the receiving unit."
  },
  {
    "question": "On aerodromes aircraft taxying on the manoeuvring area of an aerodrome shall give way to:",
    "feedback": "aircraft taking off or about to take off"
  },
  {
    "question": "The procedure to be followed after having experienced a two way communication failure during a flight under IFR in VMC is:",
    "feedback": "continue to fly in VMC, land at the nearest suitable aerodrome and report its arrival by most expeditious means to the appropriate ATS unit"
  },
  {
    "question": "An ACAS RA is triggered, ordering a climb with a rate of 2000 ft/min and a few seconds later an ACAS RA is triggered ordering a descent with a rate of -2000 ft/min. What is the correct course of action?",
    "feedback": "Obey immediately to the RA and stay in safety margins of the rate of descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what moment during the approach should the reported airfield altimeter setting be set?",
    "feedback": "When passing the transition level"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Part SERA, aircraft bearing the nationality and registration marks of a Member State of the EU, when flying over the high seas, are required to follow the Rules of the Air specified....",
    "feedback": "in Annex 2 of the Chicago Convention"
  },
  {
    "question": "If visual reference is lost while circling to land from an instrument approach, it is expected that the pilot will make an initial climbing turn towards the:",
    "feedback": "Landing runway."
  },
  {
    "question": "What may trigger a NOTAM to be emitted?\n1) Long duration work on the aerodrome2) Work or reparation on the fuel feeding area3) High safety level that increases the time at the security checks4) Strong solar radiations5) Epidemics outbreak that requires the passengers for new vaccine6) Withdrawal, change or new lights on the aerodrome7) Work on the manoevuring area that does not impede the aircraft movements8) Changes in aerodrome designation signs",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4, 5, 8"
  },
  {
    "question": "The rate of decrease of temperature with height per 100 m in the International Standard Atmosphere is :",
    "feedback": "0.65°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line of the graph renders the unsaturated lapse rate?",
    "feedback": "The green lines"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding in-flight visibility when there is shallow fog at the aerodrome with no cloud above?",
    "feedback": "When overhead the aerodrome and well above the fog, objects on the aerodrome can often be seen relatively clearly"
  },
  {
    "question": "From what type of cloud does drizzle fall ?",
    "feedback": "Stratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Typical, average characteristics of a tropical rain climate are:",
    "feedback": "Relative humidity 80%, freezing level 15000 ft, average temperature 28°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which air mass and cloud depiction matches the routing A-B?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the four radio soundings corresponds with \"OVC015\"?",
    "feedback": "C"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are flying at FL 120 and the outside temperature is -2°C, at what altitude will the \"freezing level\" be?",
    "feedback": "FL 110"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the anwers best describes weather fronts?",
    "feedback": "The transition zones between two different air masses. This transition zone is inclined, the warmer air mass rises, and clouds and precipitation may develop"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight over the sea at FL 100 from Marseille (QNH 1016 hPa) to Palma de Mallorca (QNH 1016 hPa), the true altitude is constantly decreasing. What is the probable reason for this ?",
    "feedback": "The air at Marseille is warmer than that at Palma de Mallorca"
  },
  {
    "question": "For subsonic cruising levels, a SIGMET is NOT issued in case of",
    "feedback": "isolated CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the subscale is set to the QNH of an airfield the pressure altimeter indicates",
    "feedback": "elevation while landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning the tropopause is correct?",
    "feedback": "The layer just above the tropopause is absolutely stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "In addition to a lifting action, what are two other conditions necessary for thunderstorm formation ?",
    "feedback": "Unstable conditions and high moisture content"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is the wind in the METAR different from the wind broadcasted by the ATIS?",
    "feedback": "In the METAR, the surface wind is the average of the last 10 minutes, in the ATIS, it is the average of the last 2 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a cold-air drop?",
    "feedback": "A low pressure area with colder air compared to its surroundings. It can be found by looking at upper contour charts"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you have to fly through a warm front when freezing level is at 10000 feet in the warm air and at 2000 feet in the cold air, at which altitude is the probability of freezing rain the lowest ?",
    "feedback": "12000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "A wide body takes off on a clear night in Dhahran, Saudi Arabia. Shortly after take off the aircraft's rate of climb drops to zero. This can be due to",
    "feedback": "a very strong temperature inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What minimum visibility is forecast for PARIS/CHARLES-DE-GAULLE at 2100 UTC ?",
    "feedback": "6000m"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cold front is indicated with a number at position:",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are conditions that must be in place in order for mountain waves to form?\n1) The wind blows within 30° of a right angle to the mountain range2) The wind speed abeam the top of the mountain exceeds 20 kt3) The wind speed decreases with altitude but the direction remains fairly constant4) The atmosphere is unstable on the windward side of the mountain top",
    "feedback": "1 and 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "All pilots encountering Clear Air Turbulence are requested to report it. You experience CAT which causes passengers and crew to feel definite strain against their seat belt or shoulders straps. Unsecured objects are dislodged. Food service and walking are difficult. This intensity of CAT should be reported as",
    "feedback": "moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stability in a layer is increasing if",
    "feedback": "warm air is advected in the upper part and cold air in the lower part"
  },
  {
    "question": "Shortly after dawn, an inland aerodrome (Eindhoven, The Netherlands) reports the following METAR:\nEHEH 010610Z 33005KT 0300 R21/0450 FG NSC 06/06 Q1018 =\nConsidering the above METAR, we can say that the aerodrome is experiencing (1)...... which probably extends from the surface to (2).....",
    "feedback": "(1) radiation fog, (2) less than 300 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which information should always be delivered by ATIS?",
    "feedback": "Visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the TAF:\n\nFT LSZH 151425Z 1515/1621 VRB03KT 4000 BR SCT007 BKN028 TX05/1515Z TN02/1606Z TX11/1613Z TEMPO 1515/1524 BKN008 BECMG 1515/1518 RA BECMG 1521/1524 NSW SCT008 BKN015 BECMG 1609/1612 7000 SCT015=\n\nWhich is correct?",
    "feedback": "The forecasted maximum temperature is 11° C at 13 UTC on the 16th of the month"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an unstable layer there are cumuliform clouds. The vertical extent of these clouds depends on the",
    "feedback": "thickness of the unstable layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the source of tropical continental air that affects Europe in summer?",
    "feedback": "The southern Balkan region and the Near East."
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud formation is most likely to occur at low levels when a warm air mass overrides a cold air mass?",
    "feedback": "Nimbostratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the low level winds between the subtropical high pressure belt and the ITCZ?",
    "feedback": "Trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 850 hPa pressure level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "feedback": "FL 50"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the reason for issuing the following special air report?\nARS VA812 SEV TURB OBS AT 1210Z N2020W07005 12000FT",
    "feedback": "Severe turbulence observed at 12:10 UTC"
  },
  {
    "question": "Runway visual range can be reported in",
    "feedback": "a METAR"
  },
  {
    "question": "Judging by the chart, on which of these routes can you expect to encounter moderate CAT at FL 210?",
    "feedback": "Oslo - Paris"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather phenomena can indicate the presence of low-level windshear?",
    "feedback": "Virga"
  },
  {
    "question": "A SPECI is",
    "feedback": "an aviation selected special weather report"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Bordeaux to Amsterdam, ETA 2100 UTC. What is the minimum visibility forecast for ETA Amsterdam?\n\nTAF EHAM 281500Z 281601 14010KT 6000 -RA SCT025 BECMG 1618 12015G25KT SCT008 BKN013 TEMPO 1823 3000 RA BKN005 OVC010 BECMG 2301 25020KT 8000 NSW BKN020=",
    "feedback": "3 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "FL 110, an OAT -05°C is measured. What will the temperature be at FL 50, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "+7°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "The station pressure used in surface weather charts is",
    "feedback": "QFF"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight over the sea at FL135, the true altitude is 13500 feet, local QNH 1019 hPa. What information, if any, can be gained about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying?",
    "feedback": "It is colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "For the same horizontal distance between adjacent isobars the gradient wind speed will be least at:",
    "feedback": "50°N with a cyclonic circulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What conditions are most likely to prevail in winter at an aerodrome located in square 3B?",
    "feedback": "6 - 8 oktas SC and ST, visibility moderate to poor in drizzle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the correct statement regarding the transfer of heat in the atmosphere:",
    "feedback": "The air at the surface can be cooled or warmed by the process of conduction, which is the molecular transfer of heat between the surface and the air in contact with it"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which solution provides the most accurate description of the air mass at coordinates W (43°N 024°W)?",
    "feedback": "Rear of a warm front, in warm air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the strongest headwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a flight operating from Brussels to Paris, planned for the afternoon 2nd of July 2018, cruising at 6000 ft AMSL. What type of turbulence and icing can be expected?",
    "feedback": "Moderate icing and turbulence with clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cold-air drops.....",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "Thunderstorms have a great vertical extent and may form certain clouds. TS are associated with (1) ...... and their height may extend to (2) ......",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "Thunderstorms have a great vertical extent and may form certain clouds. TS are associated with (1) ...... and their height may extend to (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) Cumulonimbus, (2) the tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tropical maritime air moving into area B in spring will probably give:",
    "feedback": "Advection fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of these cloud types can icing be virtually ruled out?",
    "feedback": "CI"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather condition would you expect at a squall line?",
    "feedback": "Thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "A valley has filled with relatively cold air during the night, topped by an inversion. On the next day, a warm air mass is advected into the area of the valley at upper levels.\n\nWhich development has to be expected within the next few hours?",
    "feedback": "The inversion will become stronger"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a favourable synoptic situation for the development of a Scirocco?",
    "feedback": "Low pressure area in the western part of the Mediterranean Sea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming clear skies and minimal to no wind, what surface conditions are most conductive for the development of a radiation inversion?",
    "feedback": "Desert"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the theoretical development of the geostrophic wind in the Northern Hemisphere?",
    "feedback": "As the air starts to move and is accelerated by the pressure gradient force, it is increasingly deflected to the right by the Coriolis force until both forces are balanced and opposite to each other"
  },
  {
    "question": "What words must be used to complete the statement below? \nA wing, contaminated with ice, will typically stall at (1).... Angle of Attack (AOA) and at (2) ..... airspeed, with small amounts of ice having already an effect, whereby the effect (3) .... if the ice is rough.",
    "feedback": "1) a lower, 2) a higher, 3) is greater"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following 1850 UTC METAR reports, is the probability of fog formation, in the coming night, the highest?",
    "feedback": "VRB01KT 8000 SCT250 11/10 Q1028 BECMG 3000 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "A primary way for clouds to dissipate is by adiabatic (1) ...... of the air through (2) ..... .",
    "feedback": "(1) warming, (2) subsidence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the surface wind usually westerly in a Northern Hemisphere polar front depression?",
    "feedback": "In front of the cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is expected to clear terrain by 2000 ft. The elevation of the mountain is 6254 ft, local QNH at an airport of elevation 3100 ft is 991 hPa, ISA + 24°C.\nCalculate the flight level in order to clear the mountain range by the specified clearance.",
    "feedback": "FL085"
  },
  {
    "question": "With which of the following types of cloud is \"+RA\" precipitation most commonly associated?",
    "feedback": "NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "When is the RVR reported at most airports?",
    "feedback": "When the meteorological visibility decreases below 1500 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at 3000 ft indicated altitude with an outside air temperature of ISA + 20°C and with the QNH of 998 hPa set in the altimeter subscale, measured by a nearby airport at sea level.\nWhat is the approximate true altitude of the aircraft?",
    "feedback": "3240 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a 0°C isotherm layer at FL060 and NS at FL070: What is the lowest FL with severe icing hazard?",
    "feedback": "FL070"
  },
  {
    "question": "The map depicts tropopause heights in March. Which region and tropopause heights does this temperature profile correspond to?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "FL 110, an OAT -05°C is measured. What will the temperature be at FL 50, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "+7°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B at the flight level corresponding to the pressure surface of the constant pressure chart. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "The true altitude will be higher over B than over A"
  },
  {
    "question": "What lowest cloud conditions (oktas/ft) are forecast for 1900 UTC at HAMBURG (EDDH) ?",
    "feedback": "5 to 7 at 500"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cross-section of air mass and cloud presentation is applicable to the straight line A-B?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "In region E, the air tends to become or remain non-turbulent because it is absolutely (1) .... and the (2) ....",
    "feedback": "(1) stable, (2) ELR is lower than the SALR"
  },
  {
    "question": "Visibility is reduced by water droplets to 1200 metres. This is classified as:",
    "feedback": "Mist"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the METAR code the abbreviation VC indicates:",
    "feedback": "present weather within a range of between approximately 8 and 16 km of the aerodrome reference point"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ice crystals are often found in and around the anvil of a thunderstorm. If found in high densities at very low temperatures, what hazard to these ice crystals present to an aircraft?",
    "feedback": "The crystals can accumulate inside the engine, then break away, causing a sudden loss of thrust, especially at low power settings"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a VOLMET broadcast?",
    "feedback": "Provision, as appropriate, of current METAR, SPECI, TAF and SIGMET by means of continuous and repetitive voice broadcast."
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature at 10000 FT in the International Standard Atmosphere is :",
    "feedback": "-5°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Runway visual range can be reported in",
    "feedback": "a METAR"
  },
  {
    "question": "For the same horizontal distance between adjacent isobars the gradient wind speed will be least at:",
    "feedback": "50°N with a cyclonic circulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does a CB contain at moderate latitudes in summer?",
    "feedback": "A combination of ice crystals, water droplets and supercooled water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "Central Europe is situated in the zone of",
    "feedback": "mid-latitude climate"
  },
  {
    "question": "At high altitudes, the presence of ice crystals can pose which potential hazards to an aircraft?",
    "feedback": "Ice crystals may form inside the engine, caused by clouds containing supercooled water droplets, leading to surges or power loss."
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterizes a stationary front ?",
    "feedback": "The surface wind usually has its direction parallel to the front"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the optimum flight level between Shannon and Keflavik according to the significant weather chart?",
    "feedback": "FL 240"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the evening, the most common reason for the dissipation of land-based fair-weather cumulus clouds is:",
    "feedback": "Cooling of the surface which stops the convection and increases the stability of the air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the track shown at FL390, what is the forecast wind at position 20°W?",
    "feedback": "090°/45 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which position is the development of thunderstorms most likely, and what is the maximum height of the CB clouds?",
    "feedback": "Frankfurt, FL 220"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the northern hemisphere the gradient wind of a cyclonic pressure distribution is 350/24, over the sea the surface wind would approximate",
    "feedback": "340/20"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions is most likely to produce severe thunderstorms, severe low-level turbulence, heavy showers of rain, and hail?",
    "feedback": "A fast-moving cold front over warm land in the summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "By the time the front \"Z\" has passed point \"Q\", the surface wind will have:",
    "feedback": "veered and increased"
  },
  {
    "question": "The frontal picture represents the situation at 0600 UTC. What is the most applicable surface weather situation at 1200 UTC over Southern England at longitude 0°?",
    "feedback": "5 to 7 oktas of stratified clouds, basis 1500 ft/GND, SHRA, BR, winds veering from south to southwest"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather conditions are associated with the summer Monsoon on the Indian sub-continent?",
    "feedback": "Strong convective activity created by the moist onshore airflow that heats up from below as it encounters the warmer continental land mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct combination of statements regarding to occlusions in Western Europe:\n1) Warm occlusions are most common in summer2) Warm occlusions are most common in winter3) Cold occlusions are most common in summer4) Cold occlusions are most common in winter",
    "feedback": "2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which of these routes would you not have to worry about turbulence at FL 340?",
    "feedback": "Shannon - Hamburg"
  },
  {
    "question": "Read the following SIGMET:\nEGJJ SIGMET 03 VALID 2291130/291530 EGJJ-\nLOC SEV TURB AND WS FCST BLW 3000FT OVER THE CHANNEL ISLANDS AREA INTSF=\n\nWhich statement about this SIGMET is best?",
    "feedback": "Over the Channel Islands area severe turbulence and wind shear are forecasted which will increase during the forecast period"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average wind for the route Athens - Geneva at FL 160.",
    "feedback": "240/40"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following causes echoes on meteorological radar screens?",
    "feedback": "Hail"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"R\" is",
    "feedback": "fine and warm at first - AC Castellanus and CB in late afternoon with thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the four radio soundings, select the one that indicates ground fog:",
    "feedback": "b)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The track of an aircraft passes over a mountain range, which has a maximum elevation of 4920 ft. Given that the correct QNH is set and the ambient temperature is ISA -10°C, what is the minimum altitude required to achieve a terrain clearance of 1000 ft?",
    "feedback": "6160 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the meteorological prerequisites, at low level, for thunderstorms formed by lifting processes, over land?",
    "feedback": "High temperatures, high humidity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement best describes the frontal activity around the red cross in the diagram?",
    "feedback": "To the West, a warm front moving northwards, to the East, a cold front moving southwards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: State the average wind for the route Frankfurt-Rome, FL 170:",
    "feedback": "23040KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "You must make an emergency landing at sea. The QNH of a field on a nearby island with an elevation of 4000 FT is 1025 hPa and the temperature is -20°C. What is your pressure altimeter reading when landing if 1025 hPa is set in the subscale?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "Less than 0 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following messages should be cancelled when the conditions are no longer occurring or no longer expected to occur?",
    "feedback": "Aerodrome warning"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft has to fly over a 14200 ft mountain chain with a minimum clearance of 2000 ft. The temperature measured at a meteorological station situated at 6500 ft is -23°C and the QNH is 1013 hPa.\nWhat altitude should the altimeter indicate?",
    "feedback": "17200 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the displayed cloud forms is representative of a cumulonimbus capillatus?",
    "feedback": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the best approximation for the wind speed at flight level 250?",
    "feedback": "By interpolation of the wind information available from the 500 and 300 hPa charts, while also considering the maximum wind information found on the Significant Weather Chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which conditions or factors determine the type of an air mass according to the classifications used by the weather services?",
    "feedback": "The latitude and the surface characteristics of the original area"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the weather conditions illustrated?",
    "feedback": "FG"
  },
  {
    "question": "In summer, when wind is calm and sky is clear, the minimum temperature over land is reached approximately",
    "feedback": "half an hour after sunrise"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what flight level is the jet stream core that is situated over Ireland?",
    "feedback": "FL 370"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about warm occlusions is true?",
    "feedback": "A warm occlusion is a combination of a warm- and a cold front. At the surface, it resembles a warm front, with embedded CBs. The precipitation falls ahead of the surface position of the front"
  },
  {
    "question": "A zone of strong convection currents is encountered during a flight. In spite of moderate gust you decide to continue the flight. What are your precautionary measures?",
    "feedback": "Decrease the speed / try to climb above the zone of convective currents if aircraft performance parameters allow."
  },
  {
    "question": "Mountain-wave airflow is commonly characterised by the fact that it .....",
    "feedback": "has an oscillating motion on the leeward side of the mountain range"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the lapse rates listed below, the air is absolutely stable when 1) Dry Adiabatic Lapse Rate DALR 2) Saturated Adiabatic Lapse Rate SALR and 3) Environmental Lapse Rate ELR:",
    "feedback": "ELR < SALR and DALR"
  },
  {
    "question": "How, if at all, is the relative humidity of an unsaturated airmass influenced by temperature changes?",
    "feedback": "It decreases with increasing temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Bordeaux to Berlin at FL 180. What can be expected at cruising level?",
    "feedback": "Moderate icing about half way along the route and moderate turbulence second part of the route."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is flying at a pressure altitude of 10000 ft, its altimeter indicates 9500 ft. The temperature is ISA -10°C and the altimeter has no instrument error.\nWhat is the true altitude?",
    "feedback": "9120 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What altitude does the altimeter show in the resetting procedure while at the transition level?\nTransition level: FL190Transition Altitude: 18000 ftQNH: 989 hPa\n(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "18280 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the lower part of the stratosphere the temperature",
    "feedback": "is almost constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which layer of the atmosphere contains more than 90 % of the total amount of water vapour?",
    "feedback": "Troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the lowest headwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 300 hPa pressure level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "feedback": "FL 300"
  },
  {
    "question": "For your flight from Zurich to Rome you consult, amongst other information, the following SIGMET:\n\nSIGMET VALID121420/121820 MOD TO SEV CAT OBS AND FCST S OF ALPS BTN FL 260 AND FL 380 / STNR / INTSF  =",
    "feedback": "You select a flight level below FL 260 due to turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Advection is :",
    "feedback": "horizontal motion of air"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot flying VFR at low level encounters an unexpected wind change exceeding 30 knots, which was not included in the low level forecasts. What type of advisory would be issued by a meteorological watch office?",
    "feedback": "AIRMET or ARS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Polar air outbreaks are depressions that can affect (1) ..... during the (2) .....",
    "feedback": "(1) central and northern China, (2) wintertime"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what time of day, or night, is radiation fog most likely to occur?",
    "feedback": "Shortly after sunrise."
  },
  {
    "question": "The mean height of the tropical tropopause is",
    "feedback": "54000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to temperature, which of the following is correct for the polar climates?",
    "feedback": "The mean temperature of all months is below plus 10°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "A cloud layer (1) ..... solar radiation leading to cooler maximum surface temperatures during the day. At night, clouds (2) ..... terrestrial (3) ..... radiation and re-radiate it back towards the surface.",
    "feedback": "(1) reflects, (2) absorb, (3) infrared"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the lowest visibility forecast for Birmingham at 280800Z?",
    "feedback": "5000 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather reports  is a warning of conditions that could be potentially hazardous to aircraft in flight ?",
    "feedback": "SIGMET."
  },
  {
    "question": "A polar front depression is approaching Western Europe over the Atlantic Ocean during winter. In terms of the air masses surrounding the depression:\n1) The warm sector will contain (1) ...... air2) The air to the east of the depression will be (2) ...... air3) The air to the west of the depression will be (3) ...... air4) The air north of the depression may be (4) ...... air",
    "feedback": "(1) tropical, (2) polar, (3) polar, (4) arctic"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characteristic is associated with a temperature inversion ?",
    "feedback": "Stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "If Paris reports a wind of 30012KT on the METAR, what wind velocity would you expect to encounter at a height of 2000 feet above the ground ?",
    "feedback": "33025KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the altitude of the condensation level, when an air pacel is lifted from MSL to 20000 ft. Static air temperature at MSL + 20°C, dew point at MSL -5°C. \nGiven:\nBrown dashed line: Constant saturation mixing ratioGreen line: Dry adiabaticMagenta line: Saturated adiabatic",
    "feedback": "10000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A moist, stable layer of air is forced to rise against a mountain range and the stability does not change. Which of the following phenomena may develop?",
    "feedback": "Stratified clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sea breezes are most likely to occur when",
    "feedback": "slack pressure gradient and clear skies result in relatively high land temperatures"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a flight operating from Zone D and expected to end in Zone A, planned for the afternoon of 26th July 2017, flying at 3000 ft AMSL. \nWhat conditions can you expect at cruising altitude?",
    "feedback": "Mainly in clouds, moderate turbulence expected within clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would the term \"vertical visibility is missing or not measurable\" be indicated in a METAR?",
    "feedback": "VV///"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a correct description of the weather situation at the slopes of the mountains in Northern Spain, when the wind comes from the north?",
    "feedback": "As the air moves upslope, it cools, and orographic fog will develop as soon as the dew point ins reached"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the track shown at FL390, what is the forecast wind at position 20°W?",
    "feedback": "090°/45 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Amongst others, what has to be expected when a cold and moist air mass covers a warm surface?",
    "feedback": "Instability of air layers near the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the following TAF extract: BECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 BECMG 2124 0500 FG VV001 What does the abbreviation \"BKN004\" mean?",
    "feedback": "5 - 7 oktas, ceiling 400 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "Vertical wind shear is",
    "feedback": "vertical variation in the horizontal wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a cause of stratus forming over flat land?",
    "feedback": "Radiation during the night from the earth surface in moderate wind."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the wind direction and speed at 3 000 FT overhead position \"Q\" at 0600 UTC?",
    "feedback": "270° 30 kt."
  },
  {
    "question": "Imagine an airfield during summer with sunny days and clear nights and with a runway parallel to the shoreline of a large inland lake 5 nautical miles away from the field.\nA small aircraft heading for the airfield in the afternoon experiences wind shear during approach and a cross wind component which makes landing difficult.\n\nThe origin of the wind shear and cross wind is most likely to be seen in",
    "feedback": "a strong sea breeze blowing more or less perpendicular to the runway."
  },
  {
    "question": "A cumulonimbus cloud at mid-latitudes in summer contains",
    "feedback": "a combination of ice crystals, water droplets and supercooled water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at FL 300 where the outside air temperature is -57.5°C and the pressure at MSL is 1013.25 hPa. If you assume that the difference between the actual temperature and the temperature in the ISA is valid for the whole troposphere, then the true altitude is",
    "feedback": "28500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following cloud types is found at high levels?",
    "feedback": "CI"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what way can the air temperature affect the dew point temperature?",
    "feedback": "When the air temperature falls below the dew point at a constant pressure in the atmosphere, the dew point also reduces"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of fog is likely to form when air having temperature of 15°C and dew point of 12°C blows at 10 knots over a sea surface having temperatures of 5°C ?",
    "feedback": "Advection fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of fronts are most likely to be present during the winter in Central Europe when temperatures close to the ground are below 0°C, and freezing rain starts to fall?",
    "feedback": "Warm fronts, warm occlusions."
  },
  {
    "question": "What minimum visibility is forecast for 0600 UTC at LONDON LHR (EGLL)?",
    "feedback": "1500 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the height of the lowest cloud forecast for Bangkok at ETA 1400 UTC ?\nTAF VTBD 271800Z 280024 VRB05KT 1200 BR TEMPO 0002 4000 BECMG 0205 9999 NSW SCT015 BKN100 TEMPO 1118 04010G20KT 5000 TSRA SCT009 BKN014 BKN018CB BECMG 2024 6000=",
    "feedback": "900 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about mixed or cloudy ice is correct?",
    "feedback": "It forms between the ideal conditions for clear ice and rime ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO, which symbol indicates danger to an aircraft in flight?",
    "feedback": "Symbols c) and d)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Favourable conditions for development of subsidence inversions in the Northern Hemisphere are common over .....",
    "feedback": "the northern continents in winter and over the subtropical oceans"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pressure altitude is equal to the true altitude if",
    "feedback": "standard atmospheric conditions occur"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements regarding an aircraft being struck by lightning is true?",
    "feedback": "The flight crew might have temporary difficulties in determining the current attitude of flight."
  },
  {
    "question": "The symbol at 16°N 083°E indicates a....",
    "feedback": "cyclone"
  },
  {
    "question": "The height of the tropopause at 38°N 19°W is:",
    "feedback": "FL320"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena has to be mentioned in a SIGMET?",
    "feedback": "Volcanic ash."
  },
  {
    "question": "When is it most probable to encounter severe weather in the form of thunderstorms, heavy rain, and severe turbulence over the eastern parts of India?",
    "feedback": "From July to August"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at an altitude of 8500 ft with a QNH of 1030 hPa set in the altimeter subscale.\nAlong the route the mean sea level pressure decreases and the local QNH is now 1000 hPa. Calculate the true altitude, if the altimeter setting remains unchanged.\nAssume a uniform vertical pressure variation at 30 ft per 1 hPa and Standard temperature",
    "feedback": "7600 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would you characterise an air temperature of -55°C at the 200 hPa level over western Europe?",
    "feedback": "Within +/-5°C of ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is flying in the lower stratosphere. Which of the following statements is correct regarding the general conditions in that area?",
    "feedback": "The air in the lower stratosphere is very dry, therefore, there are very few clouds in the stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what flight level is the jet stream core that is situated over Ireland?",
    "feedback": "FL 370"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are planning a flight at FL 170, which of these upper wind and temperature charts would be nearest your flight level ?",
    "feedback": "500 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of grid does the Numerical Weather Prediction (NWP) use?",
    "feedback": "3D Grid"
  },
  {
    "question": "An operator is planning a new regular route into an airport that will be affected by the ITCZ at certain times of the year. Which of the following hazards associated with the ITCZ should be considered in crew training?",
    "feedback": "Severe thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "In summer, when wind is calm and sky is clear, the minimum temperature over land is reached approximately",
    "feedback": "half an hour after sunrise"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements is true?",
    "feedback": "Scattered thunderstorms can be expected over France"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the temperature decrease in the ISA?",
    "feedback": "0,65°C/100 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "A layer of stratus is most likely to be dispersed by",
    "feedback": "insolation resulting in the lifting of the condensation level"
  },
  {
    "question": "A small supercooled cloud droplet that collides with an airfoil will most likely",
    "feedback": "freeze immediately and create rime ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "In maritime tropical air in mid-latitudes:",
    "feedback": "showers may develop over land areas during the summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which altitude, at temperate latitudes, may hail be expected in connection with a CB?",
    "feedback": "From the ground up to a maximum of FL 450."
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud genera is depicted on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Altostratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure.\nOne of the cross-sections illustrated at the left hand side and one of the vertical pressure structures on the right hand side correspond to a warm occlusion:",
    "feedback": "Figures 4 and 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "The SW monsoon forms in the latitude band indicated by the letter (1) ..... from (2) ..... and it brings (3) .....",
    "feedback": "(1) V, (2) April to October, (3) thunderstorms with heavy rain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are high level clouds? State the most complete answer:",
    "feedback": "CI, CC"
  },
  {
    "question": "The approach altitude is 6000 ft and the approach chart stipulates that the altitude must be temperature corrected below 0°C. The surface temperature is -5°C.\nTo ensure that the aircraft is 6000 ft above MSL (True Altitude), what indication should be read on the altitmeter when the QNH is correctly set?",
    "feedback": "6480 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What lowest cloud conditions (oktas/ft) are forecast for 1900 UTC at HAMBURG (EDDH) ?",
    "feedback": "5 to 7 at 500"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following answers is true about clear icing?",
    "feedback": "During the freezing process latent heat is released which delays the freezing of the remaining liquid part of the droplet and makes it easier for it to flow back on the wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "An area where rain ice (FZRA) is likely to be encountered must be avoided. An example of such area would be when flying:",
    "feedback": "ahead of a warm front with the OAT gauge reading -5°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following cloud types is least likely to produce precipitation ?",
    "feedback": "CI"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rime ice forms through the freezing onto aircraft surfaces of",
    "feedback": "small supercooled water drops."
  },
  {
    "question": "These four elements have been removed from the tropical cyclone advisory extract below: INTSF, JACQUES, 976HPA, NADI\nTC ADVISORYDTG: 20130712/1900ZTCAC: (1) ..................TC: (2) ..................TC Advisory NR: 2013/6OBS PSN: 12/1800Z N2706 W07306CB: W1 120NM OF TC CENTRE TOP FL450MOV: SE 35 KMHINTST CHANGE: (3) ....................C: (4) ........................MAX WIND: 30MPS\nThe correct sequence is:",
    "feedback": "(1) NADI, (2) JACQUES, (3) INTSF, (4) 976 HPA"
  },
  {
    "question": "The value of the saturated adiabatic lapse rate is closest to that of the dry adiabatic lapse rate in",
    "feedback": "cirrus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is most likely to lead to the formation of radiation fog?",
    "feedback": "Heat loss from the ground on clear nights"
  },
  {
    "question": "Amongst others, what has to be expected when a warm air mass covers a cold surface?",
    "feedback": "Development of stratiform clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "With an intense trough of low pressure over Iceland during wintertime the weather likely to be experienced is :",
    "feedback": "strong wind shear, convection and snow showers"
  },
  {
    "question": "With decreasing temperature and unchanged dew point:",
    "feedback": "The relative humidity will increase."
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass affecting position \"C\" is most likely to be",
    "feedback": "Maritime tropical"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which weather report would you expect to find information about icing conditions on the runway?",
    "feedback": "METAR"
  },
  {
    "question": "The sinking of air is favoured",
    "feedback": "in a high pressure area"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cloud base, reported in the METAR, is the height above",
    "feedback": "airfield level"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following best describes Zone D?",
    "feedback": "Depression"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following contribute the most to the process of coalescence?\n1) Water droplets colliding with each other2) Cumulonimbus clouds3) Stratiform clouds4) Convection5) Pressure difference between ice and water droplets6) Pressure difference between water droplets",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cold front accompanied by severe thunderstorms, heavy rain, hail, and violent gusts has just passed overhead at the airport. According to the SWC, the front is moving at 35 kt perpendicular to its orientation. In approximately how long should the worst conditions have moved past the airport?",
    "feedback": "1 to 3 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check these statements for correctness:\n\n1) Advecion of warm air over a cold surface is an adiabatic process\n2) A temperature change induced through rising or sinking air is an adiabatic process",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Due to a windshear event during an approach to land, the headwind component suddenly increases just before the flare. If the pilot does not take appropriate action, this could lead to...",
    "feedback": "the aircraft \"ballooning\" and landing beyond the touchdown aiming point, increasing the possibility of a runway excursion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Orographic thunderstorms may occur:",
    "feedback": "at any time during day and night."
  },
  {
    "question": "During the pre-flight briefing for a flight in Spain during summer, a pilot observes on the surface analysis chart an intense small-scale low pressure system at the surface, situated along the route. It will be associated with ....",
    "feedback": "clear sky, good visibility, and turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following causes echoes on meteorological radar screens?",
    "feedback": "Hail"
  },
  {
    "question": "Absolute instability in the atmosphere will occur when the environmental lapse rate is",
    "feedback": "greater than both saturated adiabatic lapse rate and dry adiabatic lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "In still air the temperature decreases at an average of 1.2°C per 100 m increase in altitude. This temperature change is called:",
    "feedback": "environmental lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pressure system at position \"b\" is a",
    "feedback": "col"
  },
  {
    "question": "QNH is defined as",
    "feedback": "QFE reduced to MSL using the values of the standard atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 200, OAT = ISA +10°C. The QNH, given by a meteorological station with an elevation of 1000 ft is 1010 hPa. Use 1hPa = 30 ft.  Calculate the True Altitude (rounded to 100 ft)",
    "feedback": "20700 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "With which meteorological phenomena are wind shear conditions mostly associated?",
    "feedback": "Gust fronts; low level temperature inversions; frontal surfaces"
  },
  {
    "question": "Clear air turbulence can be expected when an aeroplane or helicopter route is ....",
    "feedback": "along the leeside of a mountain ridge"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather reports could be, in accordance with the regulations, abbreviated to \"CAVOK\"? (MSA minus airport elevation equals: LSZB 10000 FT, LSZH 8000 FT, LSGG 12000 FT, LFSB 6000 FT)",
    "feedback": "LSZB 28012KT 9999 OVC100 16/12 Q1012 BECMG 5000 -RA ="
  },
  {
    "question": "Which typical weather situation over Central Europe is shown on the weather chart? (spacing of the isobars: 5 hPa)",
    "feedback": "Flat pressure pattern."
  },
  {
    "question": "When a given mass of air  descends, what effect will it have on relative humidity?",
    "feedback": "It decreases."
  },
  {
    "question": "On the European continent METARs of main airports are compiled and distributed with intervals of",
    "feedback": "0.5 hour"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a similar pressure gradient, the geostrophic wind speed will be",
    "feedback": "greater at 30°N than at 60°N"
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum vapour pressure over a flat supercooled water surface and the maximum vapour pressure over a flat ice surface of the same temperature are compared. The maximum vapour pressure is",
    "feedback": "greater over the water surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "For the same horizontal distance between adjacent isobars the gradient wind speed will be least at:",
    "feedback": "50°N with a cyclonic circulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The presence of standing lenticular AC clouds is a good indication of:",
    "feedback": "Updrafts and downdrafts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which figure best illustrates the vertical cross-section and the average slope of a cold front?",
    "feedback": "Figure 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Referring to the significant weather chart, what hazards are to be expected above Perth (32°S 116'E)?",
    "feedback": "No significant flight hazards, as there is only a jet stream visible over Perth"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. \nA flight is planned to take off from the marked aerodrome at 10:00UTC on Tuesday 23rd April. Consider the METAR, issued on the 22nd April:\n222100Z 26010KT 9999 BKN015 Q0995\nWhich of the following options is most probable in the morning of the flight?",
    "feedback": "A depression is forming on the front to the west and cloud and rain can be expected as it develops"
  },
  {
    "question": "Just before a flight at FL330 over an area where a volcano is active, a pilot checks if it is safe to fly. What meteorological message should the pilot use to check if the volcano has erupted and set volcanic ash into high flight levels?",
    "feedback": "SIGMET"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following constant pressure charts would be most relevant for planning a flight at FL 260?",
    "feedback": "400 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "At altitude, the atmospheric pressure in a column of warm air is likely to be...",
    "feedback": "higher than at the same height in a column of cold air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight visibility from the cockpit during approach in a tropical downpour can decrease to minimal",
    "feedback": "tens of metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which temperature range does rime ice most commonly occur in NS clouds?",
    "feedback": "-10°C to -30°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What typically happens to a cold high, aloft in the troposphere?",
    "feedback": "It decreases with height"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass type advected from a direction indicated by arrow number 6 is designated",
    "feedback": "maritime polar"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate average wind direction at FL180 over the Alps in the boxed area shown on the chart?",
    "feedback": "105°(T)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What conditions are most likely to prevail in winter at an aerodrome located in square 3B?",
    "feedback": "6 - 8 oktas SC and ST, visibility moderate to poor in drizzle"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an ascending unsaturated parcel of air:",
    "feedback": "the relative humidity increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the Köppen Climatology model, which climatic type is being described in the following statement?\nDuring summer (anticyclonic warm and dry air, cloudless skies. During winter with frontal depressions, cloudy with frequent precipitation, windy and cool conditions",
    "feedback": "Warm"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying through a region where the transition altitude is 6000 feet, ATC reports a transition level of FL055 and a QNH of 1042 hPa. What is the approximate reading expected on the altimeter, if the pilot changes the altimeter subscale setting to the QNH when descending through the transition level?",
    "feedback": "6370 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the correct statement regarding the transfer of heat in the atmosphere:",
    "feedback": "The air at the surface can be cooled or warmed by the process of conduction, which is the molecular transfer of heat between the surface and the air in contact with it"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the cloud genera shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Altocumulus castellanus"
  },
  {
    "question": "The crew of a flight to a North African destination is about to commence its descent. The current METAR reports moderate to heavy gusty winds, moderate sandstorm, and sky obscured. What should the crew expect to happen to the visibility?",
    "feedback": "It varies between 200 metres and 600 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather is clear and the temperature decreases uniformly and rapidly as you climb (approaching 3.2°C per  1000 ft), you have an indication of:",
    "feedback": "Unstable air."
  },
  {
    "question": "OMDB FT 1000 1212/1312 33015KT 9999 SCT030 BKN090 TEMPO 1212/1309 SHRA PROB40 TEMPO 1214/1224 VRB40KT 1000 TSSS SCT025CB BECMG 1216/1218 05010KT BECMG 1306/1308 33013G23KT=\n\nWhat is the earliest time (UTC), if any, that thunderstorms are forecast for DUBAI (MDB) ?",
    "feedback": "1400"
  },
  {
    "question": "An anticyclone is a weather phenomenon characterised by a large-scale circulation of winds around a central region of...",
    "feedback": "high atmospheric pressure, rotating clockwise in the northern hemisphere, counter-clockwise in the southern hemisphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind vector above London (51°N 000°E) at FL 330 is:",
    "feedback": "300°/140 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is true of the temperature at the tropopause?",
    "feedback": "It is higher in polar regions than in equatorial regions"
  },
  {
    "question": "refer to the picture.\nWhat type of front is to be found at position X?",
    "feedback": "Occluded cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "A plain in Western Europe with an average height of 500 m (1600 FT) above sea level is covered with a uniform SC layer of cloud during the summer months. At what height above the ground is the base of this cloud to be expected?",
    "feedback": "1500 - 7000 FT above ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: On which airport do you expect the development of the following weather situation?\nTAF 231200Z 231322 24014G32KT 4000 +TSRA SCT005 BKN015 BKN020CB BECMG 1416 29012KT 9999 BKN030TCU SCT100 TEMPO 8000 SHRA BKN025TCU BECMG 1922 27012KT 9999 SCT030 OVC220 =",
    "feedback": "EINN"
  },
  {
    "question": "Immediately following a long flight at high altitude, what phenomenon may be observed to form on the wings after landing, despite clear and mild weather with no precipitation or visible moisture in or around the airport?",
    "feedback": "Hoar frost forming around the fuel tanks due to cold-soaked wings"
  },
  {
    "question": "The synoptic chart depicts a region in the Southern Hemisphere. Which air mass is located at position L?",
    "feedback": "Cold air ahead of a warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of front is to be found at position V?",
    "feedback": "Stationary front"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight over the sea at FL135, the true altitude is 13500 feet, local QNH 1019 hPa. What information, if any, can be gained about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying?",
    "feedback": "It is colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Before landing, an altimeter set to QFE indicates",
    "feedback": "in standard atmosphere, the height of the aircraft above the official airport elevation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Read the following METAR for station XXXX:\n\nXXXX 301230Z VRB02KT 0900 R36/1100VP1500D FZFG OVC001 M02/M02 Q1029 BECMG 1500 BR OVC002=\n\nWhich statement about visibility and RVR is correct?",
    "feedback": "Prevailing visibility is 900 m, RVR has detoriated in the last 10 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about steam fog are correct or incorrect?\n1) Steam fog is formed in air with cold air mass properties\n2) Steam fog is formed only in windless conditions",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is true ?",
    "feedback": "QNH can be lower as well as higher than 1013.25 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct about the influence of a ground inversion on the formation of fog?",
    "feedback": "In the ground inversion the air closest to the ground is coldest, due to radiation, and it is stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following changes of state is known as sublimation (in meteorology)?",
    "feedback": "Solid direct to vapour"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rising air cools because",
    "feedback": "it expands"
  },
  {
    "question": "The front at the bottom of the diagram, south of position C, is",
    "feedback": "an occlusion on the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "The image on a modern airborne weather radar (AWR) shows a hook shape. What can be concluded?",
    "feedback": "The image is a hint to the presence of a severe storm"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does cold air advection affect the true vertical distance between flight levels?",
    "feedback": "The advection of cold air means advection of denser air, thus the distance between the flight levels is reduced"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. \nAccording to the following VOLMET broadcast, what is the relative wind direction for runway 34?\nWIND 350 DEGREES 12 KNOTS VISIBILITY 8 KILOMETRES LIGHT RAIN CLOUD BROKEN 8 HUNDRED FEET OVERCAST 1 THOUSAND FEET TEMPERATURE 06 DEW POINT 04 QNH 998",
    "feedback": "30° from the right"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under what condition does pressure altitude have the same value as density altitude ?",
    "feedback": "At standard temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the four radio soundings corresponds with \"OVC015\"?",
    "feedback": "C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of turbulence is dependent on the sun's radiation and therefore follows a pronounced diurnal pattern?",
    "feedback": "Convective turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which cloud type does moderate to severe airframe icing most probably occur?",
    "feedback": "NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew preparing to depart from Phuket Airport (VTSP) in Thailand on the 30th October receives the following message:\nVTSP CNL AD WRNG 2 300100/300300\nWhat is the purpose of this message?",
    "feedback": "To cancel aerodrome warning number 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at 3000 ft in a layer of stratocumulus cloud and experiences light icing. This icing intensifies as the aircraft crosses a mountain barrier whilst still in the cloud. This may be explained by...",
    "feedback": "orographic intensification as the air is forced to rise over the mountain barrier"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft follows the flight plan, cruising at FL140 within clouds, which leads over a mountain range, followed by flat areas and then crosses an area of open sea. Over which area do you expect airframe icing to be most intense?",
    "feedback": "Over the mountain range, as this causes upward air motion on the windward side, forcing large supercooled water droplets to rise above the freezing level"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over Paris at what height would you expect to find the tropopause according to the map?",
    "feedback": "approx.30000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what levels does icing predominantly form in a CB cloud?",
    "feedback": "Predominantly in the middle section of the CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "Air moving over or around large ground obstacles such as mountains can create turbulence in the lee of the terrain feature, which:",
    "feedback": "May produce violent and, for smaller aircraft, potentially uncontrollable effects resulting in pitch and/or roll to extreme positions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which degree of aircraft turbulence is determined by the following ICAO description?\n\"Conditions in which abrupt changes in aircraft attitude and/or altitude occur; aircraft may be out of control for short periods. Usually, large variations in air speed. Changes in accelerometer readings greater than 1.0 g at the aircraft's centre of gravity. Occupants are forced violently against seat belts. Loose objects are tossed about.\"",
    "feedback": "Severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "What mean temperature (°C) is likely on a course of 360° (T) from 40°N to 50°N at 040°E ?",
    "feedback": "-47"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying from Brest to Bergen, close to the surface, a pilot will most probably experience ....",
    "feedback": "increasing tailwind"
  },
  {
    "question": "What wind is forecast at FL 390 over Paris ?",
    "feedback": "210/40"
  },
  {
    "question": "Thunderstorms have a great vertical extent and may form certain clouds. TS are associated with (1) ...... and their height may extend to (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) Cumulonimbus, (2) the tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "This chart shows the weather conditions on the ground at 0600 UTC on May 23. Which of the following reports reflects weather development at Geneva Airport?",
    "feedback": "TAF LSGG 230716 23016KT 8000 -RA BKN030 OVC070 BECMG 0810 5000 RA BKN020 OVC050 TEMPO 3000 +RA BKN010 OVC030 BECMG 1215 25014KT 8000 SCT030 BKN090 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "A gustfront is",
    "feedback": "formed by the cold air outflow from a thunderstorm"
  },
  {
    "question": "With what type of cloud is \"DZ\" precipitation most commonly associated?",
    "feedback": "ST"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements regarding the intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ) is correct?",
    "feedback": "Frequent and widespread thunderstorms are to be expected within the area of the ITCZ."
  },
  {
    "question": "In the northern hemisphere, during periods of prolonged clear skies associated with anticyclonic conditions, the",
    "feedback": "surface wind speed tends to be highest during the early afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature at FL 340 overhead Copenhagen will be",
    "feedback": "-48°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sea smoke may drift onto land and affect coastal aerodromes. It forms when....",
    "feedback": "evaporated vapour from a warm water surface condenses on contact with much colder air, and is unable to rise because of a surface inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What temperature does an observer at point B encounter in the next hour?",
    "feedback": "No substantial temperature change"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from A to B (indicated on the chart) at 9000 ft altitude. After crossing the second cold front (approximately halfway to B), the wind speed is expected to (1) .... and the wind direction is expected to be (2) .....",
    "feedback": "(1) increase; (2) southwesterly"
  },
  {
    "question": "The isohypse 1620 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "feedback": "850 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main factor which contributes to the formation of very low clouds ahead of a warm front is the",
    "feedback": "saturation of the cold air by rain falling into it and evaporating"
  },
  {
    "question": "The subscale of an altimeter is set to 1013 hPa. The aircraft has to land on a point with an elevation of 390 feet where the QNH is 1023 hPa.\nThe reading on the altimeter on the ground will be:",
    "feedback": "90 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is \"mixing ratio\"?",
    "feedback": "The number of grammes of water vapour per kilogramme of dry air."
  },
  {
    "question": "What terms/values must be inserted below?\nThunderstorms form when an air mass becomes so unstable that it convects violently. Under these conditions pockets of near-surface air can form into a (1) ..... cloud, which may reach a height of up to (2) ..... .",
    "feedback": "(1) Cumulonimbus cloud, (2) 20 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "A frontal depression is developing over Sweden, and the synoptic chart represents conditions at 12:00 UTC. By 16:00 UTC, which synoptic chart and corresponding cross-sectional diagram would most likely depict the situation?",
    "feedback": "Map Z, Diagram 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at 2600 ft with the altimeter set to 1000 hPa (QNH of a nearby airfield at 600 ft). The air mass at the airfield is on average 8°C colder than standard. What is the true altitude over the field?",
    "feedback": "2540 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"Q\" is",
    "feedback": "showery with generally good visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average wind forecast for FL 300 between Edinburgh and Madrid?",
    "feedback": "280/30"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions is most likely to lead to the formation of steam fog (arctic smoke)?",
    "feedback": "Cold air moving over warm water"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an unsaturated layer in the friction layer the air is well mixed by turbulence. The layer remains unsaturated. After some time the vertical temperature profile will",
    "feedback": "correspond to the dry adiabatic lapse rate."
  },
  {
    "question": "The vertical extent of the friction layer depends primarily on",
    "feedback": "stability, wind speed, roughness of surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under the weather conditions depicted, which of the following statements is likely to apply?",
    "feedback": "Thunderstorms may occur in the summer months over Central Europe."
  },
  {
    "question": "Define the tropopause:",
    "feedback": "That area where the temperature change does not exceed two-thirds of one degree Celsius per thousand foot increase in altitude over a range of 6000 feet."
  },
  {
    "question": "What surface wind is forecast for ETA 1700 UTC at Kingston?\nMKJP 160430Z 160606 36010KT 9999 FEW025CB BECMG1315 14020G34KT FEW015CB SCT025 PROB30 TEMPO 1720 2500 +SHRA SCT010 BKN015CB BECMG 2301 34010KT FEW025=",
    "feedback": "140° / 20 kt gusts 34 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dew point is defined as the.....",
    "feedback": "temperature at which the vapour present in a sample of air would just cause saturation"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO, vertical visibility should be reported:\n1) when expressed in feet, in steps of 100 ft up to 2000 ft2) when expressed in metres, in steps of 30 m up to 600 m",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "You may expect a Mistral wind under the following conditions:",
    "feedback": "Strong surface winds blowing across or along a river valley"
  },
  {
    "question": "Depressions associated with developing frontal waves can be assumed to move in the direction of the 3000 feet wind",
    "feedback": "in the warm sector"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct for an absolutely unstable atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "Visibility is good between showers"
  },
  {
    "question": "You plan a flight over a mountain range at a true altitude of 15000 FT/AMSL. The air is on an average 15°C colder than ISA, the pressure at sea level is 1003 hPa. What indication must the altimeter (setting 1013.2 hPa) read? (barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "16200 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Carburettor icing may be expected to occur in clear air in the following conditions:",
    "feedback": "Outside air temperature +2°C, relative humidity 90%"
  },
  {
    "question": "The arrows labelled \"s\" represent the mean tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "feedback": "May to November and are called cyclones"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flying from Oslo Gardermoen Airport ENGM, Norway, to Stockholm Arlanda Airport ESSA, Sweden, encounters a squall line and can not avoid flying through the cumulonimbus and towering cumulus clouds.\nAt what levels would the aircraft most likely encounter heavy clear icing on the airframe?",
    "feedback": "The levels where the temperature is between 0°C and -10°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the typical weather conditions in a warm anticyclone over land?",
    "feedback": "Fine weather dominates in summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct regarding the International Standard Atmosphere ?",
    "feedback": "At MSL temperature is 15°C and pressure is 1013.25hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air mass is forced to ascend due to",
    "feedback": "lifting at fronts"
  },
  {
    "question": "The main constituents of the atmosphere are:",
    "feedback": "Nitrogen, Oxygen, Carbon Dioxide, Argon."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: State the height of the -40°C isotherm over Stockholm:",
    "feedback": "FL 230"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is an easterly wave identifiable on a surface weather chart?",
    "feedback": "As a weak trough"
  },
  {
    "question": "High clouds are normally composed of",
    "feedback": "Ice crystals."
  },
  {
    "question": "8/8 stratus base 200 FT/AGL is observed at sunrise at an aerodrome in the north of France; the QNH is 1028 hPa and there is a variable wind of 3 kt.\nWhat change in these clouds is likely at 12:00 UTC in summer and winter?",
    "feedback": "Winter: OVC base 500 FT/AGL; summer SCT base 3000 FT/AGL."
  },
  {
    "question": "The QNH is equal to the QFE if",
    "feedback": "the elevation = 0"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the meanings of the meteorological abbreviations SQ, BR, MIFG and SG respectively?",
    "feedback": "Sudden increase in wind speed lasting for at least one minute / mist / shallow fog / snowgrains"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: State the average wind for the route Zurich-Hamburg, FL 260:",
    "feedback": "23020KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 700 hPa pressure level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "feedback": "FL 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which coast of North America, is the danger of tropical revolving storms the greatest?",
    "feedback": "SE coast"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true concerning the coalescence process?",
    "feedback": "In the mid-latitudes this process produces only drizzle or very light rain"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of frozen precipitation with a diameter of less than 4 mm can be used in a METAR?",
    "feedback": "Ice pellets"
  },
  {
    "question": "When en-route and maintaining a constant flight level, how can you correctly describe the relationship between the true altitude and changes to the atmospheric pressure?",
    "feedback": "As pressure decreases the true altitude decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a flight from Manchester to Dublin, the highest obstruction is 3860 ft.\nGiven the following meteorological report from a neary aerodrome at 36 ft AMSL, determine the lowest safe flight level, giving 2000 ft terrain separation:\nQNH: 972 hPaTemperature: -2°C(assume 1 hPa = 30 ft)",
    "feedback": "FL075"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind direction and velocity (°/kt) at 50°N 040°E is:",
    "feedback": "020/70"
  },
  {
    "question": "During cruise at high altitude, a fully developed CB with cirrus streaks extending from its anvil is observed along the planned route. What is the recommended course of action?",
    "feedback": "Keep clear of the cirrus streaks to avoid ice crystal icing, re-route around the CB area"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sea breezes are most likely to occur when",
    "feedback": "slack pressure gradient and clear skies result in relatively high land temperatures"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud type (genus) is described by the following definition? \n\"Grey cloud layer, often dark, the appearance of which is rendered diffuse by more or less continuously falling rain or snow, which in most cases reaches the ground. It is thick enough throughout to blot out the sun. Low, ragged clouds frequently occur below the layer, with which they may or may not merge.\"",
    "feedback": "Nimbostratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather activity within a cold-air drop is usually greatest",
    "feedback": "in the afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure.The type of precipitation depicted is abbreviated to (1) ......, which falls from (2) ...... clouds and can be associated with (3) ...... turbulence",
    "feedback": "(1) GS, (2) CB, (3) moderate to severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the strongest tailwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew is to fly across the Himalayas, and the most efficient level to fly at is FL290. What is the approximate minimum terrain clearance at FL290 given the following meteorological information?\nElevation of highest terrain close to intended routing: 25460 ftOutside air temperature at FL290: -60°CQNH reported by a nearby station close to sea level: 982 hPa",
    "feedback": "690 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A meteorological observer is making observations for a METAR. The observer judges the visibility to be 1200 metres, with the restriction caused by water droplets suspended in the air. This restriction to visibility is:",
    "feedback": "Mist"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight in summer was planned to take-off from Phuket, Thailand at 08:00 LT, but the departure was delayed to 11:00 LT.\nWhat could happen to the take-off performance? The climb performance during take-off (1)....... because the air density (2)............",
    "feedback": "(1) degrades, (2) decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "The approximate inclined plane of a warm front is:",
    "feedback": "1/150"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a layer of air the decrease in temperature per 100 metres increase in height is more than 1°C. This layer can be described as being",
    "feedback": "absolutely unstable"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dewpoint temperature",
    "feedback": "can be reached by cooling the air whilst keeping pressure constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct concerning the savannah climate?",
    "feedback": "There are significant yearly variations in rainfall with a wet and a dry period"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind speed in a system with curved isobars compared to a system with straight isobars is (other conditions being the same)",
    "feedback": "higher if curvature is anticyclonic"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flying at FL230 is cleared by Air Traffic Control to descend to FL110. The average temperature for the descent is ISA +15ºC. What is the vertical distance of the descent?",
    "feedback": "12720 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which average height can the 700 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "feedback": "3,0 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "Continuous updraughts occur in a thunderstorm during the",
    "feedback": "cumulus stage."
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider that all official aviation meteorological sources indicate clear skies and good flying weather, but a commercial weather app on your phone suggests heavy thunderstorms for the area:",
    "feedback": "Use the commercial app’s forecast as a secondary reference but prioritize the information from official aviation sources. Confirm the weather conditions by reviewing satellite and radar imagery from official sources if available, and possibly consulting local weather stations for real-time updates before proceeding with the flight with extreme caution."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following types of cloud is most likely to produce heavy precipitation ?",
    "feedback": "NS."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure.\nWhich of the following runway state message, added to a METAR, could be decoded as follows?\nAll runways have deposits of dry snow, to an extent of 11 % to 25 % of the runway covered, to a depth of 50 mm, with a braking coefficient of 0.35.",
    "feedback": "88425035"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average temperature difference from ISA at FL 390 between Madrid and Dhahran?",
    "feedback": "-1°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "While descending through a cloud cover at high level, a small amount of a white, opaque deposit with a light porous texture and a rough surface is detected along the leading edge of the wing. This deposit is called:",
    "feedback": "Rime ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following cloud types is a medium level cloud ?",
    "feedback": "AS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mark the correct statement concerning lightning discharge.",
    "feedback": "While flying through air that is electrically charged the aircraft is likely to become a charge carrier itself and can initiate a lightning discharge."
  },
  {
    "question": "Below a low level inversion visibility is often",
    "feedback": "moderate or poor because there is no vertical exchange"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air mass acquires its basic properties",
    "feedback": "by stagnation of the air for a long period of time over areas having particular characteristics"
  },
  {
    "question": "Within a depression, two air masses meet so that a warm front is formed. In relation to a typical warm front:",
    "feedback": "cold air will be replaced by warm air and the frontal slope will be around 1:150"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is departing an airport at night in IMC, but soon reports to ATC that it needs to return due to a partial avionics failure and an engine shutdown, accompanied by a smell of burning in the cabin and flight deck. Which of the following meteorological phenomena has been encountered?",
    "feedback": "Lightning"
  },
  {
    "question": "When will the surface wind in a METAR record a gust factor ?",
    "feedback": "When gusts are at least 10 knots above the mean wind speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot wants to select an airport for arrival with a runway providing an RVR of at least 550 metres. Considering the following METARs, valid for the time of arrival, choose the appropriate airport (all other criteria for landing can be met at each airport).\nEGKK 191050Z 09002KT 0200 FZFG R08R/0350 R08L/0500 VV001 M03/M03 Q1008 WS RWY08R\nEGLF 191050Z 07003KT 0200 FZFG R06/0700D VV001 M03/M03 Q1008\nEGGW 191050Z 08004KT 0200 FZFG R08/0300U VV001 M02/M02 Q1007 RESG 08920294\nEGLL 191050Z 09002KT 0100 FZFG R09L/0300U R09R/0500U VV001 M02/M02 Q1008",
    "feedback": "EGLF"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a generalised zonal system of world wind circulation, the NE trade winds are applicable to zone",
    "feedback": "u"
  },
  {
    "question": "Look at the chart. Assuming a normal vertical temperature gradient, at what altitude will the freezing level above Shannon be found?",
    "feedback": "FL 60"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following situations can freezing rain be encountered ?",
    "feedback": "Ahead of a warm front in the winter"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft follows the flight plan, which crosses a mountain range, at FL140 within clouds. Afterwards, the route is leading over flat areas and then crosses an area of open sea. Over which area is airframe icing to be expected the most intense?",
    "feedback": "Over the mountain range, as this causes upward air motion on the windward side, forcing large supercooled water droplets to rise above the freezing level"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which month does the humid monsoon in India start?",
    "feedback": "In June."
  },
  {
    "question": "You fly from east to west at the 500 hPa level in the Northern hemisphere:",
    "feedback": "If the wind is from the North, there is a gain in altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "The LLWAS (Low-Level Wind Shear Avoidance System) is a system that is designed to detect low-level wind shear conditions around the periphery of an aerodrome. In this situation 2 sensors are situated in the vicinity of the aerodrome, measuring at an elevation of 150' a 12KT wind, and another one further NE, measuring at 60', 25 KT.\nWhat is the reason for that?",
    "feedback": "There are downbursts or strong downdrafts present in the area"
  },
  {
    "question": "An airmass is stable when",
    "feedback": "the vertical motion of a rising parcel of air tends to become weaker and disappears."
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are flying at FL 300 in an air mass that is 15°C warmer than a standard atmosphere, what is the outside temperature likely to be?",
    "feedback": "-30°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fallstreaks or virga are",
    "feedback": "water or ice particles falling out of a cloud that evaporate before reaching the ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the lowest forecast visibility that may be expected during an approach into Dhahran at ETA 0600 UTC ?\nTAF OEDR 280000Z 280110 VRB08KT CAVOK BECMG 0103 7000 TEMPO 0410 28014G24KT 4000 SA=",
    "feedback": "4 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is favourable for the lifting of air and the formation of clouds and precipitation?",
    "feedback": "Convergence near the ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the route indicated from Lisbon to Freetown, the Harmattan is a",
    "feedback": "NE wind affecting north-west Africa during November to April reducing visibility in rising dust."
  },
  {
    "question": "What do you understand by \"Saint Elmo's Fire\"?",
    "feedback": "A bright blue or violet glow visible around the windscreen and external parts of the aircraft, occasionally seen when flying in the vicinity of thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the North Atlantic region between 30°N and 65°N and the adjacent land areas during mid-summer, the predominant pressure systems are",
    "feedback": "Azores high and weak low over NE Canada"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are supposed to fly above a mountain that has a peak of 8600 feet on a westbound VFR flight. The ISA deviation in the area is -9 degrees Celsius and the local QNH is 995 hPa. What is the lowest usable flight level for this segment of the flight?",
    "feedback": "FL105"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which climatic type is to be expected between 10°N and 10°S?",
    "feedback": "Tropical rain climate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the approximate dimensions of a typical, fully developed Tropical Revolving Storm (TRS)?",
    "feedback": "Diameter of the eye: 30-50 kmDiameter of the entire TRS: 400-500 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning the lifting of a parcel of air is correct ?",
    "feedback": "Unsaturated parcels cool more rapidly than saturated parcels"
  },
  {
    "question": "For your flight from Zurich to Rome you consult, amongst other information, the following SIGMET:\n\nSIGMET VALID121420/121820 MOD TO SEV CAT OBS AND FCST S OF ALPS BTN FL 260 AND FL 380 / STNR / INTSF  =",
    "feedback": "You select a flight level below FL 260 due to turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rain is formed within warm clouds when a particle, such as a grain of dust, attracts a drop of moisture to itself. In a next step, this initial cloud droplet will....",
    "feedback": "collide with other droplets, thereby growing in size and eventually forming a rain drop"
  },
  {
    "question": "A main condition for the development of tropical showers and thunderstorms in the Intertropcial Convergence Zone (ITCZ) is the presence of ....",
    "feedback": "warm, humid, unstable air"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the lowest visibility that can be expected in area B?",
    "feedback": "3 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "A parcel of air has a temperature of 10°C and a dew point of 8°C. If the air cools to below the dew point, this initially causes .....",
    "feedback": "condensation"
  },
  {
    "question": "For subsonic cruising levels, a SIGMET is NOT issued in case of",
    "feedback": "isolated CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is correct regarding the propagation of mountain wave effects from low to high level?",
    "feedback": "When winds from a consistent direction, approximately perpendicular to a mountain range or high plateau, increase in speed with height within a deep, stable layer, mountain waves and their effects can extend from low to high level"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the geostrophic wind speed along a front is 24 kt, a warm front will move at a speed of about (1) ..... and a cold front will move at a speed of about (2) .....",
    "feedback": "(1) 16 kt, (2) 24 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which layer is most of the atmospheric humidity concentrated ?",
    "feedback": "Troposphere."
  },
  {
    "question": "The geostrophic wind is less than the gradient wind around an anticyclone because the",
    "feedback": "centrifugal force is added to the pressure gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "A SPECI is",
    "feedback": "an aviation selected special weather report"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the colour with which a warm front is shown on a surface chart?",
    "feedback": "Red"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement best describes the frontal activity around the red cross in the diagram?",
    "feedback": "To the West, a warm front moving northwards, to the East, a cold front moving southwards"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the cloud or phenomenon shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Cirrus with halo"
  },
  {
    "question": "In unstable air, surface visibility is most likely to be restricted by",
    "feedback": "showers of rain or snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Convective clouds are formed",
    "feedback": "in unstable atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "Glaze or clear ice is formed when supercooled droplets are",
    "feedback": "large and at a temperature just below freezing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming that an initial \"trigger\" force is present, the conditions most likely to result in the formation of thunderstorms are",
    "feedback": "Advection of cold air over a warm sea"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a sunny day and at the same latitude, over which of the following positions will the warming of air just above the surface be the greatest?",
    "feedback": "Above rocks"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by the expression \"Low level windshear\" ?",
    "feedback": "A change of wind direction and force during a limited period of time within a small area."
  },
  {
    "question": "Weather models use grids to produce weather products. What references do they use?",
    "feedback": "Latitude/longitude and time reference"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about depressions are correct or incorrect? 1) Polar lows are formed mainly over water 2) Thermal lows are formed mainly over land",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the true altitude of an aircraft flying at an indicated altitude of 4000 ft with the QNH 1026 from a nearby airport, but with sea level elevation set in the altimeter subscale? OAT ISA -15°C.",
    "feedback": "3760 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the displayed cloud forms is representative of altocumulus lenticularis?",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "You intend to overfly a mountain range. The recommended minimum flight altitude is, according to the aviation chart, 12000 ft AMSL. The average air temperature is 10°C higher than ISA, your altimeter is set to 1023 hPa (QNH of a nearby airport at nearly sea level). At what altimerter reading will you effectively be at the recommended minimum flight altitude?(barometric lapse rate 27 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "11520 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will the altimeter indicate if the actual true altitude is to be 10000 ft when the pressure altitude is 10000 ft at OAT -30°C?",
    "feedback": "11000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the temperature deviation (°C) from ISA over 50°N 010°E ?",
    "feedback": "-10"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which diagram illustrates a cold high?",
    "feedback": "C"
  },
  {
    "question": "A thermal depression is likely to form",
    "feedback": "over the Iberian peninsula during summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given: Altimeter setting: 1013.2 hPa Altimeter reading: 5000 ft Outside air temperature at 5000 ft: +5°C QFE: 958 hPa QNH: 983 hPa  What is the true height of the aircraft above the aerodrome?(barometric lapse rate 27 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "3515 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Absolute instability in a layer of air is characterized by the vertical temperature gradient in the layer being:",
    "feedback": "Greater than 1°/100 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "The diurnal range of temperature is least in tropical countries."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the displayed cloud forms is representative of a cumulus?",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Air density is mass of air per unity of volume, and is influenced by:",
    "feedback": "both b) and c) are correct."
  },
  {
    "question": "For an inland aerodrome, how does the vertical extent of the friction layer and amount of turbulence in this layer change in the late afternoon in midsummer, compared to the same time in winter (assuming similar surface wind conditions)?",
    "feedback": "Increase in both vertical extent and turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a surface temperature of +10°C, and a dew point of +5°C, at what height might you expect cumulus clouds to form?",
    "feedback": "2000ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of these cloud types can icing be virtually ruled out?",
    "feedback": "CI"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characteristics will the surface winds have in an area where the isobars on the weather map are very close together?",
    "feedback": "Strong and flowing across the isobars."
  },
  {
    "question": "171020Z 21005KT 9000 FEW030TCU FEW033CB SCT040 BKN100 19/18 Q1005 TEMPO 25015G25KT 3000 TSRA SCT005 BKN015CB=\nWhat is the conclusion for a pilot flying in the weather stated in the METAR message above?",
    "feedback": "There are thunderstorms present that should be avoided"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B at the flight level corresponding to the pressure surface of the constant pressure chart. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "The true altitude will be higher over A than over B"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is flying at a pressure altitude of 10000 ft, its altimeter indicates 9500 ft. The temperature is ISA -10°C and the altimeter has no instrument error.\nWhat is the true altitude?",
    "feedback": "9120 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What species of cloud is the following definition referring to?\n\"Strongly sprouting Cumulus with generally sharp outlines and often great vertical extent. The bulging upper part frequently resembles a cauliflower\".",
    "feedback": "Cumulus congestus"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is climbing on an instrument departure out of Christchurch airport, New Zealand, where the transition altitude is 13000 ft. The ATIS provides a QNH of 970 hPa. What is the expected reading on the altimeter, if the pilot resets the subscale when climbing through the transition altitude?",
    "feedback": "14290 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate maximum distance and height that turbulence caused by mountain waves may be encountered on the leeward side of the Rocky Mountains in the USA?",
    "feedback": "300 NM and up to the tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is true of a typical thermal depression?",
    "feedback": "It forms over land in summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Large hail stones",
    "feedback": "are typically associated with severe thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of front / occlusion usually moves the fastest?",
    "feedback": "Cold front."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which layer of the atmosphere contains more than 90 % of the total amount of water vapour?",
    "feedback": "Troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "An airport broadcasts the following METAR:\n21008KT 4500 FZDZ BR OVC008 M02/M02 Q1009\nThe figure shows a cross-section of a frontal system during winter time. At which location is the airport most likely situated?",
    "feedback": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather conditions are indications of the summer monsoon in India?",
    "feedback": "Thunderstorms, showers of heavy rain."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a cold-air drop?",
    "feedback": "A low pressure area with colder air compared to its surroundings. It can be found by looking at upper contour charts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Before a planned take-off, wind shear is forecast. What is the most advisable course of action?",
    "feedback": "Delay the take-off"
  },
  {
    "question": "When 1 hour away from the destination the pilot receives notification that tornado activity is present 10 NM from the airport, moving towards the airport and away from the direction in which the aircraft is flying.\nBased on this information, the best action for the pilot is to....",
    "feedback": "reduce the aircraft speed, as a typical tornado would pass over the airport in approximately 20 to 40 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pressure pattern located over the Atlantic Ocean between 40°N and 50°N is called ....",
    "feedback": "westerly wave"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to reduce QFE to QNH, which of the following item(s) must be known ?",
    "feedback": "Elevation of the airfield"
  },
  {
    "question": "A mountain range runs north-south and reaches 4000 feet AMSL. It is located to the west of the destination, which is at 1000 feet AMSL. The gradient wind is 27030KT, the air is unstable and rain is falling on the windward slope of the mountains. What weather phenomenon should be expected at that aerodrome?",
    "feedback": "A Foehn wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "Frontal fog can be formed",
    "feedback": "when the air becomes saturated due to evaporation of precipitation and water vapour condenses"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average wind for the route Shannon-Lisboa at FL 290:",
    "feedback": "36080KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "The W/V (°/kt) at 50°N 015°W is:",
    "feedback": "290/75"
  },
  {
    "question": "The arrows labelled \"s\" represent the mean tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "feedback": "May to November and are called cyclones"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet aircraft flies downwind of a large CB cell. Small water droplets are noticed on the windshield and unreliable indications of the OAT are observed, despite flying in clear air well outside the cloud. Which type of hazard may possibly occur?",
    "feedback": "Ice crystal icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the following METAR and SPECI observations:\nMETAR EGVN 061620Z 33022G34KT 290V350 7000 TSRA FEW015 BKN025CB BKN040 24/16 Q1016 TEMPO 4000 TSGR\nSPECI EGVN 061630Z 33022G33KT 300V350 6000 FEW015 BKN025TCU BKN040 23/16 Q1016\nThe SPECI was issued because .....",
    "feedback": "the thunderstorm has finished and the associated precipitation has ended"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying from A to B, in which area would you anticipate clear ice accretion?",
    "feedback": "East of the warm front above the 0° isotherm"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following processes within a layer of air may lead to the building of CU and CB clouds?",
    "feedback": "Convection."
  },
  {
    "question": "How long does a typical frontal depression approximately last in Europe?",
    "feedback": "7 to 10 days"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are the air masses distributed in a cold occlusion ?",
    "feedback": "The coldest air mass behind and the less cold air in front of the occlusion; the warm air mass is above ground level."
  },
  {
    "question": "Thunderstorms can occur on a warm front if the",
    "feedback": "warm air is moist and the environmental lapse rate exceeds the saturated adiabatic lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Geostrophic wind is the wind when isobars are",
    "feedback": "straight lines and no friction is involved."
  },
  {
    "question": "The 0° isotherm is forecast to be at FL 50. At what FL would you expect a temperature of -6° C?",
    "feedback": "FL 80"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding the seasonal weather conditions in Hong Kong?",
    "feedback": "Moist with SW winds in summer and dry with NE winds in winter"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dark area around 60 NM/330° on this weather radar return showing is;",
    "feedback": "Shadowing"
  },
  {
    "question": "FL 110, an OAT -05°C is measured. What will the temperature be at FL 50, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "+7°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Harmattan blows from the Sahara desert with wind vector 050°/25 kt over an airport on the coast of West Africa. Which statement is correct about the meteorological conditions most likely to be experienced at this airport?",
    "feedback": "The visibility is reduced due to sand and dust in the air"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft maintains a constant indicated altitude of 6500 ft from A (600 ft/AMSL - QNH 1012 hPa) to B (930 ft/AMSL - QNH 977 hPa). Assuming that the altimeter subscale setting remains unchanged at 1012 hPa, the height of the aircraft above the surface at B will be:(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "4520 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying over the sea at FL 100, with a true altitude of 10000 feet; local QNH is 1003 hPa. \nWhat assumption, if any, can be made about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying ?",
    "feedback": "It is warmer than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following messages should be cancelled when the conditions are no longer occurring or no longer expected to occur?",
    "feedback": "Aerodrome warning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Read this description: \"After such a fine day, the ring around the moon was a bad sign yesterday evening for the weather today. And, sure enough, it is pouring down outside. The clouds are making an oppressively low ceiling of uniform grey; but at least it has become a little bit warmer.\" Which of these weather phenomena is being described?",
    "feedback": "A warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following flight levels, if any, is forecast to be clear of significant cloud, icing, turbulence, and CAT along the marked route from SHANNON (53°N 10°W) to BERLIN (53°N 13°E) ?",
    "feedback": "FL250"
  },
  {
    "question": "What altimeter reading would you expect when landing at an airfield 3000 ft above MSL, altimeter setting is QFE for the field and local temperature is + 25°C?",
    "feedback": "0 ft."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO, haze (HZ) or smoke (FU) is reduced visibility due to the presence of solid particles (lithometeors) in the atmosphere to a value of:",
    "feedback": "5000 m or less"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the characteristics of cumuliform clouds?",
    "feedback": "Large water droplets, instability, turbulence, showers and mainly clear ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning the tropopause is correct?",
    "feedback": "The layer just above the tropopause is absolutely stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "After passing at right angles through a very active cold front in the direction of the cold air, what will you encounter, in the northern hemisphere immediately after a marked change in temperature?",
    "feedback": "A veering in the wind direction."
  },
  {
    "question": "At Lyon (LFLY, N4545 E00500), at 12 UTC, the sky is overcast with Stratocumulus and Altostratus and it is raining. Using the SWC below, valid at 1200 UTC, we can estimate a weather improvement for Lyon at:",
    "feedback": "2100 UTC"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a radiosonde?",
    "feedback": "Instrument intended to be carried by a balloon up through the atmosphere, equipped with devices to measure meteorological variables and provided with a radio transmitter for sending this information to the observing station."
  },
  {
    "question": "There is frontal fog over an aerodrome, which of these conditions is likely to dissipate the fog?",
    "feedback": "After the front has passed there is no more cold air to cool the humid air close to the surface, the visibility should improve"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following statements deal with precipitation, turbulence and icing. Select the list containing the most likely alternatives for NS cloud:",
    "feedback": "Precipitation may be snow, sleet or rain. Icing is probable and may range between light and severe. Turbulence is rarely more than moderate."
  },
  {
    "question": "The forecast period covered by the PARIS/CHARLES-DE-GAULLE TAFs totals (hours)",
    "feedback": "27"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you have to fly through a warm front when freezing level is at 10000 feet in the warm air and at 2000 feet in the cold air, at which altitude is the probability of freezing rain the lowest ?",
    "feedback": "12000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a short and very busy positioning flight, the crew neglect to select the correct QNH for the destination airfield. Using the information provided below, if they land at the destination airfield with the departure airfield QNH still set, what would the altimeter indicate on touchdown?\nDeparture airfield: QNH 1020, elevation 520 ftDestination airfield: QNH 1018, elevation 318 ft\n(assume 30 ft per 1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "378 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature at which a parcel of air becomes saturated if it cools is called:",
    "feedback": "Dew point temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at FL 200. Outside air temperature is -40°C, and the pressure at sea level is 1033 hPa. What is the true altitude?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "19400 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following processes will increase the stability of an air mass?",
    "feedback": "Cooling by the underlying surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "How do air masses move at a warm front ?",
    "feedback": "Warm air overrides a cold air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "Going from the equator to the north pole, the altitude of the tropopause",
    "feedback": "decreases and its temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Low level wind shear is likely to be greatest",
    "feedback": "at the top of a marked surface-based inversion."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which thunderstorms generally develop in the afternoon in summer over land in moderate latitudes?",
    "feedback": "Airmass thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a surface analysis chart the isobars in ridges are ...",
    "feedback": "curved and extend outwards from an anticyclone"
  },
  {
    "question": "A parcel of moist but not saturated air rises due to adiabatic effects. Which of the following changes ?",
    "feedback": "Relative humidity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the earliest time (UTC) that thunderstorms, if any, are forecast for Tunis/Carthage?",
    "feedback": "1800"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the dry adiabatic lapse rate per 100 metres ?",
    "feedback": "1.0°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the approach, the surface temperature is given as -5°C. The freezing level is at 3000 FT/AGL. At 4000 FT/AGL, there is a solid cloud layer from which rain is falling.\nAccording to the weather briefing, the clouds are due to an inversion caused by warm air sliding up and over an inclined front. Would you expect icing?",
    "feedback": "Yes, between ground level and 3000 FT/AGL."
  },
  {
    "question": "The mean wind that may be expected to affect the route segment from the coast of SE England to Geneva at FL 270 is:",
    "feedback": "220/70"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a thunderstorm the electrical discharges most commonly happen due to potential differences between...",
    "feedback": "the Earth's surface and the cloud or between different parts of the cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the greatest intensity of turbulence (i) and icing (ii) that can be expected on the route from Valencia to Charleston at FL 330?",
    "feedback": "(i) severe; (ii) severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the climb after takeoff, the altimeter setting is adjusted at the transition altitude. If the local QNH is 966 hPa, what will happen to the altimeter reading during the resetting procedure?",
    "feedback": "It will increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Due to a rapid depressurization an aircraft has to rapidly descend to the departure airport. In the turmoil, the crew forgets to switch back from standard pressure to the local QNH of 1030 hPa. With an airport elevation of 224 feet, a transition altitude of 17000 feet and a transition level at FL180, what is the indicated altitude after landing?\n(assume 1 hPa=30 feet)",
    "feedback": "Negative 286 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given: Aircraft at FL 150 overhead an airport Elevation of airport 720 FT. QNH is 1003 hPa. OAT at FL150 -5°C. What is the true altitude of the aircraft? (Assume 1 hPa = 27 FT)",
    "feedback": "15 280 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather conditions are most likely to affect an approach to Dakar during July?",
    "feedback": "Wet and thundery due to the proximity of intertropical convergence zone (ITCZ)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Freezing rain occurs when",
    "feedback": "rain falls into a layer of air with temperatures below 0°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Radiation inversions mainly develop over:",
    "feedback": "Inland areas during cloudless winter nights"
  },
  {
    "question": "After landing at an aerodrome (aerodrome elevation 1750 ft), the altimeter indicates an altitude of 1300 ft. The altimeter is set to the pressure value of 1013 hPa. What is the QNH at this aerodrome?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "1028 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pressure altitude is obtained by:",
    "feedback": "setting the altimeter to standard sea level pressure."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following precipitation types gives the most severe icing?",
    "feedback": "Freezing rain"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from A to B (indicated on the chart) at 9000 ft altitude. After crossing the second cold front (approximately halfway to B), the wind speed is expected to (1) .... and the wind direction is expected to turn (2) .....",
    "feedback": "(1) increase; (2) counterclockwise"
  },
  {
    "question": "Judging by the chart, on which of these routes can you expect to encounter moderate and locally severe CAT at FL 300?",
    "feedback": "Zurich - Rome"
  },
  {
    "question": "While mountain flying on a warm summer day under high pressure conditions, you circle a mountain of known height at peak elevation. Comparing to the indication of your altimeter, the peak elevation will therefore be....",
    "feedback": "higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at FL 130 and your true altitude is 12000 FT. What is the temperature deviation from that of the standard atmosphere at FL 130 (QNH 1013,2 hPa) ?",
    "feedback": "ISA -20°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "In mid-latitudes, what happens to the air temperature as altitude increases between the tropopause and FL650?",
    "feedback": "It varies, but generally remains relatively constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena should be described as precipitation at the time they are observed?",
    "feedback": "DZ"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature at 10000 FT in the International Standard Atmosphere is :",
    "feedback": "-5°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will happen when a warm front reaches a mountain range? The air is lifted over the mountain and will ....",
    "feedback": "strengthen the formation of clouds and precipitation on the windward side"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main difference between a tornado and a dust devil?",
    "feedback": "The vertical extent of the dust devil is smaller than that of tornadoes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why do tropical revolving storms tend to develop mostly in the western parts of the tropical oceans?",
    "feedback": "Because there is a maximum of humidity as a result of the trade winds`long sea passage"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does moderate turbulence affect an aircraft?",
    "feedback": "Changes in altitude or attitude occur but the aircraft remains in positive control at all times."
  },
  {
    "question": "Aircraft A is in a holding pattern, clear of cloud, based on an on-airfield navigation facility, at 3000 ft above the destination with the landing runway clearly visible from the hold. At the same time aircraft B is on short final, approaching the threshold of the landing runway, when the pilot loses visual reference with the runway and performs a missed approach.\nWhich form of obscuration is this scenario most likely?",
    "feedback": "Shallow fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "A supercooled droplet is one that",
    "feedback": "remains liquid at a below freezing temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. A ridge is represented in:",
    "feedback": "Location E"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet stream is located at 42°N 090°W. What is its extent of the vertical development?",
    "feedback": "39000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is meant by \"transition altitude\"?",
    "feedback": "The altitude on which a pilot is supposed to change from local QNH to standard pressure setting during climb out from an airport"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements correctly describes the difference between atmospheric turbulence and wind shear?",
    "feedback": "Atmospheric turbulence results from short-duration, irregular disturbances in the wind flow, whereas wind shear is caused by sudden and sustained changes in wind direction and/or speed over a short distance."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the difference between a macroburst and a microburst?",
    "feedback": "A macroburst affects a greater area"
  },
  {
    "question": "When and where on the Earth are outbreaks of cold polar air entering subtropical weather systems most likely to occur?",
    "feedback": "North and Central China during winter"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft in flight experiences airframe icing which makes a change of heading and/or altitude desirable.\n\nWhich intensity of ice accretion is present according to ICAO terms?",
    "feedback": "Moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which interpretation of the following message is correct? LFLD AD WRNG 1 VALID 050430/050900 FROST FCST=",
    "feedback": "It is forecast that some parts of the surface, vehicles, and aircraft parked outside will be contaminated by hoar frost between 0430 and 0900 on the 5th of that month."
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term TREND signify?",
    "feedback": "It is a brief landing forecast added to the actual weather report"
  },
  {
    "question": "A particular METAR states 4000 metres of visibility. This can refer to the visibility of a light on an unlit background. To how many candelas does this correspond to?",
    "feedback": "1000"
  },
  {
    "question": "If Paris reports a wind of 30012KT on the METAR, what wind velocity would you expect to encounter at a height of 2000 feet above the ground ?",
    "feedback": "33025KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the diagram, which figure represents a warm occlusion?",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What wind direction will occur at point B?",
    "feedback": "Southwest"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a certain position, the temperature on the 300 hPa chart is -48°C; according to the tropopause chart, the tropopause is at FL 330. What is the most likely temperature at FL 350 ?",
    "feedback": "-54°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: State the average air temperature for the route Zurich-Rome, FL 110:",
    "feedback": "-09°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "An altimeter adjusted to 1013 hPa indicates an altitude of 3600 FT. Should this altimeter be adjusted to the local QNH value of 991 hPa, the altitude indicated would be:(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "2940 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the four radio soundings, select the one that indicates low stratus:",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What degree of turbulence, if any, is likely to be encountered while flying through a cold front in the summer over Central Europe at FL 100?",
    "feedback": "Severe turbulence in CB cloud."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart:\nYou plan a 5 hour flight on 12th March 2017 at 3000 feet altitude from Hahn (H) (50°N, 007°E) to Brest (B) (49°N, 004°W), taking off at 17:00 UTC.\nWhat hazards could be expected along the route?",
    "feedback": "Moderate turbulence throughout the route, with moderate icing along the second half"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the direction and speed of movement of the occlusion, depicted on the chart?",
    "feedback": "NE, 15 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following options best describes the seasonal weather pattern in Hong Kong (22°N 114°E) in the Far East?",
    "feedback": "Mild and dry NE monsoon during the winter, hot and moist SW monsoon during the summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature at FL050 is 0°C and at FL070 -4°C. The height difference is:",
    "feedback": "1960 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the effects of climbing through an inversion layer)",
    "feedback": "Reduced climb gradient and turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "From which of the following pieces of information can the stability of the atmosphere be derived?",
    "feedback": "Environmental lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot flying a STAR changes the altimeter subscale when descending through the transition level. What is the approximate reading on the altimeter after the change, given the following information?\nQNH: 1043 hPaTransition altitude: 5000 feetTransition level: FL045\n(assume 30 ft per 1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "5400 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following conditions is moderate to severe airframe icing most likely to be encountered?",
    "feedback": "In Nimbostratus cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "In order to calculate QFE from QNH, which of the following must be known ?",
    "feedback": "Elevation of the airfield."
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass at position X is most likely to be:",
    "feedback": "Maritime tropical"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions gives the highest value of the QNH?",
    "feedback": "QFE = 995 hPa, elevation = 1600 FT (488m)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the jet stream section overhead Iceland. In this part of the jet stream there are two small, solid black lines across the jet stream axis. Which of the following statements correctly decodes this symbol?",
    "feedback": "The height of the jet stream axis changes by +/- 3000 ft and/or the speed varies by +/- 20 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Continuous freezing rain is observed at an airport. Which would be the most probable vertical temperature lapse rate?",
    "feedback": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"A\" is",
    "feedback": "frequent showers of rain and snow, good visibility outside precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The schematic global views show the areas of easterly (red) and westerly (blue) winds in the upper troposphere.\n\nWhich of the four figures is typical for January?",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Relative humidity",
    "feedback": "increases if the air is cooled whilst maintaining the vapour pressure constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the definition of relative humidity ?",
    "feedback": "Ratio between the actual mixing ratio and the saturation mixing ratio X 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which weather chart gives information about icing and the height of the freezing level ?",
    "feedback": "Significant weather chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "Polar air outbreaks are depressions that can affect (1) ..... during the (2) .....",
    "feedback": "(1) central and northern China, (2) wintertime"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the ITCZ is correct?",
    "feedback": "It is normally fed with converging northern and southern trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Bordeaux to Amsterdam, ETA 2100 UTC. What lowest cloud base is forecast for arrival at Amsterdam?  TAF EHAM 281500Z 2816/2901 14010KT 6000 -RA SCT025 BECMG 2816/2818 12015G25KT SCT008 BKN013 TEMPO 2818/2823 3000 RA BKN005 OVC010 BECMG 2823/2901 25020KT 8000 NSW BKN020 =",
    "feedback": "500 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud, normally found in the medium level, may extend to the low and high  levels?",
    "feedback": "NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average wind at FL 160 between Zurich and Rome ?",
    "feedback": "020/50"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which airport, at 1200 UTC, has the lowest probability of precipitation?",
    "feedback": "LSZH"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are preparing to depart from Riga, Latvia, shortly after the passage of a warm front. The temperature recently dropped to around -10°C, is now -4°C, and is expected to rise to about +2°C within the next few hours. At this moment, which of the following poses the greatest environmental hazard for departure?",
    "feedback": "Risk of moderate icing and freezing precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What temperature does an observer at point C encounter in the next hour?",
    "feedback": "The temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "An airborne weather radar installation makes it possible to detect the location of",
    "feedback": "zones of precipitation, particulary liquid-state precipitation, and also their intensity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does a CB contain at moderate latitudes in summer?",
    "feedback": "A combination of ice crystals, water droplets and supercooled water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "What winds are mainly associated with the winter monsoon in the monsoon regions of the Indian sub-continent ?",
    "feedback": "Northeasterly winds bringing dry and hazy air."
  },
  {
    "question": "Mountains can affect ice accretion, due to orographic intensification, because...",
    "feedback": "the air may become polluted by dust from the mountain slopes, creating hygroscopic freezing nuclei"
  },
  {
    "question": "Does the following report make sense?\nLSZH VRB02KT 5000 MIFG 02/02 Q1015 NOSIG",
    "feedback": "The report is possible, because shallow fog is defined as a thin layer of fog below eye level."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the deviation of the temperature at FL 140 above Copenhagen compared to ISA?",
    "feedback": "9°C colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average temperature at FL 160 between Oslo and Paris ?",
    "feedback": "-19°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Judging by the chart, what wind speeds can you expect at FL 230 above Amsterdam?",
    "feedback": "80 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "When last 10 minutes wind velocity deviates more than 10 kts from mean value during the same period of time, this will be indicated as:",
    "feedback": "A gust"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a clear, freezing-cold night in late autumn, what might the flight crew be expected to observe on arrival at the aircraft, parked outside on the apron, prior to an early morning flight?",
    "feedback": "The overnight radiative cooling of the land and fuselage surface may have caused hoar frost to form, covering the aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The reported surface wind for Brussels airport, located in Belgium, is 25009 KT. What is the expected wind at approximately 2000 ft AGL?",
    "feedback": "28018KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Surface wind is the:",
    "feedback": "airflow near to the surface that is reduced in strength by the effect of friction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Merging and processing data from gridded forecasts, automatic aircraft detection and reports from pilots is useful, because:",
    "feedback": "It can be provided to the flight crew through their EFB for more situational awareness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Continuous freezing rain is observed at an airfield. Which of the four diagrams (a to d from left to right) is most likely to reflect temperatures above the airfield concerned?",
    "feedback": "Diagram 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Flight is performed from Rome to Nairobi. Considering the sector Rome to 25N on the route indicated, what mean upper winds may be expected at FL 300 during winter?",
    "feedback": "Westerly jet streams in excess of 70 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The electric field in the atmosphere generates a significant potential difference between the Earth's surface and the ionosphere.\nIt is believed this is caused by....",
    "feedback": "the global distribution of thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "The presence of ice pellets at the surface is evidence that",
    "feedback": "freezing rain occurs at a higher altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a visual clue which may help to locate and therefore avoid a wind-shear area?",
    "feedback": "Virga"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the northern hemisphere the gradient wind of a cyclonic pressure distribution is 350/24, over the sea the surface wind would approximate",
    "feedback": "340/20"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a generalised zonal system of world climatic and wind circulation, zone \"t\" is an area of",
    "feedback": "subtropical high pressure systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following types of cloud is most likely to be associated with prolonged and continuous moderate rain?",
    "feedback": "NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a cold-air drop?",
    "feedback": "A topographic depression filled with cold air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Within the atmosphere water exists in different states. Which change of state process delivers the main part of the energy in thunderstorms and hurricanes?",
    "feedback": "Condensation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What minimum visibility (m) is forecast for 0600 UTC at LONDON LHR (EGLL) ?",
    "feedback": "1500"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a front crosses a mountain range, its activity",
    "feedback": "strengthens \"upwind\" of the mountains."
  },
  {
    "question": "A polar low is a ...",
    "feedback": "small depression over sea areas, accompanied by frequent wintry showers"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena is least likely to lead to the formation of a Cumulonimbus with thunderstorm ?",
    "feedback": "Ground radiation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena should be described as precipitation at the time they are observed?",
    "feedback": "SN"
  },
  {
    "question": "During take-off at sunrise, if haze is reported, a pilot is likely to experience the greatest reduction in visibility when departing from runway:",
    "feedback": "09"
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the altitude of the condensation level, when an air pacel is lifted from MSL to 20000 ft. Static air temperature at MSL + 20°C, dew point at MSL -5°C. \nGiven:\nBrown dashed line: Constant saturation mixing ratioGreen line: Dry adiabaticMagenta line: Saturated adiabatic",
    "feedback": "10000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"B\" is",
    "feedback": "frequent showers of rain or snow, good visibility outside showers"
  },
  {
    "question": "Central Europe is situated in the zone of",
    "feedback": "mid-latitude climate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Judging by the chart, what windspeeds can you expect at FL 340 above Rome?",
    "feedback": "145 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will be the classification of high level clouds and where will the base be?",
    "feedback": "above 16500ft, Cirriform"
  },
  {
    "question": "Shortly after take-off an aircraft encounters a sharp inversion and soon after experiences a rapidly increasing tailwind.\n\nWhich combination of effects on the aircraft can be expected?",
    "feedback": "Reduced performance, immediately followed by a significant loss of lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the navigation display, how should the pilot alter the aircraft's heading?",
    "feedback": "Turn left to avoid the storm"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these four METAR reports suggests that rain is most likely in the next few hours?",
    "feedback": "23015KT 8000 BKN030 OVC070 17/14 Q1009 BECMG 4000 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "After a sunny spring day and a cloudless night you depart from an inland airport in calm winds. Soon after takeoff the wind veers sharply and increases in speed. Your low level windshear warning goes off in the cockpit. What meteorological phenomenon can cause this?",
    "feedback": "Nocturnal ground inversion causing a nocturnal low-level jet"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot prepares for the last flight in July within central Europe. The pilot has just finished reviewing the meteorological information and noticed that the destination weather report warns of tornadoes in the area. This is.....",
    "feedback": "possible, as tornadoes can occur in Europe throughout the year"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is correct regarding forecasts of en-route turbulence?",
    "feedback": "The accurate forecasting of the severity, extent, and levels affected by turbulence is based on modelling. Forecast documentation also covers a fixed time period and it is often not reliable, so pilot reports of turbulence are of great value"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which average height can the 300 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "feedback": "9,0 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "The diagram of the system represents a:",
    "feedback": "warm occlusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following weather reports could, in accordance with the regulations, the abbreviation \"CAVOK\" be used?",
    "feedback": "27019G37KT 9999 BKN050 18/14 Q1016 NOSIG="
  },
  {
    "question": "Relative humidity depends on",
    "feedback": "moisture content and temperature of the air"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a trend forecast?",
    "feedback": "A landing forecast appended to METAR/SPECI, valid for 2 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the lower layers of the atmosphere due to friction the wind changes direction towards the low pressure area because :",
    "feedback": "wind speed decreases and therefore coriolis force decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "In stratiform clouds",
    "feedback": "weak vertical currents occur and the temperature is nearly equal to the temperature of the surrounding air at the same height"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under what conditions may airframe icing be expected? When the outside air temperature is (1) .... or lower, and the airframe temperature is (2) .... or lower.",
    "feedback": "(1) 0°C, (2) 0° C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud type may indicate the presence of severe turbulence ?",
    "feedback": "Altocumulus lenticularis"
  },
  {
    "question": "As a parcel of air warms, its ability to hold water vapour:",
    "feedback": "Increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the northern hemisphere the wind at the surface blows",
    "feedback": "counter-clockwise around, and toward the centre of, a low pressure area"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of fog is often observed in the coastal region of Newfoundland in spring time?",
    "feedback": "Advection fog."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the temperature deviation in degrees Celsius, from the International Standard Atmosphere overhead Frankfurt ?",
    "feedback": "ISA -13°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following options correctly describes the propagation of mountain wave effects?",
    "feedback": "Mountain wave effects can propagate from low to high level"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nPressure altitude: 4000 ftIndicated altitude: 4500 ftTemperature: ISA + 23°C\nWhat is the true altitude?",
    "feedback": "4914 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In mature CBs the probability of severe icing, according to meteorological rules, is greatest in the following temperature range:",
    "feedback": "0°C to -23°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QFF at an airfield in California located 69 metres below sea level is 1030 hPa. The air temperature is 10°C lower than a standard atmosphere. What is the QNH?",
    "feedback": "More than 1030 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"S\" is",
    "feedback": "overcast with drizzle and orographic fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which clouds consists mainly of ice crystals and can be defined as ice clouds?\n1) Nimbostratus2) Cirrocumulus3) Stratocumulus4) Altostratus5) Cumulus congestus6) Cumulonimbus capillatus7) Altocumulus castellanus",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Heavy drizzle is reported at the destination airport. What is the visibility to be expected on short final when landing?",
    "feedback": "The visibility could be as low as 500 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Bahrain Transition Altitude TA is 13000 ft and the Transition Level TL is FL150. If the Bahrain QNH is 1003 hPa, how thick is the Transition Layer, assuming that 1 hPa = 40 ft at altitude?",
    "feedback": "1600 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight over the sea at FL 135, the true altitude is 13500 feet; local QNH is 1019 hPa. What information, if any, can be gained about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying?",
    "feedback": "It is colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "What areas are most frequently affected by monsoons?",
    "feedback": "West Africa and South Asia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct or incorrect?\n1) During a blocking omega situation, the blocking omega high pressure area causes a very short duration of fine weather 2) The tropopause is generally colder overhead the equator, compared to the temperature of the tropopause overhead the north pole",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The average change of pressure with height in the lower atmosphere is:",
    "feedback": "1 hPa/30ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cloud type most applicable to square 2D is",
    "feedback": "AS"
  },
  {
    "question": "A trough is indicated by letter:",
    "feedback": "A"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the defined upper level of the WS activity in the following message?\n\n... MOD WS APCH RWY18 FCST=",
    "feedback": "1600 ft above runway level"
  },
  {
    "question": "State the four families of clouds:",
    "feedback": "High, medium and low clouds, and clouds with extensive vertical development."
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the lowest headwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Steady precipitation, in contrast to showery precipitation falls from",
    "feedback": "stratiform clouds with little or no turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding in-flight visibility when there is shallow fog at the aerodrome with no cloud above?",
    "feedback": "When overhead the aerodrome and well above the fog, objects on the aerodrome can often be seen relatively clearly"
  },
  {
    "question": "Runway Visual Range (RVR) is",
    "feedback": "usually better than meteorological visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "A given mass of air is saturated with water vapour (no condensed water). If temperature increases",
    "feedback": "the amount of water vapour remains constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather situation leads to the formation of a downburst?",
    "feedback": "Cold air descending out from a mature cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are flying from Rome to Amsterdam at FL 200, what conditions can you expect at cruising altitude?",
    "feedback": "Moderate or severe turbulence and icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the relationship, if any, between QFE and QNH at an airport situated 50 FT below sea level?",
    "feedback": "QFE is greater than QNH."
  },
  {
    "question": "The following changes are observed after frontal passage:\nWind: Sharp veer from SW to NWClouds: Nimbostratus and StratocumulusPressure: Decreasing and then sharp increase after passageVisibility: Good behind the front\nState the type of front and the air mass:",
    "feedback": "Cold front, stable air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ITCZ affects",
    "feedback": "West Africa between 10° and 30° N, and the north coasts of the Arabian Sea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following best describes Zone A?",
    "feedback": "Trough of low pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "The RVR, as reported in a METAR, is always the",
    "feedback": "value representative of the touchdown zone"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what flight level is the jet stream core that is situated over Germany?",
    "feedback": "FL 330"
  },
  {
    "question": "The arrows labelled \"t\" represent the mean tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "feedback": "June to October and are called cyclones"
  },
  {
    "question": "A mountain range is aligned in an East-West direction. Select the conditions from the answers below that could give rise to standing waves. Wind values are given for 2000 ft, 5000 ft, and 10000 ft:",
    "feedback": "180°/29 kt; 180°/40 kt; 180°/60 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are cleared to climb to FL060 after take-off from an airport. After levelling of, the local QNH of 999 hPa remains set. What is the difference between your aircraft and other traffic at FL060?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "Your aircraft is 420 ft higher"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot planned a flight but the destination reports a weather phenomenon which induced the pilot to update the fuel log. Which of the following phenomena does this most likely refer to?",
    "feedback": "Recent snow showers"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying in mountainous terrain and assuming ISA temperatures and strong winds, which of the following is correct?",
    "feedback": "In case of venturi effect, the actual altitude of the aircraft is lower than the indicated altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the heaviest type of precipitation, if any, forecast for BORDEAUX/MERIGNAC at 1000 UTC ?",
    "feedback": "light rain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following combinations of pressure and temperature is correct in the International Standard Atmosphere ISA?",
    "feedback": "500 hPa -21.1°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the effect of a strong low level inversion ?",
    "feedback": "It promotes vertical windshear."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which  weather condition lowers true altitude as compared to pressure altitude to a position where flight over mountains could be dangerous?",
    "feedback": "Cold low."
  },
  {
    "question": "A surface based inversion is a characteristic of",
    "feedback": "nocturnal radiation during clear nights"
  },
  {
    "question": "The presence of altocumulus castellanus indicates",
    "feedback": "instability in the middle troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying northbound just out of Moscow at FL120. What sort of in-flight weather hazard might be encountered?",
    "feedback": "Moderate icing and turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where and under which of the following conditions is orographic fog likely to form when the surface wind in a tropical maritime air mass is forecast 27010KT?",
    "feedback": "On the west-facing slopes of high ground when the air's relative humidity is high"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average wind for the route Zurich - Rome at FL110.",
    "feedback": "230/10"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following will dissipate orographic fog?",
    "feedback": "Downslope wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characteristic is associated with a temperature inversion ?",
    "feedback": "Stability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line of the graph renders the behaviours of the dew point of unsaturated air parcels in vertical motions?",
    "feedback": "The dashed brown lines"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the code R24R/P1500 mean?",
    "feedback": "RVR RWY 24 right above 1500 metres."
  },
  {
    "question": "A 300 hPa pressure level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "feedback": "FL 300"
  },
  {
    "question": "The warm sector is indicated by letter:",
    "feedback": "C"
  },
  {
    "question": "The height and the temperature of the tropopause are respectively in the order of",
    "feedback": "16 km and -75°C over the equator"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flies through nimbostratus clouds on a warm front, with the 0°C isotherm being at 6000 ft and the local QNH measured at 994 hPa. At which flight level would the airframe icing caused by freezing rain be the most severe?",
    "feedback": "At or near the 0°C isotherm"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Lisbon (LPPT) to Kingston (MKJP):\n\nAt 40°N 20°W, the temperature deviation from ISA at FL 390 is",
    "feedback": "0°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following correctly describes how area forecasts of upper-air meteorological phenomena, for pre-flight planning purposes, are produced?",
    "feedback": "The responsible World Area Forecast Centre provides gridded data of forecast upper-air phenomena including winds, icing, and turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "An isothermal layer may exist when in that layer:",
    "feedback": "The ELR is lower than the SALR"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cloud type most applicable to square 2C is",
    "feedback": "AS"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are planning a flight from Lisbon to Palermo. The latest TAF and SIGMET for Palermo show no indication of cumulonimbus (CB) clouds or thunderstorm activity in the area.\nHowever, while checking additional resources, you come across an online thunderstorm reporting tool that shows active CB clouds and thunderstorms southwest of Palermo. Given this information, should you still take the risk of turbulence and thunderstorm activity into account during your approach into Palermo?",
    "feedback": "During the flight planning phase, pilots may use multiple sources to prepare for the flight. They may expect CB clouds and thunderstorms in the vicinity of the airport"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cloud type most applicable to square 3C is",
    "feedback": "NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is about to line up on the runway. ATC provides the Runway Visual Range. This indicates the range at which the pilot can do which of the following?\n1) See the runway surface markings2) Locate the precision approach path indicators3) Confirm the runway designator4) Clearly see six centre line lights5) See the lights delineating the runway6) Identify the runway centre line",
    "feedback": "1, 5, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aircraft making an approach to an airfield located in square 3B, the most likely weather conditions in winter time are",
    "feedback": "low cloud, mist"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the vicinity of industrial areas, smoke is most likely to affect ground visibility when",
    "feedback": "there is a low level inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the QFE at Locarno (200 metres above sea level) is 980 hPa, what is the approximate QNH ?\n(barometric lapse rate 27 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "1005 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "The arrows labelled \"u\" represent the tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "feedback": "July to October and are called typhoons"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following cloud types are most likely to produce light to moderate icing when they are not subject to orographic lifting and consist of supercooled cloud droplets?",
    "feedback": "Altocumulus and altostratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Mountain-wave airflow is commonly characterised by the fact that it .....",
    "feedback": "has an oscillating motion on the leeward side of the mountain range"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is correct regarding the dissipation of the Nocturnal Jet?",
    "feedback": "It dissipates in the morning as the air warms and vertical mixing sets in"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following an alert received from the Low Level Wind Shear Alerting System (LLWSAS), ATC informs the crew of an aircraft on approach:\n\"Wind shear alert, centre-field wind 150 at 12, north-east boundary wind 060 at 25\".\n(The centre-field wind is obtained from an anemometer approximately in the middle of the airfield, the north-east boundary wind from a different anemometer near that location).\nHow should this message be interpreted?",
    "feedback": "The change in wind direction and speed may indicate an active downburst"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from B to A on the diagram at FL090. About halfway through the flight, a cold front is passed. The wind direction (1) ....... and the wind speed will (2) ........",
    "feedback": "(1) veer; (2) decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is relative humidity?",
    "feedback": "The ratio of the actual water vapour content in the air to the saturated water vapour content of the air at a given temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind indicator for a weather observation receives the measured value from an anemometer. Where is this instrument placed?",
    "feedback": "On a mast 8-10 m above the ground."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is parked overnight prior to an early morning departure. The crew notice a slight glistening on top of the wings. The wings look clear though. The pilot should, under these conditions, appreciate that:",
    "feedback": "the aircraft should be sprayed with de-icing fluid of the correct type"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which aircraft is experiencing the greatest headwind, when flying close to the surface?",
    "feedback": "Aircraft C"
  },
  {
    "question": "The relative humidity of a sample air mass is 50%. How is the relative humidity of this air mass influenced by changes of the amount of water vapour in it?",
    "feedback": "It increases with increasing water vapour."
  },
  {
    "question": "Above and below a low level inversion the wind is likely to",
    "feedback": "change significantly in speed and direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "The rate of cooling of ascending saturated air is less than the rate of cooling of ascending unsaturated air because:",
    "feedback": "heat is released during the condensation process"
  },
  {
    "question": "What pressure is defined as QFE?",
    "feedback": "The pressure at field elevation"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flies into supercooled rain in an area with a temperature below 0°C. The type of icing it will most likely encounter is:",
    "feedback": "clear ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "The average forecast wind for the leg from Madrid to Dhahran at FL 390 is",
    "feedback": "270/50"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a significant weather chart, we see the information according to the graph for the area where a VFR flight will take place.\n                       \nIf the flight is planned at FL 85, we can estimate that",
    "feedback": "we will probably have to divert around some cumulus tops."
  },
  {
    "question": "The pressure system located over the Atlantic Ocean, spanning from 40° N to 50° N, is called:",
    "feedback": "Westerly wave"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements: 1) The SW monsoon which occurs over certain land areas between 0° and 23°N is a typical summer phenomenon 2) Tropical cyclones never occur over the Atlantic Ocean between 0° and 23°N",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What extends outward from a high pressure system?",
    "feedback": "The correct answers are: Ridge, Col"
  },
  {
    "question": "FL 140, an OAT -12°C is measured. What will the temperature be at FL 110, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "-6°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mountains can affect ice accretion, due to orographic intensification, because ....",
    "feedback": "the air is forced to rise over the topographical barrier and supercooled water droplets may be formed on the windward side"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the option which correctly describes the figure:",
    "feedback": "1 - Pressure Gradient Force, 2 - Geostrophic wind, 3 - Coriolis Force"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is a ceiling defined?",
    "feedback": "Height above ground or water of the lowest layer of cloud below 20000 ft covering more than half of the sky."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the figures correctly represents the relationship between the height of the tropopause, the height of the core of the jet stream, and wind direction in the Northern Hemisphere?",
    "feedback": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cloud in the image is a (1) ..... which is formed by (2) ..... and triggered by (3) ..... . The vertical growth of the cloud is restricted by (4) ..... .",
    "feedback": "(1) Cumulus, (2) convection, (3) heating from below, (4) a subsidence inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the SWC for ICAO area EURO, a jet stream is located around 50°N and its core is at FL320. The crew should avoid flying (1) ..... and just (2) ..... the jet core in order to avoid the area where turbulence is most likely to be expected.",
    "feedback": "(1) in the cold air, (2) below or near"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select two aviation hazards you would find at E4:",
    "feedback": "Windshear, +RA"
  },
  {
    "question": "The greater the pressure gradient the",
    "feedback": "closer the isobars and the stronger the wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is planning a route segment where the highest obstacle is 4530 feet. What is the lowest safe flight level, taking the following information into account?\nForecast regional QNH: 1029 hPaRegional temperature forecast at 2000 feet AMSL: +22°C",
    "feedback": "FL060"
  },
  {
    "question": "A zone of strong convection currents is encountered during a flight. In spite of moderate gust you decide to continue the flight. What are your precautionary measures?",
    "feedback": "Decrease the speed / try to climb above the zone of convective currents if aircraft performance parameters allow."
  },
  {
    "question": "You intend to overfly a mountain ridge at an altitude of 15000 ft AMSL. The average air temperature is 15°C lower than ISA, the sea level pressure 1003 hPa. Which altimeter indication (standard setting) is needed?(barometric lapse rate 27 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "16170 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The surface wind velocity (°/kt) at PARIS/CHARLES-DE-GAULLE at 1330 UTC was",
    "feedback": "270/04"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following METAR is given:\nKDRA 271235Z 21007KT 5000 26/M03 Q1018 NOSIG=\nThe airport is at an elevation of 210 below MSL.\nWhich statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "QFF is greater than QNH"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is approaching an airport (elevation 643 ft AMSL) in the following conditions:\n01002KT 9999 OVC024 M20/M22 Q0993\nWith the QNH 0993 set in the subscale, what altitude does the altimeter indicate on landing?",
    "feedback": "643 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the low level winds between the subtropical high pressure belt and the ITCZ?",
    "feedback": "Trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a clear night, a Cargolux 747 freighter takes off from King Khalid International Airport in Riyadh, Saudi Arabia. A short time after lift-off, climb performance is significantly worsened. What is the probable reason?",
    "feedback": "A strong temperature inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is parked at an uncontrolled airfield and there is no reported local QNH setting. The airport elevation is 1411 ft and the pilot sets the altimeter to indicate 0 ft. Which barometric pressure would the altimeter indicate?\nLocal barometric pressure:",
    "feedback": "At the airport datum - QFE"
  },
  {
    "question": "The icing in cloud which forms over hills is likely to be more severe than in the same type of cloud over level terrain because",
    "feedback": "enforced ascent of air releases more water, which is retained in the cloud by the increased upward components"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the tracks (dashed lines) is represented by the cross-section?",
    "feedback": "Track D-A"
  },
  {
    "question": "A parcel of air is said to be saturated if it has a relative humidity of:",
    "feedback": "100 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft in straight and level flight may suddenly experience clear air turbulence (CAT), which may ....",
    "feedback": "cause structural damage to the aircraft, potentially shortening its fatigue life"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following sets of conditions are most likely to lead to the formation of advection fog?",
    "feedback": "A mild moist airstream flowing over colder surfaces with the wind speed less than 15 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 250, OAT = -45°C. The QNH, given by a meteorological station at MSL is 993.2 hPa.\nCalculate the approximate True Altitude of this aircraft (barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa):",
    "feedback": "23400 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The morning following a clear, calm night when the temperature has dropped to the dewpoint, is likely to produce",
    "feedback": "radiation fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "What winds are mainly associated with the winter monsoon regions of the Indian sub-continent?",
    "feedback": "Northeasterly winds bringing dry and hazy air."
  },
  {
    "question": "The most effective way to dissipate cloud is by",
    "feedback": "subsidence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart excerpt.The geostrophic wind at 45°N 025°W is approximately:",
    "feedback": "11525KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature gradient in the international standard atmosphere (ISA) is:",
    "feedback": "0.65°C/100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "The polar front is",
    "feedback": "the boundary between polar and tropical air masses"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is part of the runway state message?\n1) Separator2) Runway3) Type of deposit4) Braking action5) Contamination6) Depth",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Marseille Information gives you the following meteorological information for Ajaccio and Calvi for 16:00 UTC :\nAjaccio: wind 360°/2 kt, visibility 2000 m, rain, BKN stratocumulus at 1000 FT, OVC altostratus at 8000 FT, QNH 1023 hPa.\nCalvi: wind 040°/2 kt, visibility 3000 m, mist, FEW stratus at 500 FT, SCT stratocumulus at 2000 FT, OVC altostratus at  9000 FT, QNH 1023 hPa.\nThe ceilings (more than 4 oktas) are therefore:",
    "feedback": "1000 FT at Ajaccio and 9000 FT at Calvi"
  },
  {
    "question": "Although hazardous ice crystals do not appear on an aircraft's weather radar, pilot can avoid most of these concentrations in flight by....",
    "feedback": "using the weather radar to identify and avoid CBs and the areas downwind of them"
  },
  {
    "question": "If Paris reports a wind of 08010KT on the METAR, what wind velocity would you expect to encounter at a height of 2000 feet above the ground ?",
    "feedback": "11020KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena should be described as precipitation at the time they are observed?",
    "feedback": "+SHSN"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cold-air drop....",
    "feedback": "is usually most evident in the circulation and temperature fields of the middle troposphere and may show little or no sign on a surface chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind direction and velocity (°/kt) at 40°N 040°E is",
    "feedback": "330/75"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the Bora?",
    "feedback": "It is a strong, cold squally downslope wind at the Adriatic coast"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying in the northern hemisphere under tailwind conditions (cross wind component zero), which statement is correct regarding the location of pressure systems in relation to your flight path?",
    "feedback": "A low pressure area is on your left"
  },
  {
    "question": "Freezing fog exists if fog droplets",
    "feedback": "are supercooled"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main reason for implementing gridded forecast products?",
    "feedback": "Gridded forecasts help flight crews and dispatchers to better visualize flight hazards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following assessments in regard to icing and turbulence is true for the main cloud genera altostratus (AS) and altocumulus (AC)?",
    "feedback": "Flight in AS and AC may result in icing, AC has a higher probability for turbulence than AS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following circumstances most favours the development of orographic fog?",
    "feedback": "High relative humidity"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a cold front moves at 30 knots, you could expect the warm front to be moving at:",
    "feedback": "20 knots"
  },
  {
    "question": "When front \"G\" passes position \"T\", the surface wind should:",
    "feedback": "veer and increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning volume and temperature of an ascending parcel of air is correct?",
    "feedback": "The volume increases while the temperature decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "A non-occluded frontal wave passes through the airport. What form of precipitation do you expect ?",
    "feedback": "Continuous rain or snow during several hours until the warm front arrives. The precipitation stops for several hours within the warm sector. On the arrival of the cold front, showers within a couple of hours."
  },
  {
    "question": "Determine the lowest flight level which is safe to fly, providing at least 1000 feet clearance. Given:\nMaximum ground elevation: 2852 ftHeight of obstacle above maximum ground elevation: 385 ft\nMeteorological information from a station close to sea level:QNH: 1038 hPaTemperature +36°C",
    "feedback": "FL035"
  },
  {
    "question": "At the top of orographic waves, in mountainous regions, the cloud most likely to be encountered is",
    "feedback": "altocumulus lenticularis."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following instruments is used for measuring the velocity of the surface wind?",
    "feedback": "Anemometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the strongest tailwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "An airborne weather radar installation makes it possible to detect the location of:",
    "feedback": "zones of precipiation, particularly liquid-state precipitation, and also their intensity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the true statement concerning isobars and wind flow patterns around high- and low-pressure systems that are shown on a surface weather chart.",
    "feedback": "When the isobars are close together, the pressure gradient force is greater and wind velocities are stronger."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the classification of the airmass affecting position \"Q\" at 0600 UTC?",
    "feedback": "Tropical maritime."
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of cloud can produce hail showers?",
    "feedback": "CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are well separated CB clouds described on the Significant Weather Chart?",
    "feedback": "OCNL CB."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft cruises at FL 300 in an airmass, which is 15°C warmer than the Standard Atmosphere. The OAT is therefore....",
    "feedback": "-30°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under which conditions is icing most likely to occur on a wing?",
    "feedback": "Thin wing profile, fast speed, large SCWD"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the following TAF extract:\nBECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 BECMG 2124 0500 FG VV001\nWhat does the abbreviation \"VV001\" mean?",
    "feedback": "Vertical visibility 100 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at 2600 ft with the altimeter set to 1000 hPa (QNH of a nearby airfield at 600 ft). Considering that the air mass at the airfield is on average 8°C warmer than standard, calculate the aircraft's true altitude over the field:",
    "feedback": "2664 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The sea breeze is a wind from the sea",
    "feedback": "occurring only in the lower layers of the atmosphere in daytime"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true with regard to mountain waves?",
    "feedback": "Flight with headwind toward high ground is likely to be more hazardous than flight with tailwind toward high ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "A tornado, when compared to a dust devil, is normally (1) ....... in diameter, and it originates from (2) ........",
    "feedback": "(1) wider; (2) a cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will be the effect on the reading of an altimeter of an aircraft parked on the ground shortly before an active cold front passes?",
    "feedback": "It will be increasing."
  },
  {
    "question": "An observer on the northern hemisphere is under influence of the wind system of a depression, which is moving from West to East. The centre of the depression passes to the South of the observer. For this observer the wind direction is",
    "feedback": "continuously backing"
  },
  {
    "question": "When air reaches its saturation vapour pressure it immediately becomes:",
    "feedback": "slightly warmer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Convective activity over land in mid-latitudes is greatest in",
    "feedback": "summer in the afternoon."
  },
  {
    "question": "On a cloudless night, just after midnight, you are approaching an aerodrome which is located in a valley surrounded by slightly higher terrain. On final, 500 ft above ground level, a tailwind component of 12 kt is observed.\nThe reported surface wind is calm. As the approach is continued closer to the runway, the indicated airspeed (IAS) can be expected to suddenly (1) .... and the air density to (2) ..... .",
    "feedback": "(1) increase (2) increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO Annex 3, \"visibility\" is defined as:\n1) The greatest distance at which a black object of suitable dimensions can be seen and recognized when observed against a bright background\n2) The greatest distance at which lights in the vicinity of 10000 candelas can be seen and identified against an unlit background",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements correctly describes the occurrence of a cold-air drop and one of the associated hazards for aviation?",
    "feedback": "Cold air becomes trapped, creating an area of low pressure aloft, which causes instability"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart excerpt.What is the approximate geostrophic wind at 55°N 005°E?",
    "feedback": "31015KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: Which airport has the biggest probability for the formation of fog the following night?",
    "feedback": "LFPO"
  },
  {
    "question": "FT LSZH 211200Z 2112/2218 22018G35KT 9999 SCT012 BKN030  TX15/2115Z TN05/2206Z  TX 17/2214Z BECMG 2113/2115 25025G45KT TEMPO 2117/2120 4000 +SHRA BKN025TCU BECMG 2120/2122 25015KT=\nWhich of these statements best describes the weather most likely to be experienced at 1500 UTC on the 21st day of the month?",
    "feedback": "Visibility 10 kilometres or more, ceiling 3000 feet, wind 250°, temperature 15°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of these cloud types can icing be virtually ruled out?",
    "feedback": "CS"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the classification of the air mass affecting Brest airport (LFRB)?",
    "feedback": "Maritime tropical."
  },
  {
    "question": "Air density and pressure vary with altitude. At approximately what altitude is the density 50% of that at sea level, considering ISA conditions?",
    "feedback": "22000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "From what type of cloud does drizzle fall ?",
    "feedback": "Stratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following cloud is classified as low level cloud ?",
    "feedback": "ST"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"480\" below the jet stream means:",
    "feedback": "The top of the jet stream's vertical depth"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which phenomenon can be experienced in a cold-air drop (cold air pool) at the surface?",
    "feedback": "Low visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct as regards fog, mist or haze?",
    "feedback": "Fog is water that has condensed close to ground level, producing a cloud of very small droplets that reduces visibility to less than 1 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which conditions or factors determine the type of an air mass according to the classifications used by the weather services?",
    "feedback": "The latitude and the surface characteristics of the original area"
  },
  {
    "question": "A gust front is",
    "feedback": "formed by the cold air outflow from a thunderstorm"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Northern Hemisphere, an aircraft flies from A to B:",
    "feedback": "The wind is increasing and veering"
  },
  {
    "question": "An inversion is",
    "feedback": "an increase of temperature with height"
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of information given by an airborne weather radar is a map with an indication of:",
    "feedback": "Precipitation and its intensity"
  },
  {
    "question": "A parcel of air contains 15 grams of water vapour per kilogram of air. The maximum it could hold is 20g/kg of air. What is its Relative Humidity (RH)?",
    "feedback": "75 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the characteristics of a tropical squall line?\n1) Convective rains2) Duration of several months3) Small vertical extent4) Long anvil clouds5) Strong winds",
    "feedback": "1, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about winds are correct or incorrect?\n1) Foehn is a warm downslope wind\n2) Mountain wind is a cold upslope wind",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Generally northern hemisphere winds at 5000 FT/AGL are southwesterly while most of the surface winds are southerly. What is the primary reason of difference between these two wind directions?",
    "feedback": "Friction between the wind and the surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "The change in the angle of incidence of sunlight through the seasons results in ....",
    "feedback": "two transitional climate zones in each hemisphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the source of tropical continental air that affects Europe in summer?",
    "feedback": "The southern Balkan region and the Near East."
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the North Atlantic region between 30°N and 65°N together with the adjacent land areas during winter, the normal disposition of the main anticyclones at the surface is",
    "feedback": "Azores, Siberia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hazardous hailstones, reaching the ground, are most likely to be experienced below CB clouds situated:",
    "feedback": "in continental interiors in middle latitudes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Precipitation in the form of showers occurs mainly from",
    "feedback": "convective clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "The approximate mean wind component (kt) along true course 180° from 50°N to 40°N at 005° W is",
    "feedback": "tail wind 55 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Frontal fog is most likely to occur",
    "feedback": "in advance of a warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true concerning advection fog?",
    "feedback": "It can be formed suddenly by day or night"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of air movement is associated with the centre line of a trough?",
    "feedback": "Convergence with lifting."
  },
  {
    "question": "St. Elmo's fire near thunderstorms can be described as...",
    "feedback": "an electric discharge from the aircraft caused by static build-up on the airframe"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which clouds, normally found in the medium level, can extend to the other levels?",
    "feedback": "NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "The METAR for your destination aerodrome reads:\nEGUB 280950Z 05019KT 9999 BKN032TCU 03/M00 Q1000 TEMPO 1000 +SHSN\nWhat does the \"TEMPO 1000 +SHSN\" mean?",
    "feedback": "During the next 2 hours, heavy snow showers, lasting less than 1 hour in total, will reduce visibility to 1000 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are planning to fly across a mountain range. The chart recommends a minimum altitude of 12000 feet above mean sea level. The air mass you will be flying through is an average 10°C warmer than ISA. Your altimeter is set to 1023 hPa (QNH of a nearby airport at nearly sea level). What altitude will the altimeter show when you have reached the recommended minimum altitude?",
    "feedback": "11520 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cloud type most applicable to square 2B is",
    "feedback": "CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air consists of various gases. Which constituent can occur at jet cruise altitude and poses a hazard when inhaled in large quantities?",
    "feedback": "Ozone"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 38662 FT pressure level (FL 390) ?",
    "feedback": "200 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "The average temperature below FL200 is ISA +5°C. What is the vertical distance between FL070 and FL190?",
    "feedback": "12240 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The crew of an aircraft flying from London Heathrow (EGLL) to Palma de Mallorca (LEPA), when passing to the west of Paris, wish to check the latest weather at aerodromes in the vicinity, in case of the need for an in-flight diversion. To obtain this information what single source of meteorological information, available through VHF, could the crew consult?",
    "feedback": "VOLMET"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct concerning rotors below the crest of a mountain wave?",
    "feedback": "The wind direction at the lower side of the rotors is opposite to the prevailing wind direction."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which best describes the maximum intensity of icing, if any, at FL150 in the vicinity of BUCHAREST (45°N 026°E) ?",
    "feedback": "Moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What visibility is most likely to be experienced during an approach into Madrid at 2300 UTC ?\nTAF LEMD 281200Z 281812 13005KT CAVOK TEMPO 1821 8000 SCT020 SCT030 BECMG 2123 21005KT 9999 SCT015 BKN080 PROB40 TEMPO 2306 6000 SCT008=",
    "feedback": "10 kilometres or more"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements: 1) The summer monsoon in India is a NE monsoon 2) Hurricanes usually occur in winter",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is on an airport with QFE 1015 hPa. The altimeter is set to QNH 1010 hPa.\nDetermine the altimeter reading on the ground:",
    "feedback": "minus 150 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather conditions in the region of the Alps would you expect with Foehn from south?",
    "feedback": "Clouds, on the southern sides of passes in the Alps"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct?\n1) The top of stratus clouds just below a subsidence inversion is a common place for aircraft icing2) Hoar frost can form on an aircraft even when the skin temperature is above 0 degrees Celsius3) Rime ice is formed by small, supercooled water droplets4) Temperature have to be very low for ice crystal icing to occur",
    "feedback": "3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The map depicts tropopause heights in March. Which region and tropopause heights does this temperature profile correspond to?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the lowest tailwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the expected upper wind patterns in July?",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QFF at an airfield located 400 metres above sea level is 1016 hPa. The air temperature is 10°C higher than a standard atmosphere. What is the QNH?",
    "feedback": "More than 1016 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following combinations contain the greatest air density?",
    "feedback": "High pressure and low temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "When high level convergence occurs in the atmosphere the surface pressure:",
    "feedback": "Rises in the area below and the air subsides"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a significant weather chart, hail is represented by symbol",
    "feedback": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Radiation inversions mainly develop over:",
    "feedback": "Inland areas during cloudless winter nights"
  },
  {
    "question": "A low level flight departs from Stockholm Arlanda (ESSA) westbound as depicted with the red arrow. Which of the following meteorological hazards can be expected shortly after departure?",
    "feedback": "FZRA"
  },
  {
    "question": "The validity of a routine TAF is",
    "feedback": "stated in the TAF"
  },
  {
    "question": "During flight in clouds, which of the following means is the best one to identify the position of embedded CBs?",
    "feedback": "Weather radar"
  },
  {
    "question": "Except for the cold highs at the poles, the Earth's pressure zones shift position in accordance with the seasonal position of the sun. In the Northern Hemisphere, during summer, what happens to the pressure zones?",
    "feedback": "They migrate towards the North Pole"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is approaching under visual flight rules an airfield whose runway is parallel to the coast. When downwind over the sea, the airfield is on the left. What wind effect should be anticipated on final approach and landing during a sunny afternoon ?",
    "feedback": "Crosswind from the left"
  },
  {
    "question": "The top of a stratus cloud is commonly supported by a capping (1) ..... immediately (2) ..... the cloud top.",
    "feedback": "(1) inversion, (2) above"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Instrumented Runway Visual Range System (IRVR) measures runway visibility. Which of the following correctly describes the averaging time period for the collected data, assuming there has been no marked discontinuity?",
    "feedback": "10 minutes for METAR or SPECI reports"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are low level clouds? State the most complete answer:",
    "feedback": "ST, NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "A convergence is a situation where the winds:",
    "feedback": "Transport more mass of air in than out"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are favourable conditions for the formation of freezing rain?",
    "feedback": "Warm air aloft from which rain is falling into air with a temperature below 0°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "What intensity and type of airframe icing is most likely to occur in a layer of stratus cloud of a limited depth at a temperature of -5°C?",
    "feedback": "Light to moderate rime ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QNH at an airfield located 200 metres above sea level is 1009 hPa. The air temperature is 10°C lower than a standard atmosphere. What is the QFF?",
    "feedback": "More than 1009 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the conditions required for the formation of hoar frost?",
    "feedback": "The temperature of the surface is lower than the dew point of the air and this dew point is lower than 0°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "During the late afternoon an air temperature of +12°C and a dew point of +5°C were measured. What temperature change must occur during the night in order to induce saturation?",
    "feedback": "It must decrease to +5°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which feature can be identified based on the satellite image provided?",
    "feedback": "Cloud height"
  },
  {
    "question": "The area H, in January, would be under the influence of the",
    "feedback": "NE monsoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which describes the maximum intensity of turbulence, if any, at FL 210 in the vicinity of the Canary Islands (29°N 015°W)?",
    "feedback": "Severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the cruise at a pressure altitude of 19000 ft, an aircraft approaches an intense upper-level trough. Considering the flight is over a mountainous area, which of the following statements correctly describes the issues regarding the aircraft's altitude that should be discussed by the flight crew?",
    "feedback": "The trough would decrease the true altitude and therefore reduce the terrain clearance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements regarding the development of valley inversions is correct?",
    "feedback": "Valley inversions often are a result of radiation cooling in combination with gravity, both affecting the air at the surface of a mountain slope."
  },
  {
    "question": "What maximum surface windspeed (kt) is forecast for BORDEAUX/MERIGNAC at 1600 UTC ?",
    "feedback": "30"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following factors have the greatest effect on the formation of the various types of ice on an aircraft ?",
    "feedback": "Cloud temperature and droplet size"
  },
  {
    "question": "The average temperature of an air mass is ISA -10°C. Determine the vertical distance between FL070 and FL040:",
    "feedback": "2880 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the Köppen Climatology model, which climatic type is being described in the following statement?\nMost of the time anticyclonic weather, very cold and dry but modified by depressions penetrating the region and bringing unsettled weather and precipitation; Temperatures below the surface temain permanently frozen. The mean temperature of all months is below + 10°C.",
    "feedback": "Polar"
  },
  {
    "question": "The correct definition of \"low drifting sand\" is:",
    "feedback": "Sand that is lifted by the wind to less than 2 m above ground level"
  },
  {
    "question": "At an airport (0 m AMSL), a QNH of 1022 hPa is observed and the temperature is unknown:",
    "feedback": "The QFF is 1022 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a land- and sea-breeze circulation the land-breeze blows :",
    "feedback": "during the night and is weaker than the sea-breeze."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the ISA deviation at FL370 with an OAT of -45°C?",
    "feedback": "+ 11.5°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "In cold clouds where ice crystals and cloud droplets coexist, most precipitation starts out as...",
    "feedback": "Snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering a primary depression, a secondary depression will most likely appear...",
    "feedback": "on a cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following instruments is used for measuring atmospheric pressure?",
    "feedback": "Mercury barometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What minimum visibility is forecast for PARIS/CHARLES-DE-GAULLE at 2100 UTC ?",
    "feedback": "6000m"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is Clear Air Turbulence?",
    "feedback": "The erratic movement of air in the absence of any significant visual clues is caused by bodies of air moving at very different speeds"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the evening, the most common reason for the dissipation of land-based fair-weather cumulus clouds is:",
    "feedback": "Cooling of the surface which stops the convection and increases the stability of the air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "After landing at an aerodrome (QNH 993 hPa) it is noticed that the altimeter is still set to 1013 hPa and that it reads 1200 feet. What is the elevation of the aerodrome above mean sea level?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "600 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the abbreviation used in METAR and TAF, when ice particles with a diameter of 4 mm have been observed?",
    "feedback": "PL"
  },
  {
    "question": "Within a short interval, several flight crews report that they have experienced strong clear air turbulence in a certain airspace. What is the consequence of these reports?",
    "feedback": "The competent aviation weather office will issue a SIGMET"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average temperature for the route Hanover-Istanbul at FL260?",
    "feedback": "-32°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "How long does a typical microburst last?",
    "feedback": "1 to 5 minutes."
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of information given by ground weather radar is a map with an indication of...",
    "feedback": "precipitation and its intensity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The geostrophic wind flows over the area of the Scandinavian peninsula and over the north eastern part of Europe (1) ..... to the isobars and in (2) ..... direction.",
    "feedback": "(1) parallel, (2) a clockwise"
  },
  {
    "question": "Surface-based temperature inversions are common during",
    "feedback": "cloud-free nights in winter when the ground is dry"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the central part of the Atlantic Ocean between 10°N and 20°N the prevailing winds are",
    "feedback": "NE trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "A special air-report",
    "feedback": "may trigger a SIGMET message"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is expected to clear terrain by 2000 ft. The elevation of the mountain is 4430 ft, local QNH at an airport of elevation 2420 ft is 994 hPa, OAT +9°C.\nCalculate the flight level in order to clear the mountain range by the specified clearance.\n(use 1 hPa = 30 ft)",
    "feedback": "FL080"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft departs an airport at night in IMC but soon informs ATC that it must return due to a partial avionics failure, an engine shutdown, and a burning smell detected in the cabin and on the flight deck. Which meteorological phenomenon did the aircraft encounter?",
    "feedback": "Lightning"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fog or mist will start to form when the air becomes saturated. This may happen when the temperature (1) ..... to the dew point temperature and/or there is (2) ..... in dew point temperature in relation to that of the air temperature.",
    "feedback": "(1) decreases, (2) an increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is planned to fly from Bangkok (B, approx. 13°N 100°E) to Manila (east of M, approx. 15°N 121°E). Assuming the track follows a straight line and the cruising FL increases from initially FL370 to FL490 halfway through the flight, where along the route is it most likely to encounter a high concentration of hazardous ice crystals?",
    "feedback": "At cruising altitude for the last 600 NM before descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is operating over the plains of Tanzania in summer at low level, with the ITCZ situated directly over Tanzania. Which of the following conditions are most likely to be experienced?",
    "feedback": "Thunderstorms with heavy rain particularly at midday"
  },
  {
    "question": "The family of medium clouds include altostratus, altocumulus and nimbostratus.  In moderate latitudes their height of base ranges from:",
    "feedback": "6500 to 23000 feet."
  },
  {
    "question": "Advection fog often forms over the sea and drifts inland. Under what conditions would advection fog be likely to form over land?",
    "feedback": "Warm moist air passing over snow-covered land"
  },
  {
    "question": "With other variables remaining constant, the base of free convective cloud will:",
    "feedback": "rise with increasing temperature at the earth's surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "The insolation is maximum:",
    "feedback": "at local noon."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a generalised zonal system of world climatic and wind circulation, zone \"u\" is an area of",
    "feedback": "NE trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"R\" is",
    "feedback": "fine and warm at first - AC castellanus and CB in the late afternoon with thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "The wind speed in the core of the jet stream west of Rome is about 80 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a mountainous area a minimum safe altitude of 8000 ft is given. An airport in the vicinity with an elevation of 0 ft reports the following data:\n\nAir temperature -24° C at FL 100\nPressure value QNH 990 hPa\n\nWhich is the lowest usable flight level under these conditions?",
    "feedback": "FL 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at FL 100 in an airmass which is 15°C colder than ISA, local QNH 983. True altitude?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "8500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ice accretion occurs when the ambient temperature is (1) .... in flight. Ice can also form when water molecules change their state directly from (2) .... to (3) .... . This process is called (4) ....",
    "feedback": "(1) 0°C or below; (2) vapour; (3) solid; (4) sublimation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The decrease in temperature, per 100 metres, in a saturated rising parcel of air at lower level of the atmosphere is approximately",
    "feedback": "0.6°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QNH at an airfield in California located 69 metres below sea level is 1018 hPa. The air temperature is 10°C higher than a standard atmosphere. What is the QFF?",
    "feedback": "More than 1018 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lowest cloud conditions (oktas/ft) at BORDEAUX/MERIGNAC at 1330 UTC were",
    "feedback": "1 to 2 at 3000"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a clear sky, continental ground surface, wind calm, the minimum temperature is reached approximately",
    "feedback": "half an hour after sunrise"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions is most conductive to the formation of clear ice?",
    "feedback": "Supercooled droplets are large and the temperatures are just below freezing"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight over the sea at FL 100 from Marseille (QNH 1016 hPa) to Palma de Mallorca (QNH 1016 hPa), the true altitude is constantly decreasing. What is the probable reason for this ?",
    "feedback": "The air at Marseille is warmer than that at Palma de Mallorca"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the SWC. Identify the hazards for a flight from Shannon (53°N 009°W) to Warsaw (52°N 021°E) at FL120. The flight will ....",
    "feedback": "pass below a CAT area but through an area of moderate turbulence and moderate icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which airport is most likely to have radiation fog in the coming night?",
    "feedback": "LSZH"
  },
  {
    "question": "An isohypse of the 500 hPa pressure surface is labelled with the number 552. This means that for all points on the isohypse the",
    "feedback": "topography is 552 decameters above MSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which typical weather condition is shown by the design for northern Italy?",
    "feedback": "High pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Typical, average characteristics of a tropical rain climate are:",
    "feedback": "Relative humidity 80%, freezing level 15000 ft, average temperature 28°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which wind systems converge on the ITCZ, when it lies at the equator?",
    "feedback": "SE trade winds and NE trade winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over which areas can tropical revolving storms occur?",
    "feedback": "Caribbean Sea, Gulf of Bengal, Indian Ocean east of Madagascar"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flying at FL 100 from Marseille (QNH 1012 hPa) to Palma de Mallorca (QNH 1006 hPa) experiences no change to true altitude. The reason for this is that :",
    "feedback": "the air at Palma de Mallorca is warmer than that at Marseille"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most dangerous form of airframe icing is",
    "feedback": "clear ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft, flying so that the altimeter indicates 2500ft with the current regional QNH set in the subscale, is flying towards an area of lower pressure. If the pilot fails to revise the subscale setting as the QNH changes, then the aircraft will:",
    "feedback": "Gradually descend"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the following aerodrome routine and special meteorological reports. Why was the SPECI released?\nMETAR LFPG 192200Z 35010KT 6000 VCTS -SHRA SCT006 FEW010 BKN020CB 08/07 Q1035 NOSIG\nSPECI LFPG 192215Z 32022G35KT 2000 TS +SHRA SCT005 BKN008CB 08/07 Q1035",
    "feedback": "The SPECI was released because of the thunderstorm's approach over the airport and the precipitations' intensification"
  },
  {
    "question": "Clouds, fog or dew will always be formed when:",
    "feedback": "water vapour condenses."
  },
  {
    "question": "A trough near the surface is an area of",
    "feedback": "convergence and widespread ascent"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do you recognize a cold-air drop?",
    "feedback": "As a low pressure area aloft (e.g. on the 500 hPa chart)"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the chart, for a direct flight from Madrid LEMD to Berlin EDDT, which of the following cruising levels would avoid all areas of forecast turbulence and icing?",
    "feedback": "FL190"
  },
  {
    "question": "A temperature of 10°C above ISA is observed at FL 180. What is the effective distance between FL 60 and FL 120?",
    "feedback": "6240 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the picture:In which of the numbered locations would you encounter a jet stream?",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying to an airport which is located on the coast at the sea level of a Norwegian fjord (a long narrow inlet of the sea). You can expect the approach to the aerodrome to be affected by sea smoke under the following conditions:",
    "feedback": "Surface air temperature -5°C, 500 ft temperature -5°C, water temperature +10°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "A given volume of 1 m3 of air is saturated with water vapour. With increasing air temperature the",
    "feedback": "relative humidity will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate yearly frequency of tropical revolving storms in the Southwest Pacific, east of Australia?",
    "feedback": "9"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a weather chart, widespread fog is indicated by:",
    "feedback": "three horizontal lines."
  },
  {
    "question": "When the subscale is set to the QNH of an airfield the pressure altimeter indicates",
    "feedback": "elevation while landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is most likely to lead to the dissipation of radiation fog ?",
    "feedback": "A marked increase in wind velocity near the ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "For both saturated and unsaturated air instability will occur when the...",
    "feedback": "environmental lapse rate is greater than both the DALR and SALR"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a thunderstorm (CB) 10 miles ahead is assessed as still being in the mature phase, what should a pilot of a light aircraft do?",
    "feedback": "He should change heading to circumnavigate the storm."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the answers below is a correct decode of part of the METAR for Barcelona/Intl?\n\nMETAR LEBL 020830Z 11008KT 070V130 9999 FEW030 SCT055 25/17 Q1013 NOSIG=",
    "feedback": "Wind direction varying between 70° and 130°\nvisibility 10 km or more\nno significant change within the next two hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Just after departure, an aircraft reported downdrafts and a sudden increase in wind speed. What was experienced?",
    "feedback": "Low level wind shear"
  },
  {
    "question": "An airport broadcasts the following METAR:\n23008KT 4500 -DZ BR OVC006 15/13 Q1008\nThe figure shows a cross-section of a frontal system during winter time. At which location is the airport most likely situated?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which choice provides the most accurate description of the meteorological feature at coordinates 56°N 20°W?",
    "feedback": "High pressure system"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the height of the tropopause normally vary with latitude in the northern hemisphere ?",
    "feedback": "It decreases from south to north."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the following TAF extract;\nBECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 TEMPO 2124 0500 FG VV001\nWhat does the abbreviation \"PROB30\" mean?",
    "feedback": "Probability of 30%."
  },
  {
    "question": "A valley inversion is formed by:\n1) Katabatic winds drawing cold air into the valley2) Anabatic winds sending warm air up the valley and forcing cold air into the valley3) Unstable air in the valley, while the inversion dissipates quickly and has no effect on aviation4) Stable air in the valley, with reduced visibility below the inversion. Downdrafts might be present5) Clouds above the mountain, stopping the top of a mountain from cooling6) Cold air settled in low-lying areas during the night, trapping warmer air above",
    "feedback": "1, 4, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "What values are used for the forecasted wind at higher levels?",
    "feedback": "Direction relative to true north and speed in knots"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the earliest time (UTC), if any, that thunderstorms are forecast for BORDEAUX/MERIGNAC (LFBD)?",
    "feedback": "1200"
  },
  {
    "question": "Visibility is reduced by water droplets to 1200 metres. This is classified as:",
    "feedback": "Mist"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is true regarding the eye of a hurricane? You can expect ....",
    "feedback": "vertical windshear"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most hazardous type of cloud that may be encountered on a cross country flight is:",
    "feedback": "Cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following describes correctly how a cold-air drop is formed?",
    "feedback": "A large mass of polar air moves to a lower latitude and becomes surrounded by warmer air. This creates a low pressure centre above the surface, known as a cold-air drop"
  },
  {
    "question": "Freezing fog consists of",
    "feedback": "supercooled water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "The frontal picture represents the situation at 0600 UTC. What is the most applicable surface weather situation at 1200 UTC over Southern England at longitude 0°?",
    "feedback": "5 to 7 oktas of stratified clouds, basis 1500 ft/GND, SHRA, BR, winds veering from south to southwest"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of weather conditions do you encounter in a cold-air drop centre?",
    "feedback": "Showers and thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "A parcel of air has a temperature of 15 degrees C and a dew point of 10 degrees C. What is its approximate relative humidity?",
    "feedback": "75 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average wind for the route Athens - Geneva at FL 160.",
    "feedback": "240/40"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the meaning of \"RERA\" in a METAR?",
    "feedback": "There has been moderate or heavy rain since the last issue of METAR."
  },
  {
    "question": "Determine whether the temperature and air pressure will increase or decrease at the location indicated in the image.",
    "feedback": "Temperature decreases, pressure increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "With all other quantities being constant, the density of the air increases with increasing",
    "feedback": "air pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over Berlin, what intensity of turbulence and icing is forecast at FL 170?",
    "feedback": "Moderate turbulence, moderate icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over the ocean at the ITCZ the prevailing surface wind is....",
    "feedback": "light with varied direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a Significant Weather Chart the thunderstorm symbol signifies:",
    "feedback": "Moderate/severe turbulence and moderate/severe icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "A mountain breeze (katabatic wind) blows",
    "feedback": "down the slope during the night."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate value of atmospheric pressure at 5500 m AMSL in comparison to the atmospheric pressure at mean sea level?",
    "feedback": "One half"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud or phenomenon is shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Virga"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 120, OAT = ISA -15°C. The QNH, given by a meteorological station with an elevation of 2500 ft is 995 hPa. Use 1hPa = 30 ft.  Calculate the True Altitude (rounded to 100 ft)",
    "feedback": "11000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is frost considered hazardous to flight?",
    "feedback": "All of the above"
  },
  {
    "question": "At FL 180, the air temperature is -35°C.The air density at this level is:",
    "feedback": "Greater than the density of the ISA atmosphere at FL 180."
  },
  {
    "question": "The duration of the cumulus stage (building stage) of a single-cell TS is:",
    "feedback": "15-20 min"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following best describes a Monsoon?",
    "feedback": "During the summer, the large-scale, low-level wind predominantly blows from the ocean towards the continent, but during the winter, it blows from the continent towards the ocean"
  },
  {
    "question": "For 1300 UTC select a METAR which you consider to be most appropriate to position 'T':",
    "feedback": "19010KT 6000 RA BKN016 OVC090 08/06 Q1004="
  },
  {
    "question": "The absence of regular convection in the stratosphere due to warmer layers higher up and cooler ones lower down makes this part of the Earth's atmosphere...",
    "feedback": "generally turbulence-free"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Lisbon (LPPT) to Kingston (MKJP):\n\nConsidering the route segment between 60°W and 70°W, at FL 390 the forecast mean temperature is",
    "feedback": "-55°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Complete the following statement according to the figure.\nMountain waves and rotors are expected at ..... and ..... respectively.",
    "feedback": "3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart excerpt.The geostrophic wind at 45°N 030°W is approximately:",
    "feedback": "21045KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is correct regarding a warm anticyclone?",
    "feedback": "It increases in intensity with increasing altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements: 1) A blocking high must be a warm high 2) Sea-breeze fronts only occur in mid-latitudes",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the northern hemisphere, what is the average lifespan of a cold-air drop at height in a position to the south of the normal polar front?",
    "feedback": "2 to 3 days"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average temperature for the route Zurich - Rome at FL 110.",
    "feedback": "-9°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Thunderstorms in exceptional circumstances can occur in a warm front if",
    "feedback": "the warm air is convectively unstable."
  },
  {
    "question": "On an upper wind and temperature chart:",
    "feedback": "the pressure is constant all over the chart."
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is preparing for a flight and needs to know if volcanic ash is present along the route. Which source provides this information?",
    "feedback": "SIGMET"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Foehn wind is a",
    "feedback": "warm fall wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "While descending through FL130, the clouds shown on the picture are observed. What type of clouds are to the left of the image?",
    "feedback": "Altocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena can provide the initial lifting leading to air mass thunderstorms?",
    "feedback": "Advection of cold air over a warm sea"
  },
  {
    "question": "A microburst phenomenon can arise in the",
    "feedback": "downdraught of a cumulonimbus at the mature stage."
  },
  {
    "question": "During an adiabatic process heat is",
    "feedback": "neither added nor lost"
  },
  {
    "question": "If CAVOK is reported then",
    "feedback": "no low drifting snow is present"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the meaning of the following weather  message?\n… CNL WS WRNG 1 211130/211330=",
    "feedback": "The first wind shear warning on the 21st of that month, issued at 1130 UTC has been cancelled at the same day at 1330 UTC."
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass affecting position B is most likely to be:",
    "feedback": "Maritime polar."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the meaning of the abbreviation \"SCT\" ?",
    "feedback": "3 - 4 oktas"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. The centre of an anticyclone is located at 53°N 011°W, to the west of southern Ireland and has been affecting the surrounding area, including the UK, for several days. During the 20th February, the centre of this anticyclone is forecast to move east. Which of the following meteorological phenomena could you expect on the west coast of Wales (53°N 005°W) between midday and midnight on the 20th February?",
    "feedback": "Advection fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the ISA temperature at FL 110?",
    "feedback": "-7°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flying from A to B as shown at 500 ft altitude will experience (1) ..... from the (2) ..... .",
    "feedback": "(1) tailwind, (2) right"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the diagram. Assuming the usual direction of movement, to which position will the polar frontal wave have moved ?",
    "feedback": "Position C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the lowest tailwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "With what type of cloud is \"+TSRA\" precipitation most commonly associated?",
    "feedback": "CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following describes the Ice Water Content (IWC) of a cloud?",
    "feedback": "The IWC is measured in g/m3 and it reaches maximum values in the upper levels of the core of convective systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which weather conditions are most likely to be connected with a flat/uniform pressure distribution?",
    "feedback": "The development of local wind systems, like the sea breeze or the valley wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart:\nYou plan a 5 hour flight on 12th March 2017 at 3000 feet altitude from Hahn (H) (50°N, 007°E) to Brest (B) (49°N, 004°W), taking off at 17:00 UTC.\nThe planned cruise altitude must be higher than 3200 ft. At what altitude must the aircraft fly to avoid moderate to severe icing?",
    "feedback": "It is impossible to avoid icing on this route"
  },
  {
    "question": "In region E, the air tends to become or remain non-turbulent because it is absolutely (1) .... and the (2) ....",
    "feedback": "(1) stable, (2) ELR is lower than the SALR"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 100, OAT = ISA -15°C. The QNH, given by a meteorological station at an elevation of 3000 ft MSL is 1035 hPa.\nCalculate the approximate True Altitude of this aircraft (barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa):",
    "feedback": "10240 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following best describes Zone C?",
    "feedback": "Ridge of high pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying an aircraft that is certified for flight into known icing conditions, the crew chooses a route with the lowest possibility of airframe icing. Which of the following routes should be chosen?",
    "feedback": "A route with dry snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nPressure altitude: 2500 ftTemperature: ISA + 18°CA height of 2000 ft is indicated on the altimeter with the QFE of a nearby aerodrome set\nWhat is the true height above the aerodrome?",
    "feedback": "2144 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "You receive the following METAR :\nLSGG 0750Z 00000KT 0300 R05/0700N FG VV001 M02/M02 Q1014 NOSIG =\nWhat will be the RVR at 0900 UTC?",
    "feedback": "The RVR is unknown, because the \"NOSIG\" does not refer to RVR."
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass affecting position \"R\" is most likely to be",
    "feedback": "Maritime polar"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature at FL 330 overhead London will be",
    "feedback": "-42°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sea smoke is normally encountered:",
    "feedback": "Over water aeras"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying in a cumulus cloud where the temperature is below zero, considering aerofoil shape and supercooled water droplet size, in which case will ice accretion be the most significant?",
    "feedback": "Thin aerofoil, large droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a weather station, at 0600 UTC, the air temperature and dew point are respectively: T = 0,5°C,Td = -1,5°C. In the METAR message transmitted by this station, the \"temperature group\" will be:",
    "feedback": "01/M01"
  },
  {
    "question": "At FL 300 between Geneva and Tunis, what mean wind would be most likely?",
    "feedback": "245/50"
  },
  {
    "question": "The isohypse 8760 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "feedback": "300 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "The front located from 10°W to 10°E ist most likely to be",
    "feedback": "a quasi-stationary front"
  },
  {
    "question": "What OAT would you expect at FL 200 over Geneva ?",
    "feedback": "-24°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions/factors control the formation of convective clouds within the ITCZ?\n1) Convergence of strong trade winds2) Subtropical high pressure zones located around 30° N/S latitude3) High water concentration from warm water masses4) The easterly jet stream",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "A convergence line is indicated by",
    "feedback": "Sector 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "What pressure does an observer at point A encounter in the next hour?",
    "feedback": "Rising pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which temperature range does mixed ice most commonly occur in NS clouds?",
    "feedback": "-7°C to -13°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure.\nWhich of the following runway state message, added to a METAR, could be decoded as follows?\nAll runways have deposits of dry snow, to an extent of 11 % to 25 % of the runway covered, to a depth of 50 mm, with a braking coefficient of 0.38.",
    "feedback": "88425094"
  },
  {
    "question": "An arctic airport situated at MSL has an initial approach altitude of 6000 ft. The approach chart stipulated that the initial approach altitude must be temperature corrected below 0°C in order to provide the necessary obstacle clearance.\nThe surface temperature is  -5°C. What should be the indication on the altimeter with the QNH correctly set to ensure the aircraft is at 6000 ft above MSL before commencing the approach?",
    "feedback": "6480 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement about the content of continuous VOLMET messages (VHF) and scheduled VOLMET messages (HF) is correct?",
    "feedback": "Both types of VOLMET messages contain trend forecasts, where available"
  },
  {
    "question": "What intensity and type of aircraft icing is likely to occur at FL 100 in a thunderstorm, with the freezing level at 7000 ft?",
    "feedback": "Moderate to severe icing due to clear ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the Köppen Climatology model, which climatic type is being described in the following statement?\nTwo main wet seasons at the equinoxes, temperature around 28°C, heavy rain showers and thunderstorms, high temperature and high humidity, light surface winds. Expected between 10°N and 10°S.",
    "feedback": "Tropical"
  },
  {
    "question": "Between which latitudes are you most likely to find the region of travelling polar front depressions during summer?",
    "feedback": "45° - 70°"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average wind for the route Athens-Kabul at FL390?",
    "feedback": "260° / 45 KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "A given volume of 1 m3 of air is saturated with water vapour. With decreasing air temperature the",
    "feedback": "relative humidity will remain the same"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions are you most likely to encounter when approaching an active warm front at medium to low level ?",
    "feedback": "Low cloud base and poor visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "A temperature increase with increasing altitude is called",
    "feedback": "Inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "With the development of a thunderstorm, at what stage will there be only updraughts of air?",
    "feedback": "Initial stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "In addition to a stable layer of air over a substantial mountain range, the conditions most favourable to the development of standing waves are",
    "feedback": "wind speed excess of 20 kt at the surface and increasing with height, wind direction perpendicular to the general direction of the range"
  },
  {
    "question": "The amount of the sun's heat absorbed by the Earth depends on the sun's:",
    "feedback": "elevation and duration of the insolation."
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of precipitation is characterised by translucent, round or non-uniform solid pellets with diameters of less than 5 mm, falling from stratified clouds?",
    "feedback": "PL"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the colours with which a stationary front is shown on a surface chart?",
    "feedback": "Red and blue"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the risks associated with flying in thunderstorms?",
    "feedback": "Water ingestion in the engine, turbulence, icing, and static electricity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under which conditions does a wind, similar to the Mistral, form?",
    "feedback": "Strong surface winds blowing along a river valley"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the typical differences between the temperature and humidity between an air mass with its origin in the Azores and an air mass with its origin over northern Russia ?",
    "feedback": "The air of the Azores is warmer and more humid than the North-Russian air."
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider gridded forecast products. Numerical weather prediction handles and processes data within defined grid units. Which option most correctly completes the phrase?\nThe grid units are defined by ....",
    "feedback": "horizontal, vertical, and time coordinates"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the relative movement of the two airmasses along a cold front ?",
    "feedback": "Cold air pushes under a warm air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wind shear is experienced when:",
    "feedback": "There is a ground inversion and strong winds above the inversion layer."
  },
  {
    "question": "A vertical spacing of 1000 FT, is the standard required separation between two FL. Under conditions of  cold air advection (ISA -15°C), what would the true vertical separation be?",
    "feedback": "Less than 1000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying from Paris to Copenhagen.\n\nWhich of the following flight levels would you choose in order to avoid turbulence and icing?",
    "feedback": "FL 260"
  },
  {
    "question": "A plain in Western Europe with an average height of 500 m (1600 FT) above sea level is covered with a uniform CC layer of cloud during the summer months. At what height above the ground is the base of this cloud to be expected?",
    "feedback": "15000 - 35000 FT above the terrain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather phenomena can indicate the presence of low-level windshear?",
    "feedback": "Virga"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following symbols represents a quasi-stationary front?",
    "feedback": "Symbol 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Chinook is a",
    "feedback": "warm and dry wind that forms as air descends on the leeward side of the Rocky Mountains"
  },
  {
    "question": "Air mass subsidence:",
    "feedback": "Enhances atmospheric stability and dissolves clouds at upper levels"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is correct regarding the tropopause?",
    "feedback": "There is an abrupt change in the environmental lapse rate of air temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "From which of the following pieces of information can stability of the atmosphere be derived?",
    "feedback": "Environmental lapse rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the reason for issuing the following special air report?\nARS VA812 SEV TURB OBS AT 1210Z N2020W07005 12000FT",
    "feedback": "Severe turbulence observed at 12:10 UTC"
  },
  {
    "question": "In addition to a lifting action, what are two other conditions necessary for thunderstorm formation ?",
    "feedback": "Unstable conditions and high moisture content"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term CAVOK is used when weather conditions are:",
    "feedback": "9999, NSC, NSW"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a valley an inversion can be formed by ....",
    "feedback": "katabatic winds with cold air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true of the dew point of an air mass?",
    "feedback": "It can only be equal to, or lower, than the temperature of the air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are at FL60, but you forget to switch to the standard pressure setting and remain instead on the local QNH of 1025 hPa. How much higher or lower are you from the other aircraft at FL60 with the standard pressure setting correctly set?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "360 ft lower"
  },
  {
    "question": "Approximately how much time will it take for a CB cloud to develop to the mature stage?",
    "feedback": "15 to 20 min"
  },
  {
    "question": "Up to which flight level could the effects of mountain waves be expected to be encountered?",
    "feedback": "FL600"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a route segment from A to B the highest terrain elevation is approximately 200 feet. For an instrument flight the minimum obstacle clearance is 1000 feet. The subscale of the altimeter is set to the local QNH of 1013 hPa and the temperature on the ground is  -5°C. Assume a standard temperature lapse rate. What is the approximate minimum acceptable altimeter indication during the flight on this route segment?",
    "feedback": "1300 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the route between Valencia and Charleston at FL 340, the forecast mean temperature is",
    "feedback": "-50°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air temperature of -30°C at the 300 hPa level over central Europe in summer is",
    "feedback": "High"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following changes of state is known as condensation?",
    "feedback": "Gas to liquid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions is most likely to produce severe thunderstorms, severe low-level turbulence, heavy showers of rain, and hail?",
    "feedback": "A fast-moving cold front over warm land in the summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "During which stage of thunderstorm development are rotor winds characterized by roll clouds most likely to occur ?",
    "feedback": "Mature stage."
  },
  {
    "question": "The QNH of an airport at sea level is 983 hPa and the temperature deviation from ISA is -15°C below FL100. What is the approximate true altitude of FL100?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "8500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft reports to ATC that during departure it has encountered strong downdrafts and a sudden change in wind velocity. What is the most accurate term for this phenomenon?",
    "feedback": "Low-level wind shear"
  },
  {
    "question": "A possible threat associated with the use of airborne weather radar to detect potentially hazardous conditions is...",
    "feedback": "that heavy precipitation forms a shield for the area beyond where severe weather may exist"
  },
  {
    "question": "The height of the lifting condensation level is determined by",
    "feedback": "temperature and dewpoint at the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flies from London to South France and experiences a strong wind from the right. Which of the following is correct?",
    "feedback": "The true altitude will increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "A moist, stable layer of air is forced to rise against a mountain range and the stability does not change. Which of the following phenomena may develop?",
    "feedback": "Stratified clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "METAR EGTK 090950Z 09003KT 6000 NSC 04/00 Q1031 NOSIG\nBased on the METAR, fill in the gaps:\nThere are no (1) .... under the height of (2) .... above the aerodrome, and no (3) .... at any height. No expected changes within the next (4) ....",
    "feedback": "(1) Clouds(2) 5000 ft(3) CB or TCU(4) 2 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tropical maritime air moving into area B in spring will probably give:",
    "feedback": "Advection fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "In temperate latitudes what weather conditions may be expected over land during the summer in the centre of a stationary high pressure zone ?",
    "feedback": "Calm winds, haze."
  },
  {
    "question": "In the mid-latitudes the stratosphere extends on an average from",
    "feedback": "11 to 50 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "When does frontal fog, also known as mixing fog, occur?",
    "feedback": "When very humid warm air meets with very humid cold air."
  },
  {
    "question": "What flying conditions may be encountered when flying in cirrus clouds?",
    "feedback": "Average horizontal visibility more than 1000 m; nil icing."
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average temperature for the route Geneva -Stockholm at FL 260.",
    "feedback": "-47°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Supercooled droplets are always",
    "feedback": "at a temperature below freezing"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following would the pilot of a light aircraft expect to encounter the strongest Clear Air Turbulence (CAT)?",
    "feedback": "Flying downwind from hills and mountains at low altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is encountered during the summer, over land, in the centre of a cold air drop?",
    "feedback": "Showers and thunderstorms."
  },
  {
    "question": "How, if at all, is the relative humidity of an unsaturated airmass influenced by temperature changes?",
    "feedback": "It decreases with increasing temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind tends to follow the contour lines (isohypses) above the friction layer because",
    "feedback": "the coriolis force tends to balance with the horizontal pressure gradient force"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can the grid forecast data be defined?",
    "feedback": "Latitude/longitude and vertical data (height or pressure)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a common result of subsidence ?",
    "feedback": "An inversion over a large area with haze, mist."
  },
  {
    "question": "The passage of a warm front can be associated with areas of fog. The types of fog just in advance and just after the passage are respectively",
    "feedback": "frontal fog and advection fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option correctly places, in a chronological order, the four stages of a mid-latitude depression life cycle?The stages are named and described as follows:\nOcclusion: The cold front has caught up with the warm front, the warm air has been partially lifted upDeveloped: Fronts are well defined, there is a pronounced warm sectorCyclogenesis: A disturbance and fall in pressure causes cyclonic circulationFrontolysis: All the warm air has been lifted up",
    "feedback": "Cyclogenesis, Developed, Occlusion, Frontolysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "Judging by the chart, what significant weather, if any, is forecasted?",
    "feedback": "In areas B, C, and E: Infrequent moderate, clustered severe turbulence in small areas north of N53 and west of W010"
  },
  {
    "question": "What prevents air from flowing directly from high-pressure areas to low-pressure areas ?",
    "feedback": "Coriolis force"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the dangers of flying close to the ITCZ?",
    "feedback": "Showers, strong winds, and thunderstorms at noon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two aircraft are flying simultaneously in level flight at different flight levels on opposite tracks overhead a given position.\n\nAircraft A flying at FL 070 experiences a 30 kt headwind.\nAircraft B flying at FL 060 experiences a 20 kt headwind.\n\nNone of the aircraft experiences cross wind. This wind condition will be referred to as",
    "feedback": "vertical wind shear only"
  },
  {
    "question": "What grid point parameters, produced by World Aera Forecast Centres (WAFCs) allows third parties and flight planners to create visualisations of CB flight hazards?",
    "feedback": "Horizontal extent of CB and CB cloud top height"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the troposphere the decrease of pressure per 100 m increase in height",
    "feedback": "is smaller at higher levels than at lower levels."
  },
  {
    "question": "What intensity and which type of airframe icing is most likely to occur when an aircraft descends rapidly from FL 320 (temp. -45°C) to FL 60 in warm, moist clear air?",
    "feedback": "Light or moderate hoar frost"
  },
  {
    "question": "The station pressure used in surface weather charts is",
    "feedback": "QFF"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under which condition will clear ice form quickly on the wing leading edge?",
    "feedback": "Large droplets hit the aircraft at temperatures below the freezing point"
  },
  {
    "question": "In METAR messages, the pressure group represents the",
    "feedback": "QNH rounded down to the nearest hPa."
  },
  {
    "question": "Why are indications about the height of the tropopause not essential for flight documentation in the tropics?",
    "feedback": "The tropopause is generally well above the flight level actually flown."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B at the flight level corresponding to the pressure surface of the constant pressure chart. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Your true altitude is higher over A than over B"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: State the average wind for the route Zurich-Rome, FL 110:",
    "feedback": "23015KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "If atmospheric conditions exist such that the temperature deviation is ISA +10°C in the lower troposphere up to 18000 FT, what is the actual layer thickness between FL 60 and FL 120 ?",
    "feedback": "6240 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "At a coastal aerodrome, sea smoke is reducing the visibility to less than 1000 metres. Which of the following conditions is likely to dissipate the fog?",
    "feedback": "A cold front introducing unstable air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the North Atlantic region between 30°N and 65°N, the mean position of the polar front during summer extends from",
    "feedback": "Newfoundland to N Scotland"
  },
  {
    "question": "Within a typical subtropical convective system, what area is likely to have the highest concentration of ice crystals?",
    "feedback": "The anvil or 'overshooting top' of the cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following processes is the most important one concerning the heating of the air in the troposphere?\n\nThe radiation of the sun heats",
    "feedback": "the surface of the earth, which heats the air in the troposphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of what does lenticular cloud provide evidence?",
    "feedback": "Mountain waves"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what time of the year, are the paths of north Atlantic lows moving from west to east generally, at their most southerly position?",
    "feedback": "Winter."
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot plans to depart from ESSA airport. During the briefing the meteorologist informs him/her that there is strong instability in the area and presents the following special weather report:SPECI ESSA 31035G45KT 270V360 3000 BKN010CB BKN023TCU OVC040 24/20 Q0990 RERA WS=\nGiven the information available to the pilot, a tornado....",
    "feedback": "could form because of the existent circular air motion and the prevailing low pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following lists of factors influence the climate zone at a particular place on Earth?",
    "feedback": "Latitude - air masses  - heat exchange from ocean currents - distribution of mountain barriers"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the following METAR: \nEDDM 250850Z 33005KT 2000 R26R/P1500N R26L/1500N BR SCT002 OVC003 05/05 Q1025 NOSIG=\n\nWhich of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Visibility is reduced by water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air mass acquires its basic properties:",
    "feedback": "By stagnation of the air for a long period of time over areas having particular characteristics"
  },
  {
    "question": "In winter, when descending to an airport and breaking through the boundary for a low level inversion:",
    "feedback": "Thrust will most likely increase and visibility decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over Amsterdam, what amount and general type of cloud would you expect at FL 160 ?",
    "feedback": "Mainly 5 to 8 oktas of stratiform clouds in layers"
  },
  {
    "question": "The W/V (°/kt) over position S in Ireland is",
    "feedback": "330/60"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the requirements for the formation of a thunderstorm?",
    "feedback": "An adequate supply of moisture, conditional instability and a lifting action"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where does polar continental air originate?",
    "feedback": "Siberian landmass."
  },
  {
    "question": "The tropopause is lower",
    "feedback": "over the North Pole than over the equator"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Bordeaux to Amsterdam, ETA 2100 UTC. What is the minimum visibility forecast for ETA Amsterdam?\n\nTAF EHAM 281500Z 281601 14010KT 6000 -RA SCT025 BECMG 1618 12015G25KT SCT008 BKN013 TEMPO 1823 3000 RA BKN005 OVC010 BECMG 2301 25020KT 8000 NSW BKN020=",
    "feedback": "3 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Bordeaux to Berlin at FL 180. What can be expected at cruising level?",
    "feedback": "Moderate icing about half way along the route and moderate turbulence second part of the route."
  },
  {
    "question": "At which airport is the following weather development taking place?\nTAF 231322 24014G32KT 4000 +TSRA SCT005 BKN015 BKN020CB BECMG 1416 29012KT 9999 BKN030TCU SCT100 TEMPO 8000 SHRA BKN025TCU BECMG 1922 27012KT 9999 SCT030 OVC220 = (chart 1200 UTC)",
    "feedback": "EINN"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pressure altimeter can indicate different altitudes depending on the setting. Regardless of setting it can generally be said that it indicates:",
    "feedback": "altitude corresponding to difference between reference pressure and the pressure where the instrument is."
  },
  {
    "question": "Katabatic wind is",
    "feedback": "a flow of cold air down the slope of a mountain."
  },
  {
    "question": "Air density and pressure vary with altitude. At approximately what altitude is the density 25% of that at sea level, considering ISA conditions?",
    "feedback": "40000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a stratus type cloud you find:",
    "feedback": "little convective currents and the temperature is similar to the temperature of the surrounding air at the same altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "The chart shows wind direction/speed, and temperature at various altitudes above the indicated position. Determine the weather phenomenon encountered by an aircraft departing from an airport located in the area of 5230N 0230W, shortly after take-off when passing 2000 ft, if the associated weather is nimbostratus cloud (NS) with a cloud base of 3500 ft.",
    "feedback": "Freezing rain"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the weather phenomena to be expected when flying from Perth (32°S 116°E) to Melbourne (38°S 144°E) at FL250?",
    "feedback": "Individual thunderstorms with hail and moderate or severe turbulence and ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which pilots are obliged to transmit a special air-report if they encounter severe aircraft icing?",
    "feedback": "All categories of pilots"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following meteorological phenomenon indicates upper level instability which may lead to thunderstorm development ?",
    "feedback": "AC castellanus."
  },
  {
    "question": "During periods of cloudless weather over land in the northern hemisphere the",
    "feedback": "surface wind speed tends to be highest during the mid afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud genera are shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the temperature and dew point are less than one degree apart the weather conditions are most likely to be",
    "feedback": "fog or low cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "SIGMET information is issued as a warning for significant weather to",
    "feedback": "all aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following might be described in the runway state message part of a METAR?\n1) Runway designator2) Aerodrome designator3) Extent of contamination4) Depth of deposit5) Friction coefficient6) Trend information regarding depths of deposits",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "A student pilot carried out two identical cross-country flights at 2000 ft, one in the afternoon and the other just after sunrise. On returning from the early morning cross-country flight the student remarked that this flight was much smoother and easier to fly.\nHow can this observation be explained?",
    "feedback": "The increased stability and reduced convection likely decreased the upper limit of the turbulent friction layer to below 2000 ft on the early morning cross-country flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "With other variables remaining constant, the base of free convective clouds will....",
    "feedback": "rise with increasing temperature at the Earth's surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a low pressure system at the surface, and a high pressure system in the upper air. A vertical cross-section of isobaric surfaces will show isobars curved...",
    "feedback": "downwards at the surface, and upwards in the upper air"
  },
  {
    "question": "A mountain range spans from South to North and the wind is from the west. Where is the orographic low expected?",
    "feedback": "On the leeward side of the mountain"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a saturated air mass descends down a slope its temperature increases at",
    "feedback": "a lower rate than in dry air, as evaporation absorbs heat."
  },
  {
    "question": "The figure shows a surface weather chart. What is the purpose of the inset \"geostrophic wind scale\" (GWS)?",
    "feedback": "The GWS is used to measure the geostrophic wind speed at about 3000 ft/GND by means of the distance between two isobars on the chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "In winter, after breaking through a low level inversion during descent and assuming the pilot does not intervene,",
    "feedback": "thrust most likely will increase and visibility is likely to deteriorate."
  },
  {
    "question": "A parcel of unsaturated air is forced to rise through an isothermal layer. So long as it remains unsaturated, the temperature of the parcel...",
    "feedback": "decreases 1°C per 100 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which pressure and temperature conditions may you safely assume that the minimum usable flight level at least lies at the same height, as the minimum safe altitude?",
    "feedback": "At a temperature greater than or equal to that of the ISA and where the QNH is greater than or equal to 1013 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Both cumuliform and stratiform cloud structures can present significant icing environments. There is, however, a distinction in that the cumuliform cloud structure.....",
    "feedback": "contains relatively large supercooled water droplets, which can lead to a very rapid build-up of ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is the Gulf Stream vital for the Earth's climate system?",
    "feedback": "It distributes warm water from the equator to northern regions, moderating temperatures."
  },
  {
    "question": "How would you characterise an air temperature of -15°C at the 700 hPa level over western Europe?",
    "feedback": "Low"
  },
  {
    "question": "A layer can be",
    "feedback": "stable for unsaturated air and unstable for saturated air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the strongest headwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will be the effect on the reading of an altimeter of an aircraft parked on the ground as an active cold front is passing?",
    "feedback": "It will first increase then decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: What wind speed do you expect over Rome at FL 340?",
    "feedback": "145KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following clouds may extend into more than one layer?",
    "feedback": "Nimbostratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the meaning of the symbol at position 25°N 172°W?",
    "feedback": "The lowest level of the tropopause in that area"
  },
  {
    "question": "A conditionally unstable air mass is forced to ascend a mountain slope. What type of clouds can be expected?",
    "feedback": "Clouds with considerable vertical development and associated turbulence."
  },
  {
    "question": "On which route do you expect the cross section below?",
    "feedback": "D-A"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"A\" is",
    "feedback": "mainly overcast with stratus or stratocumulus and drizzle, moderate to strong winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements: 1) The summer monsoon in the southern part of India is a NE monsoon 2) The prevailing climatic zone in Australia is the dry climate",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate speed of a 90 km/h wind, expressed in knots?",
    "feedback": "50 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot flying VFR at low level encounters an unexpected wind change exceeding 30 knots, which was not included in the low level forecasts. What type of advisory would be issued by a meteorological watch office?",
    "feedback": "AIRMET or ARS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about weather satellites are correct or incorrect?\n1) The pictures from geostationary weather satellites are generally of higher resolution than the pictures from satellites in a polar orbit\n2) Satellites in a polar orbit are closer to the earth than geostationary satellites",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the following TAF extract:\nBECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 BECMG 2124 0500 FG VV001\nWhat does the \"BECMG\" data indicate for the 18 to 21 hour time frame?",
    "feedback": "The new conditions are achieved between 1800 and 2100 UTC"
  },
  {
    "question": "Appended to a METAR you get the following runway report: 01650428\nWhat must you consider when making performance calculations?",
    "feedback": "The friction coefficient is 0.28."
  },
  {
    "question": "Good visibility in the lower levels may be expected when",
    "feedback": "cool dry air is moving over a warmer surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the most likely cause of a lack of clouds at higher levels in a stationary high?",
    "feedback": "Sinking air"
  },
  {
    "question": "When established on the final approach path, and after passing below a cloud associated with a microburst, an aircraft can experience...",
    "feedback": "pitch changes without pilot input"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft has to fly over a 14200 ft mountain chain with a minimum clearance of 2000 ft. The temperature measured at a meteorological station situated at 6500 ft is -23°C and the QNH is 1013 hPa.\nWhat altitude should the altimeter indicate?",
    "feedback": "17200 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which stage of the life cycle of a single thunderstorm cell occur both up- and downdrafts simultaneously?",
    "feedback": "Mature stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is expected to clear a terrain by 2000 ft. The elevation of the mountain is 14200 ft and the local QNH at an airport (elevation 6500 ft) is 1013 hPa, OAT  -23°C. Calculate the indicated altitude to be shown in the altimeter in order to clear the mountain range by the specified clearance.\n(use 1 hPa=30 ft)",
    "feedback": "17200 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air mass which originates over the North Atlantic between 50 and 70 degrees north and is moving in over Scandinavia is called",
    "feedback": "maritime polar air."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a characteristic phenomenon for a stable atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "Stratified clouds."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the characteristics of a cold-air drop?",
    "feedback": "A lower pressure compared to its surroundings. It can be found at higher levels"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements correctly describes the usual movements and forecasted tracks of tropical revolving storms in the southern Indian Ocean?",
    "feedback": "First to the west or southwest, then turning southerly. It is hard to predict the track exactly."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. What is the airmass at the surface at location K?",
    "feedback": "Warm sector"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which gas component of the air has the greatest importance for the weather on earth?",
    "feedback": "Water vapour"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Bordeaux to Amsterdam, ETA 2100 UTC. At ETA Amsterdam what surface wind is forecast?\n\nTAF EHAM 281500Z 281601 14010KT 6000 -RA SCT025 BECMG 1618 12015G25KT SCT008 BKN013 TEMPO 1823 3000 RA BKN005 OVC010 BECMG 2301 25020KT 8000 NSW BKN020=",
    "feedback": "120° / 15 kt gusts 25 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mountain waves should be expected",
    "feedback": "on the downwind side of the mountain chain"
  },
  {
    "question": "The possibility of significant icing at altitude should be expected when on ground you observe:",
    "feedback": "ice pellets"
  },
  {
    "question": "The arrows labelled \"r\" represent the mean tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "feedback": "December to April and are called cyclones"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of turbulence is initiated when the direction and/or speed of wind changes dramatically within a short horizontal and/or vertical distance?",
    "feedback": "Wind shear (shear turbulence)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What flight conditions are most likely to be experienced in square 2B by an aircraft at FL 120?",
    "feedback": "VMC above layers of ST and SC, generally stable conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which instrument is used for measuring atmospheric humidity?",
    "feedback": "Hygrometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Shortly after dawn, an inland aerodrome (Eindhoven, The Netherlands) reports the following METAR:\nEHEH 010610Z 33005KT 0300 R21/0450 FG NSC 06/06 Q1018 =\nConsidering the above METAR, we can say that the aerodrome is experiencing (1)...... which probably extends from the surface to (2).....",
    "feedback": "(1) radiation fog, (2) less than 300 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the life cycle of a thunderstorm, which stage is characterized predominantly by downdrafts?",
    "feedback": "Dissipating stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does temperature vary with increasing altitude in the ICAO standard atmosphere below the tropopause?",
    "feedback": "Decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Thunderstorm cells reach their greatest intensity during the",
    "feedback": "mature stage."
  },
  {
    "question": "A Maritime Polar air mass travels over warm land in the Northern Hemisphere. This can result in (1) ...... and (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) heavy showers, (2) powerful thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an unstable layer there are cumuliform clouds. The vertical extent of these clouds depends on the",
    "feedback": "thickness of the unstable layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "With what type of cloud is heavy precipitation unlikely during the summer months ?",
    "feedback": "SC, AS"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the meaning of the different coloured areas on a plan position indicator of an airborne weather radar?",
    "feedback": "Different ranges of intensities of precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an approach a pilot changes the subscale setting from standard to the reported QNH. Then, the indication of the barometric altimeter changes from a:",
    "feedback": "Flight level to an altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "The synoptic chart depicts a region in the Southern Hemisphere. What is the pressure system shown at position J?",
    "feedback": "Frontal depression"
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum amount of water vapour that the air can contain depends on the",
    "feedback": "air temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "What change in pressure will occur at point F during the next hour?",
    "feedback": "A drop in pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the symbol indicate on a significant weather chart?",
    "feedback": "The center of a tropopause \"high\", where the tropopause is at FL 400."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following clouds are shown on the figure?(It is not raining and there is no drizzle present)",
    "feedback": "SC"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which position is the development of thunderstorms most likely, and what is the maximum height of the CB clouds?",
    "feedback": "Frankfurt, FL 220"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is planning to depart from an airfield at sea level in the southern hemisphere below a layer of nimbostratus cloud with ceiling 5000 ft. The surface temperature at the airfield is +3°C, +7°C at the cloud ceiling, and it is raining. The aircraft's initial track will be towards a nearby mountain range. Which of the following phenomena might indicate a risk of icing outside of the cloud shortly after take-off?",
    "feedback": "A temperature inversion aloft between 2000 ft and 5000 ft where the temperature at 2000 ft is +4°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are squall lines?",
    "feedback": "Bands of intensive thunderstorms."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true ?",
    "feedback": "QNH can be equal to QFE"
  },
  {
    "question": "The geostrophic force is strongest:",
    "feedback": "Close to the poles"
  },
  {
    "question": "During descent, the Transition Level given by ATC is FL055. The true altitude is 6000 ft, the temperature is on average ISA + 10°C.\nCalculate the local QNH:",
    "feedback": "1021 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying in the southern hemisphere at low altitude (less than 2000 feet) and going directly away from a centre of low pressure. What direction, relative to the aircraft, does the wind come from ?",
    "feedback": "From the left and slightly on the nose"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature at FL 160 is -22°C. What will the temperature be at FL 90 if the ICAO standard lapse rate is applied ?",
    "feedback": "-8°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a correct description of Ice Crystal Icing (ICI)?",
    "feedback": "ICI forms at high altitudes and is usually associated with the anvil of a CB. A high accumulation of ice crystals can damage the engine and even cause engine failure"
  },
  {
    "question": "A warm front is approaching the destination aerodrome at approximately the same time the aircraft will make its approach. In addition to rain and low cloud, what conditions could be expected?",
    "feedback": "A band of shallow fog, clearing as soon as the front passes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Atmospheric soundings give the following temperature profile :\n3000 FT +15°C\n6000 FT +8°C\n10000 FT +1°C\n14000 FT -6°C\n18000 FT -14°C\n24000 FT -26°C\nAt which of the following flight levels is the risk for aircraft icing, in cloud, greatest?",
    "feedback": "FL 150"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the southern hemisphere what wind effect would  you expect when flying from a high pressure area towards a low pressure area at FL 100?",
    "feedback": "Wind from the right."
  },
  {
    "question": "How many tornadoes typically occur in North America every year?",
    "feedback": "more than 1000"
  },
  {
    "question": "What information is missing from this message?\nVV N4045.0 W01730.01520 FL370 REPORTED 40NMS FL350-380 _________",
    "feedback": "Wind and temperature (e.g. 270/50 and -56°C)"
  },
  {
    "question": "An isohypse (contour)",
    "feedback": "indicates the true altitude of a pressure level"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying at FL 180 in the Northern Hemisphere you experience a left drift:",
    "feedback": "Your TA increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the role of a MWO?",
    "feedback": "Analyze charts and prepare SIGMETS within the FIR"
  },
  {
    "question": "Areas of sinking air are generally cloudless because as air sinks it",
    "feedback": "is heated by compression"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud formation is most likely to occur at low levels when a warm air mass overrides a cold air mass?",
    "feedback": "Nimbostratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "In an air mass with no clouds the surface temperature is 15°C and 13°C  at 1000m. This layer of air is:",
    "feedback": "stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the anwers best describes weather fronts?",
    "feedback": "The transition zones between two different air masses. This transition zone is inclined, the warmer air mass rises, and clouds and precipitation may develop"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of air mass never occurs over Central Europe ?",
    "feedback": "Equatorial air"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the typical lifespan, in days, of a mid-latitude depression?",
    "feedback": "4 to 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "Geostrophic wind",
    "feedback": "is perpendicular to the horizontal pressure gradient force"
  },
  {
    "question": "The arrows on the image of a weather radar display indicate....",
    "feedback": "shadow areas behind heavy precipitation cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "Runway visual range can be reported in",
    "feedback": "a METAR"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a prolonged VMC descent in very cold air, you penetrate a humid air mass. What type of icing will you encounter?",
    "feedback": "hoar frost"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of fog can NOT be formed over water?",
    "feedback": "Radiation fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight over the sea at FL 100 from Marseille (QNH 1012 hPa) to Palma de Mallorca (QNH 1012 hPa), the true altitude is constantly increasing. What action, if any, should be taken ?",
    "feedback": "None, the reason for the change is that the air around Palma is warmer than the air around Marseille"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do you understand by \"Adiabatic Cooling\"?",
    "feedback": "When the pressure applied on a parcel of air is reduced, the air in the parcel is allowed to expand; as the volume increases, the temperature decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider an anticyclone. If the geostrophic wind speed is 40 kt, the gradient wind speed for the same isobar interval is ....",
    "feedback": "greater than 40 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The outside air temperature is +21°C and the dew point +9°C. Calculate the approximate relative humidity (RH):",
    "feedback": "40%"
  },
  {
    "question": "The synoptic chart depicts a region in the Southern Hemisphere. The widest zone of precipitation is to be found at location ....",
    "feedback": "L"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the evening around sunset, during final approach, westerly winds are predominant, and there is haze near the ground. Which of the following statements is correct about visibility in the last phase of the approach?",
    "feedback": "The sun is at a low position, deteriorating the visibility even more"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a stable atmosphere, which of the following wind direction would cause the strongest turbulence at the airport?",
    "feedback": "070°"
  },
  {
    "question": "During summer, a weak pressure gradient covers a coastal airfield in Eastern England resulting in mainly clear skies. The surface wind at dawn was calm.\nIf the alignment of the coastline in the vicinity of the airfield is predominantly north/south, the surface wind is likely to become",
    "feedback": "easterly to south-easterly and increase in velocity by afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "\"Solid precipitation which is transparent or translucent and has a diameter of 5mm or less formed by the freezing of raindrops or refreezing of melted snow, and usually bounces off hard surfaces\", is a description of",
    "feedback": "ice pellets"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which route of flight does the height of the tropopause vary the most?",
    "feedback": "Route 2: Keflavik - Brussels"
  },
  {
    "question": "The speed of a warm front is approximately ......",
    "feedback": "10 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the statements below describes either the coalescence process or the Wegener-Bergeron-Findeisen process,  concerning the formation of precipitation?",
    "feedback": "The coalescence process involves collisions between water droplets of different size"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the strong relatively cold katabatic wind, blowing down the northern Adriatic coast, mainly during the winter and spring called?",
    "feedback": "Bora."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following thunderstorms produce the most severe conditions, such as heavy hail and destructive winds?",
    "feedback": "Squall line thunderstorms."
  },
  {
    "question": "When water evaporates into unsaturated air",
    "feedback": "heat is absorbed"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a large area covered by an air mass of uniform density and situated in the northern hemisphere, isobars on the weather map are equidistant. In this case, geostrophic wind speed",
    "feedback": "increases when travelling south"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are high level condensation trails formed that are to be found occasionally behind jet aircraft ?",
    "feedback": "Through water vapour released during fuel combustion"
  },
  {
    "question": "The average position of the ITCZ varies over the year.\nWhich zone (1) indicates its most northerly position and when (2) does this occur?",
    "feedback": "(1) T, (2) July"
  },
  {
    "question": "You cruise at FL 200 and notice an OAT of -35°C. The airmass has therefore an average temperature which is....",
    "feedback": "10°C colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements:\n1) The transfer of heat by radiation and advection is non-adiabatic\n2) The ascent and descent of air cause adiabatic changes of temperature",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of lightning is represented in the picture?",
    "feedback": "Cloud to air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following groups of conditions requires a crew to transmit a special air-report (subsonic air transport)?",
    "feedback": "Severe turbulence; widespread thunderstorms; severe mountain waves"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following choices lists only main cloud genera that are mostly the clue for an unstable thermal stratification in the atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "Cirrocumulus, altocumulus, cumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why are polar regions colder than equatorial regions?",
    "feedback": "Because the angle of incidence of the solar radiation is very small in polar regions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following statements concerning the formation of aircraft icing is most correct ?",
    "feedback": "A cloud consisting of both supercooled cloud droplets and ice crystals produces aircraft icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What may be expected after take-off from a runway located in a low cold-air pool (valley inversion) on the lee side of a mountain?",
    "feedback": "Wind shear when crossing the inversion layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which air mass are extremely low temperatures encountered?",
    "feedback": "Polar continental air."
  },
  {
    "question": "At which average height can the 500 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "feedback": "5,5 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "In relation to the total weight of the atmosphere, the weight of the atmosphere between mean sea level and a height of 5500 m is:",
    "feedback": "50 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "The initial phase of a thunderstorm is characterized by",
    "feedback": "continuous updrafts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart:\nAn aircraft is planned to fly from Nairobi to Manila (marked with red circles). Assuming the track follows a straight line between the two points on the chart, and the cruising FL increases from initially FL370 to FL490 before Top of Descent (TOD), where along the route is it most likely to encounter a high concentration of hazardous very small ice crystals?",
    "feedback": "Clear for the first approximately 1500 NM and then likely for the remaining portion of the cruise"
  },
  {
    "question": "Your departure aerodrome lies at the bottom of a valley in the mountains. Overnight, with clear skies, the wind has started to blow down the mountainside. The air temperature at 1000 ft AGL is +2°C. What temperature could be expected at the airport just after sunrise?",
    "feedback": "-1°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which kind of meteorological messages are normally transmitted in a VHF-VOLMET broadcast within Europe?",
    "feedback": "METAR / SPECI"
  },
  {
    "question": "FL 160, an OAT -22°C is measured. What will the temperature be at FL 90, if you consider the temperature gradient of the Standard Atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "-8°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are planning a flight at FL 290, which of these upper wind and temperature charts would be nearest your flight level ?",
    "feedback": "300 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is true of a secondary depression in the northern hemisphere?",
    "feedback": "It tends to move round the primary in a cyclonic sense"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air mass is a body of air that",
    "feedback": "covers an extensive area and has fairly uniform properties of temperature and moisture."
  },
  {
    "question": "The unit(s) of distance used in RVR reporting is/are:",
    "feedback": "Metres or feet at the discretion of the State concerned"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over LONDON (51°N 000°E/W), the lowest FL listed which is unaffected by CAT is:",
    "feedback": "280"
  },
  {
    "question": "Lines connecting points of equal pressure are called:",
    "feedback": "Isobars."
  },
  {
    "question": "On which of the following aviation weather charts can a pilot most easily find a jetstream?",
    "feedback": "Significant weather chart."
  },
  {
    "question": "Different reports of the surface wind at an aerodrome are listed below. Which of the statements best explains the variability in the reported surface wind?\n09:20Z METAR: 27007KT09:20Z TAF: 26006KT09:20Z Aerodrome controller: 26006KT",
    "feedback": "At larger aerodromes, the reported surface wind is measured by an anemometer at a height of 10 m and averaged over 2 minutes for ATIS and the aerodrome controller, but averaged over 10 minutes for the METAR"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the following METAR for a Spanish aerodrome in September, an hour before sunset, at what distance might a pilot expect to see the theshold of runway 26 whilst on final approach?\nMETAR LEXX 211730Z 26008KT 220V320 3000 HZ SKC Q1010",
    "feedback": "More than 1500 metres but less than 3000 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "At the same latitude the geostrophic wind is less than the gradient wind around an anticyclone with equal pressure gradient because the",
    "feedback": "centrifugal force is added to the pressure gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are in the process of planning a flight from Brussels (50°55'N 004°30'E) to Deauville (49°00'N 000°00'E) on 12th March 2017, departing at 20:00 UTC and with a flight time of approximately 3 hours. The route will follow the line from B to D on the chart, and the minimum altitude that can be flown is 3200 feet.\nWhich altitude would allow the flight to remain clear of forecasted moderate or severe icing conditions along the entire route?",
    "feedback": "Icing conditions cannot be avoided on this route"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the preparation for approach to Zurich airport (1416 ft/AMSL) a pilot hears the following message on the ATIS: \"Inversion warning. Inversion of 12°C between 1900 ft and 2300 ft altitude.\"\nThis message indicates that the pilot should be prepared",
    "feedback": "for wind shear just above the inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"B\" is",
    "feedback": "frequent showers of rain or snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which solution provides the most accurate description of the air mass at coordinates W (43°N 024°W)?",
    "feedback": "Rear of a warm front, in warm air"
  },
  {
    "question": "The arrows labelled \"v\" represent the mean tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "feedback": "December to April and are called cyclones"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which instrument is used for measuring rainfall?",
    "feedback": "Pluviometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is descending from FL230 to FL120. The temperature equals ISA +15°C. Determine the vertical distance:",
    "feedback": "11660 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which are characteristics of an unstable cold air mass moving over a warm surface ?",
    "feedback": "Cumuliform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "The synoptic chart depicts a region in the Southern Hemisphere. The worst weather with extensive clouds and showers is to be found at location  ....",
    "feedback": "M"
  },
  {
    "question": "About ten identical clouds are in the sky, well isolated from one another, dense, with well defined contours, developing vertically in a cauliflower shape. The side of these clouds lit by the sun is bright white. Their base, relatively dark, is essentially horizontal and at FL 30, and their tops at FL 150. These clouds are",
    "feedback": "towering Cumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "The rate of decrease of temperature with height per 100 m in the International Standard Atmosphere is :",
    "feedback": "0.65°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the strongest winds close to the ground?",
    "feedback": "In the transition zone between air masses"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most likely reason for radiation fog to dissipate or become low stratus is :",
    "feedback": "increasing surface wind speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "During an overcast day, the surface of the Earth underlying the clouds is mainly heated by (1) ...... solar radiation, which is (2) ..... -wave radiation.",
    "feedback": "(1) diffuse, (2) short"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which instrument is commonly used to determine the state of stability of the atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "A radiosonde"
  },
  {
    "question": "An OAT of -55°C at the 200 hPa pressure level:",
    "feedback": "equals approximately (+/-5°C) ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the following METAR and SPECI observations:\nMETAR EGVN 061450Z 22004KT 9999 SHRA VCTS SCT060CB BKN100 28/16 Q1016 BECMG 27015G30KT\nSPECI EGVN 061512Z 18007KT 6000 TSRA SCT060CB BKN100 27/15 Q1016 BECMG 27015G30KT \nThe SPECI was issued because of the .....",
    "feedback": "Onset of a thunderstorm and the associated change in intensity of precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud or phenomenon is shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Cirrus"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following circumstances is a SIGMET issued ?",
    "feedback": "Marked mountain waves."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is one major advantage of the gridded forecasts?",
    "feedback": "Data can be relayed by aircraft or pilot reports by being merged to onboard information processing systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate composition of the dry air by volume in the troposphere ?",
    "feedback": "21 % oxygen, 78 % nitrogen, and the rest other gases"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight is planned from point A (38°10'55\"N, 013°05'58\"E) to point B (48°21'14\"N, 011°47'10\"E). Assume the pressure gradient force is the same at point A and point B, what can be stated about the relationship between the geostrophic wind speeds at these two points?",
    "feedback": "The geostrophic wind speed is higher at point A than at point B"
  },
  {
    "question": "What types of cloud will you see flying at FL 50 towards a warm front ?",
    "feedback": "At some 800 km CS, later AS, and at some 300 km  NS until the front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why must a pilot be very careful when planning near a Tropical Revolving Storm (TRS) over the North Atlantic that is moving westwards and approaching the Caribbean Islands?",
    "feedback": "It is very difficult to accurately forecast the exact path of the TRS"
  },
  {
    "question": "The figures depict vertical cross sections of pressure systems. Figure 4 represents ....",
    "feedback": "a cold high pressure area"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements:\n1) Surface winds are usually closer to geostrophic balance over oceanic areas than over land\n2) Above the friction layer the wind is always geostrophic",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: Which weather situation do you expect for LGAT at 1450 UTC?",
    "feedback": "21002KT 6000 BR SCT040 29/16 Q1010 NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a generalised zonal system of world wind circulation the travelling low pressure systems are applicable to zone",
    "feedback": "s and y"
  },
  {
    "question": "A supercooled droplet is",
    "feedback": "a droplet still in liquid state at a temperature below freezing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure.The wind direction for the airport is 270/15KT on VOLMET. What wind is to be expected on short final approach to runway 33?",
    "feedback": "30° from the left"
  },
  {
    "question": "Among the ten groups of clouds, the following two are mentioned specifically in MET-reports and forecasts intended for aviation:",
    "feedback": "Cumulonimbus and towering cumulus."
  },
  {
    "question": "In a neutral stable atmosphere, the Environmental Lapse Rate (ELR) in the case of unsaturated air equals (1) ..... and the ELR in the case of saturated air equals (2) ....DARL = Dry Adiabatic Lapse Rate, SALR = Saturated Adiabatic Lapse Rate",
    "feedback": "(1) DALR, (2) SALR"
  },
  {
    "question": "In this question the wind speed with straight isobars (vst), the wind speed around a high-pressure system (vhigh) and the wind speed around a low-pressure system (vlow) in the southern hemisphere are being compared while pressure gradient and latitude are constant. Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "vst < vhigh and vst > vlow."
  },
  {
    "question": "Complete the following statement correctly to describe atmospheric divergence in relation to synoptic charts. There is a net flow of air .....",
    "feedback": "away from the area of divergence across the isobars marked on the chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flying in the southern hemisphere at 2000 feet, has to turn to the right in order to allow for drift. In which direction, relative to the aircraft, is the centre of low pressure ?",
    "feedback": "In front."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main explanation for the faster wind speeds at upper levels?",
    "feedback": "A lower density of the air"
  },
  {
    "question": "The chart shows isobars and fronts at 1200 UTC on October 10. Which of the following reports reflects weather development at Zurich Airport?",
    "feedback": "TAF LSZH 101601 VRB02KT 8000 SCT280 BECMG 1618 00000KT 3500 MIFG BECMG 1820 1500 BCFG BECMG 2022 0100 FG VV001 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "A wide body takes off on a clear night in Dhahran, Saudi Arabia. Shortly after take off the aircraft's rate of climb drops to zero. This can be due to",
    "feedback": "a very strong temperature inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at FL200 from Perth (32°S 116°E) to Jakarta (06.2°S 107°E). Select the correct statement with regard to turbulence:",
    "feedback": "During cruise, the aircraft may encounter severe turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QNH of an airport at sea level is 983 hPa and the temperature deviation from ISA is -15°C below FL 100. What is the true altitude of FL 100?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "8500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which weather phenomena are typical for the northern side of the Alps with stormy winds from the south (Foehn)?",
    "feedback": "Good visibility, turbulence."
  },
  {
    "question": "When a cumulonimbus cloud reaches its mature stage and rain starts to fall from the base, the temperature in its core (1) ...., causing the air to become (2) .... dense than its surroundings.",
    "feedback": "(1) decreases, (2) more"
  },
  {
    "question": "You plan a flight to take-off from a coastal airfield in hazy conditions during sunrise. Which of the following runways will provide the worst visibility?",
    "feedback": "09"
  },
  {
    "question": "A high pressure area (slack pressure gradient) covers an area of the Mediterranean Sea and coastal region during the summer. What surface wind direction is likely at an airport at the coast on a sunny afternoon?",
    "feedback": "Sea to land."
  },
  {
    "question": "What can you expect at FL 180, when the wind is geostrophic and you fly at a constant true altitude of 18'000 ft?",
    "feedback": "No crosswind"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cumulus congestus is",
    "feedback": "a cumulus that is of great vertical extent"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following zones is most likely to encounter little or no precipitation?",
    "feedback": "The north side of the alps with a prevailing Foehn from the south."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO, which symbol indicates danger to an aircraft in flight?",
    "feedback": "Symbol b)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true concerning frontal fog?",
    "feedback": "It may be formed by day as well as by night"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. What is the correct description of the pressure system shown by \"J\"?",
    "feedback": "Frontal depression"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option best describes turbulence?",
    "feedback": "Airflow that causes random deviations from the desired flight path which need immediate corrective action"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the correct term for the descending air flow in a large high pressure area?",
    "feedback": "Subsidence."
  },
  {
    "question": "Advection fog can be formed when",
    "feedback": "warm moist air flows over a colder surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Moist air is:",
    "feedback": "Less dense than dry air"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot wants to select an airport for arrival with a runway providing an RVR of at least 300 metres. Considering the following METARs, valid for the time of arrival, choose the appropriate airport (all other criteria for landing can be met at each airport).\nEGKK 191050Z 09002KT 0200 FZFG R08R/0250 R08L/0350 VV001 M03/M03 Q1008 88910195\nEGLF 191050Z 09002KT 0200 FZFG R06/0075D VV/// M03/M03 Q1008\nEGGW 191050Z 08004KT 0100 FZFG R08/0175U VV001 M02/M02 Q1007 RESG 08920294\nEGLL 191050Z 09002KT 0100 FZFG R09L/0200U R09R/0250U VV001 M02/M02 Q1008",
    "feedback": "EGKK"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aircraft at FL 80, ahead of the front in square 2D, the expected flight conditions are",
    "feedback": "below AS type cloud, generally smooth air with light precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud genera or phenomenon is shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Nimbostratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "As a parcel of air cools, its ability to hold water vapour:",
    "feedback": "Decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true regarding moderate-to-severe airframe icing?",
    "feedback": "It will not occur in clear-sky conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct or incorrect?\n1) Ice water content (IWC) is a special form of ice crystal icing (ICI)2) The ice mass per unit volume of air is called ice water content (IWC)",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the Köppen Climatology model, which climatic type is being described in the following statement?\nTypical subtropcial anticyclonic weather. Prevailing weather conditions are descending warm and dry air, cloudless skies. Short wet season: Low latitudes during summer. high latitudes during winter. Large diurnal temperature changes during summer.",
    "feedback": "Arid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the following atmospheric processes which can lead to high ice crystal concentrations and ice crystal icing?",
    "feedback": "Strong convective activity lifting large concentrations of moisture to high altitudes where sublimation then creates very small ice crystals"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather conditions are expected at Paris airport (LFPO) around 1300 UTC?",
    "feedback": "23014KT 3000 +RA SCT008 OVC025 15/13 Q1004 NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "Between which flight levels and at what intensity could you encounter turbulence in CAT area 2?",
    "feedback": "From FL 200 to FL 380, moderate, occasionally severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements: 1) Trade winds reach up to the tropopause 2) The air advected by the SW monsoon over West Africa has its source region in the southern hemisphere",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A routine air report (AIREP) is missing a required element. Which of the following is the missing component?\nARP SUA804 N2258 E06528 1031 F350 MS44 ____________",
    "feedback": "227/030KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Bora is a",
    "feedback": "cold catabatic wind with the possibility of violent gusts"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ICAO Standard Atmosphere assumes that temperature will reduce at the rate of",
    "feedback": "2°C per 1000 ft up to 36090 ft after which it remains constant to 65617 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate true altitude of an aircraft with an indicated altitude of 8000 ft and an OAT of +12°C, when the correct QNH is set in the subscale of the altimeter?",
    "feedback": "8416 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the technical term for an increase in temperature with altitude?",
    "feedback": "Inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering satellite meteorological data, the difference between visible and infrared (IR) images is that ....",
    "feedback": "low clouds may be difficult to identify on the IR image"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the differences between radiation fog and advection fog ?",
    "feedback": "Radiation fog forms due to surface cooling at night in a light wind. Advection fog forms when warm humid air flows over a cold surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line of the graph renders the unsaturated lapse rate?",
    "feedback": "The green lines"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"R\" is",
    "feedback": "fine and warm at first - AC Castellanus and CB in late afternoon with thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: On which route of flight would you expect no icing at FL 180?",
    "feedback": "Hamburg-Stockholm"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following areas do surface high pressure systems usually predominate over the North Atlantic region between 30°N and 65°N and the adjoining land areas during the northern summer?",
    "feedback": "Azores, SE USA, SW Europe"
  },
  {
    "question": "What conditions are most likely to lead to the formation of hill fog?",
    "feedback": "Humid stable air mass, wind blowing towards the hills."
  },
  {
    "question": "Jet streams may be found in",
    "feedback": "A3 and A8"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew is flying over a mountain ridge in Ecuador, South America, in January, when the Intertropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ) is present over the area. Which of the following hazards should the crew be prepared for?",
    "feedback": "Local low pressure, causing the altimeter to over-read"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a common cause of ground or surface temperature inversion ?",
    "feedback": "Terrestrial radiation on a clear night with no or very light winds."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flies from A to B on the weather chart. What weather phenomena will be encountered?",
    "feedback": "Freezing drizzle"
  },
  {
    "question": "In towering cumulus (TCU) clouds:",
    "feedback": "Strong updrafts occur and the temperature in the cloud is higher than in the surrounding air at the same height"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the formation of rime ice in flight, water droplets freeze",
    "feedback": "rapidly and do not spread out"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over London (EGLL), what amount and general type of cloud would you expect at FL 60?",
    "feedback": "Locally 5-7 oktas cumulus and stratocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true concerning orographic fog?",
    "feedback": "It may be formed by day as well as by night"
  },
  {
    "question": "Weather satellite images are classified by the wave range of their sensors.\n\nWhich channels are commonly used in aviation?",
    "feedback": "Infrared, visual"
  },
  {
    "question": "What wind direction will occur over the land (surface) at point E?",
    "feedback": "West"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at 2 500 FT/AGL, with a southerly wind, and intend to land at an airport, at sea level directly below. From approximately which direction would you expect the surface wind (mid-latitude, northern hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "South-southeast."
  },
  {
    "question": "By use of Doppler techniques, modern airborne weather radar can detect turbulence in...",
    "feedback": "thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about air masses are correct or incorrect?\n1) The polar ice caps are source regions of polar air\n2) Tropical air may have cold air mass properties",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Looking at the chart, at what altitude above Frankfurt would you expect the tropopause to be located?",
    "feedback": "FL 350"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"A\" is",
    "feedback": "snow showers - gale force wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "A frontal depression over Western Europe has probably formed...",
    "feedback": "4 days before over the Western Atlantic"
  },
  {
    "question": "When is the RVR reported at most airports?",
    "feedback": "When the meteorological visibility decreases below 1500 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the mean temperature deviation from ISA for the route Frankfurt - Rome at FL 180?",
    "feedback": "4°C colder than ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew receives a Runway Visual Range (RVR) from the tower with their line-up clearance. When lined up on the runway, which of the following can the pilots expect to see, given this information?\n1) Runway Centreline Lights2) PAPI Lights3) Runway Edge Lights4) Approach Lights5) Threshold Lights6) Runway Centreline Markings",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lowest height of the tropopause on the entire chart is:",
    "feedback": "FL220"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements is true?",
    "feedback": "Local snow and severe aircraft icing can be expected over Germany"
  },
  {
    "question": "A winter day in northern Europe with a thick layer of stratocumulus clouds and temperature close to zero degrees C at ground level, you can expect:",
    "feedback": "A high probability for icing in clouds. Severe icing in the upper part due to accumulation of large droplets."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are examples of grid point datasets prepared by the World Area Forecast Centres (WAFCs)?",
    "feedback": "Upper wind and temperature data, humidity, icing, and clear air turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whilst collecting pre-flight information for your flight to Parma/Italy, you are checking the SIGMETs for Europe. There is no indication of any CBs or thunderstorm activity, however, a live lightning app depicts some thunderstorms SW of Parma, moving towards Parma. Which of the following is correct?",
    "feedback": "SIGMETs may miss information, therefore, the WAFC should be contacted for additional weather updates"
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of cloud formed when warm, light air rises rapidly into cooler air is a:",
    "feedback": "Cumulus-type."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is expected to clear terrain by 2000 ft. The elevation of the mountain is 6254 ft, local QNH at an airport of elevation 3100 ft is 991 hPa, ISA + 24°C.\nCalculate the flight level in order to clear the mountain range by the specified clearance.",
    "feedback": "FL085"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft takes off from airport A (elevation 270 ft), with the QFE of 994 hPa correctly set. Without re-setting the altimeter the pilot lands at airport B (elevation 405 ft higher than A). The QNH at airport B is 1000 hPa. What will the altimeter read on landing at airport B?",
    "feedback": "513 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following types of cloud can extend over the low, medium and high cloud levels ?",
    "feedback": "CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what flight level above Ankara would you expect the tropopause to be located?",
    "feedback": "FL 370"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pressure distribution located mainly in square 2A is a",
    "feedback": "ridge of high pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over which areas can tropical revolving storms occur?\n1) Gulf of Mexico2) South Asia3) South Atlantic Ocean4) Indian Ocean east of Madagascar",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What process in an air mass leads to the creation of wide spread NS, AS and ST cloud coverage?",
    "feedback": "Lifting"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 150, with an outside temperature of -30°, above an airport where the elevation is 1660 ft and the QNH is 993 hPa.\nCalculate the true altitude (barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa):",
    "feedback": "13600 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "During foehn from the south the air temperature is generally:",
    "feedback": "higher north of the Alps than south of the Alps at the same altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning volume and temperature of a ascending parcel of air is correct?",
    "feedback": "The volume increases while the temperature decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "How long from the time of observation is a TREND in a METAR valid?",
    "feedback": "2 hours."
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of lightning is represented in the picture?",
    "feedback": "Cloud to cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over Caen Airport LFRK the transition altitude is given as 13000 feet, and the transition level as FL150. If the QNH at the airfield is 1003 hPa, what is the vertical extent of the transition layer?\n(assume 1 hPa=40 feet)",
    "feedback": "1600 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which route do you expect the cross section below?",
    "feedback": "B-D"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what airframe temperatures would you expect the worst icing effects?",
    "feedback": "Between 0°C and -15°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Several physical processes contribute to atmospheric warming. Which of the following contribute the most ?",
    "feedback": "Convection and condensation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Determine the most accurate estimate of the approximate Relative Humidity, given:\nAir temperature: +18°CDew point: +12°C",
    "feedback": "70%"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is descending to land under IFR. If the local QNH is 1009 hPa, what will happen to the altitude reading when the altimeter is reset at the transition level ?",
    "feedback": "It will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the correct explanation for this statement about atmospheric heating.\nAtmospheric heating mostly occurs (1) ...... the tropopause due to the Greenhouse Effect, which traps (2) ....... radiation.",
    "feedback": "(1) below, (2) infrared"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about mountain waves are correct or incorrect?\n1) For the development of strong down- and updrafts in mountain waves the atmosphere must be unstable\n2) If a rotor occurs in a mountain wave it is always visible",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the QNH at Locarno (200 metres above sea level) is 1025 hPa, what is the approximate QFE?(assume 1 hPa = 8 m)",
    "feedback": "1000 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is the criterion for the vertical division of the lower part of the atmosphere into troposphere and stratosphere?",
    "feedback": "Vertical temperature profile"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about icing are correct or incorrect?\n1) In a CB icing can only occur between 0°C and -15°C\n2) In relation with a warm front icing can only occur inside clouds",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "A mountain range spans from North to South. A warm front from the West is passing over the mountains, with rain (RA) and a cloud ceiling of 2000 ft.\nWhat is the expected weather at an airfield situated on the Eastern side of the mountains?",
    "feedback": "Cloud base higher than 2000 ft and colder air than on the Western side of the mountain chain"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct regarding the cooling/warming of the Earth's surface by radiation?",
    "feedback": "More heat is radiated into space from a warm surface than from a cold surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are flying at FL 120 and the outside temperature is -2°C, at what altitude will the \"freezing level\" be?",
    "feedback": "FL 110"
  },
  {
    "question": "The isohypse 11880 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "feedback": "200 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the following aerodrome warnings, a pilot on departure at (1) ...... airport has reported (2) .......\nLDRI WS WRNG 1 160520 VALID 160520/161200 WS ALL RWY FCST=LGTS WS WRNG 1 160520 MBST APCH RWY 16 REP AT 0500 A320 35KT LOSS 1 NM FNA=LGAV WS WRNG 1 160520 MBST IN CLIMB OUT REP AT 0500 A320=EDDF WS WRNG 1 160520 VALID 160520/161200 WS RWY18 FCST=",
    "feedback": "(1) LGAV, (2) a microburst"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are pilot reports of significant weather in flight subsequently used by the receiving meteorological office and their systems?",
    "feedback": "The reports can be processed into weather models to improve subsequent forecasts"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at 2000 ft when it enters an air mass which is 10°C colder. The true altitude will be",
    "feedback": "Decreased by 80 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the sky is overcast, what means are used by meteorological services for measuring wind in any height between earth's surface and 10000 m?",
    "feedback": "Radiosondes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does this picture depict?",
    "feedback": "North foehn"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of lightning is represented in the picture?",
    "feedback": "Cloud to ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct or incorrect?\n1) Ice crystal icing occurs when snowflakes and supercooled droplets mix2) Ice crystal icing is a threat for the engines when cruising at high altitudes",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a stormscope?",
    "feedback": "An instrument on board an aircraft to detect electrical discharges."
  },
  {
    "question": "An airmass is unstable when",
    "feedback": "an ascending parcel of air continues to rise to a considerable height."
  },
  {
    "question": "Under anticyclone conditions in the northern hemisphere, with curved isobars the speed of the gradient wind is",
    "feedback": "greater than the geostrophic wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following symbols represents a squall line?",
    "feedback": "Symbol a)"
  },
  {
    "question": "How could a crew visually identify that a tropical squall line is about to pass over their destination aerodrome, and what immediate hazard should they expect on the approach?",
    "feedback": "A distinct roll cloud will be followed by a sudden, rapid increase in wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "A squall line usually is most likely to be encountered",
    "feedback": "ahead of a cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather forecast for a low level route includes a warning of possible moderate to severe turbulence. For an aircraft in flight and operating along this route, which of the following, if available, would provide the most up-to-date information that could help the pilot to avoid the worst turbulence?",
    "feedback": "Pilot reports can provide the most valuable information on any weather hazards, including turbulence, that is useful to other pilots approaching the same area"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QNH at an airfield located 0 metres above sea level is 1022 hPa. The air temperature is not available. What is the QFF?",
    "feedback": "1022 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which conditions would you most likely encounter clear icing, and how would it normally appear?",
    "feedback": "Cumuliform clouds, large water droplets, temperatures between 0°C and -15°C.\nAppears smooth and tends to spread back over an aircraft wing."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following instruments or methods can be used to determine surface weather?\n1) Anemometer2) Barometer, measuring air pressure3) Human observation4) Rain gauge5) Sensors to measure height of the cloud base6) Significant weather chart7) Visibility sensors",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 5, 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying at 5000 feet in the northern hemisphere over plains (flat country) with an anticyclone on the left and a depression on the right, the wind will be",
    "feedback": "a head wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an ILS approach on RWY 33, a northwesterly wind is blowing parallel to the runway. Its speed is decreasing rapidly with increasing height while its change in direction is negligible. What has the pilot to be aware of with respect to wind shear and glide path (no autopilot engaged)?",
    "feedback": "Without the pilot's intervention, the aircraft is likely to fly above the designated glide path with increasing deviation from it."
  },
  {
    "question": "A temperature of +15°C is recorded at an altitude of 500 metres above sea level. If the vertical temperature gradient is that of a standard atmosphere, what will the temperature be at the summit of a mountain, 2500 metres above sea level?",
    "feedback": "+2°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the amount of supercooled water droplets change as the number of particles in the air increases?",
    "feedback": "The amount of supercooled water droplets increases with more particles"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather phenomena is indicated by the clouds over Scandinavia?",
    "feedback": "Low pressure system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning volume and temperature of a descending parcel of air is correct?",
    "feedback": "The volume decreases while the temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "When in the upper part of a layer warm air is advected  the",
    "feedback": "stability increases in the layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. What is the airmass at the surface at location M?",
    "feedback": "Cold air mass behind of a cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is flying an ILS approach towards runway 14, with the wind blowing parallel to the runway from the southeast. The wind strength is rapidly increasing with altitude, but the direction remains the same. What needs to be considered on the approach?",
    "feedback": "Without pilot intervention, the aircraft will likely fly below the glidepath with an associated decrease in IAS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather conditions would be expected at Athens Airport (LGAT) at around 1450 UTC? (chart 1200 UTC)",
    "feedback": "21002KT 6000 BR SCT040 29/16 Q1026 NOSIG ="
  },
  {
    "question": "If the surface temperature is 15°C , then the temperature at 10000 FT in a current of ascending unsaturated air is:",
    "feedback": "-15°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud genera is shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Nimbostratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the QNH at Locarno (200 metres above sea level) is 1015 hPa, what is the approximate QFE?\n(Assume 1hPa = 8m)",
    "feedback": "990 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Snow grains",
    "feedback": "fall from stratus or supercooled fog."
  },
  {
    "question": "The main difference between turbulence and a wind gust is:",
    "feedback": "A gust is only a sudden increase in wind speed while turbulence is associated with specific weather patterns"
  },
  {
    "question": "The images are examples of visible and infrared satellite images respectively, valid for the same time.\nUsing these satellite images, it can be concluded that the clouds stretching in a band from the Gulf of Mexico northeastward into New York are of the type:",
    "feedback": "Cumulus and Cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dry adiabatic lapse rate has a value of",
    "feedback": "1°C/100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct/incorrect?\n1) The tropopause height increases with increasing latitude\n2) The tropopause is a continuous levelled surface",
    "feedback": "1) incorrect, 2) incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is planned to fly from Tashkent (T, approx. 41°N 69°E) to Lusaka (L, approx. 15°S 28°E). The cruising FL increases from initially FL340 to FL450 halfway through the flight. What hazardous weather would you encounter en-route?",
    "feedback": "Ice crystals the last 600 NM before descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the type, intensity and seasonal variation of precipitation in the equatorial region ?",
    "feedback": "Rainshowers, hail showers and thunderstorms occur the whole year, but frequency is highest during two periods: April-May and October-November."
  },
  {
    "question": "The height of the friction layer is largest under the following conditions:",
    "feedback": "Rough terrain, high wind speed, unstable air, during a warm summer afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Surface visibility at your destination in the centre of France in August is reported as 1500 metres in haze, with an inversion at 500 feet above aerodrome level and sky clear above.\nWhen making a non-precision approach to runway 18 shortly before sunset with a minimum descent altitude of 600 feet above aerodrome level, at what range would you expect to see the runway and why?",
    "feedback": "More than 1500 metres because the aircraft will still be flying above the haze"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a favourable synoptic situation for the development of a Scirocco?",
    "feedback": "Low pressure area in the western part of the Mediterranean Sea"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the QFE at Locarno (200 metres above sea level) is 1000 hPa, what is the approximate QNH?",
    "feedback": "1025 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass affecting position \"R\" is most likely to be",
    "feedback": "Continental tropical"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true regarding moderate-to-severe airframe icing?",
    "feedback": "It is likely to occur in nimbostratus cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compared to a Microburst, a Macroburst:",
    "feedback": "Has a longer duration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions would cause the altimeter to indicate a lower altitude than that actually flown ?",
    "feedback": "Air temperature higher than standard"
  },
  {
    "question": "In mid-latitudes, the tops of Cumulus are often limited by",
    "feedback": "a temperature inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ice crystals are often found in and around the anvil of a thunderstorm. If found in high densities at very low temperatures, what hazard to these ice crystals present to an aircraft?",
    "feedback": "The crystals can accumulate inside the engine, then break away, causing a sudden loss of thrust, especially at low power settings"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is untrue regarding the importance of the tropopause?",
    "feedback": "Air temperature starts to fall severely above the tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather conditions favour the formation of radiation fog?",
    "feedback": "Light wind, little or no cloud, moist air."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which FL corresponds with the 400 hPa pressure level?",
    "feedback": "FL 240"
  },
  {
    "question": "A sample of moist but unsaturated air may become saturated by",
    "feedback": "expanding it adiabatically"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the root cause for the seasonal climate change in the Mediterranean region between a mild, moist winter and a warm, dry summer?",
    "feedback": "The seasonal north-south movement of the thermal Equator, which affects the position of the subtropical high pressure system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the situations described below will probably yield the most turbulent conditions during final approach and landing?",
    "feedback": "Time: in the afternoon\nWinds aloft: strong\n\nAirport: lacking in uniformity, rough terrain"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying with an outside air temperature of -12°C and a TAS of 250 kt at FL 150 through 8 octas NS. What type and degree of icing is most probable?",
    "feedback": "In clouds pushed up against the mountains, moderate to severe mixed ice."
  },
  {
    "question": "In the TAF for Dehli, during the summer, for the time of your landing you note: TEMPO TS. What is the maximum time this deterioration in weather can last in anyone instance ?",
    "feedback": "60 minutes."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of a frontal system corresponds to the following description, and is the air within this part stable or unstable?\n\nWind: abrupt change in direction from SW to NW, gusty\nClouds: cumulonimbus with great vertical extent, stratocumulus in precipitation areas\nPrecipitation: heavy showers or thunderstorms in relative small areas\nVisibility: significant improvement behind the precipitation area",
    "feedback": "Cold front in unstable atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "The difference between geostrophic wind and gradient wind is caused by",
    "feedback": "curvature of isobars"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: Which statements are true?",
    "feedback": "CBs have formed over the Iberian peninsula, with tops at about 25'000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following circumstances would the formation of a low level jet stream in the evening be most likely?",
    "feedback": "An inflow of cold air over land or strong radiation cooling in the evening can lead to an inversion. At or just below the top of the inversion a low level jet stream can form"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate speed of a 25-knot wind, expressed in kilometres per hour?",
    "feedback": "45 km/h"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a thunderstorm (CB) 10 miles ahead is assessed as still being in the mature phase, what should a pilot of a light aircraft do?",
    "feedback": "He should change heading to circumnavigate the storm"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind at 500ft above ground is 290/15kt and at the same position at 600ft above ground 300/22kt. How is this wind situation called?",
    "feedback": "Moderate vertical wind shear"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning the airflow during the summer monsoon is correct?",
    "feedback": "Southwesterly airflow over India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "The front to the north of Frankfurt is moving north-east at about 5 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The indicated clouds overhead Scandinavia are most likely an indicator for a(n)....",
    "feedback": "cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "A thin coating of hoar frost on the airfoil surface:",
    "feedback": "has significant negative effects on the lift of the wing"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lowest assumed temperature in the International Standard Atmosphere (ISA) is :",
    "feedback": "-56.5°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "When isobars, for an area in the mid-latitudes on a weather map, are close together, the wind is most likely to be",
    "feedback": "strong"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term SIGMET signify?",
    "feedback": "A SIGMET is a warning of dangerous meteorological conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "RVR is measured when meteorological visibility falls below:",
    "feedback": "1500 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning the Scirocco is correct?",
    "feedback": "It blows from southerly directions and can carry dust and sand which may reach Europe."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 18289 FT pressure level (FL 180) ?",
    "feedback": "500 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning volume and temperature of a descending parcel of air is correct?",
    "feedback": "The volume decreases while the temperature increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case that obstacles on the surface (trees, houses, etc.) are the only cause of turbulence, it will be greatest at",
    "feedback": "150 m/GND"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which of these routes would you not have to worry about turbulence at FL 340?",
    "feedback": "Shannon - Hamburg"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which process is mainly responsible for the warming of layers of air in the medium levels of the troposphere?",
    "feedback": "Convection"
  },
  {
    "question": "A frontal thunderstorm will most likely appear during the (1) .... and will be (2) .... than an air mass thunderstorm",
    "feedback": "(1) winter, (2) faster"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average temperature for the route Zurich - Lisboa at FL 200.",
    "feedback": "-33°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "EDDF TAF 061000Z 0612/0718 23012KT 7000 SCT026 BECMG 0615/0618 22020KT BECMG 0700/0703 16015KT 8000 FEW026 BECMG 0709/0712 24010KT 7000 SCT028 BECMG 0715/0718 22008KT FEW035\nAccording to the TAF, a pilot planning to take off from Frankfurt airport (EDDF) on the 7th of the month at 05:00 UTC could expect (1) ...... visibility, a wind speed of (2) ...... and (3) ...... clouds",
    "feedback": "(1) 8000 m, (2) 15 KT, (3) few"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following options is a main source of information regarding the location and strength of Clear Air Turbulence (CAT) areas?",
    "feedback": "Reports from pilots who are experiencing CAT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the sets of two pressure charts (surface and 700 hPa level), when compared, illustrate the existence of a cold-air drop best?",
    "feedback": "Diagram 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "If Paris reports a wind of 16020KT on the METAR, what wind velocity would you expect to encounter at a height of 2000 feet above the ground?",
    "feedback": "19040KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO, which symbol indicates severe icing ?",
    "feedback": "Symbol a)"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aircraft making an approach to an airfield located in square 3B, away from the vicinity of the fronts, the most likely weather conditions in winter are",
    "feedback": "poor visibility in mist and drizzle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of a frontal system corresponds to the following description?\n\nWind: NW, gusty\nClouds: cumulus, cumulonimbus\nPrecipitation: showers, occasional thunderstorms\nVisibility: very good apart from precipitation areas",
    "feedback": "Weather behind the cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Normally atmospheric pressure stops falling rapidly behind a warm front, the air temperature rises"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are flying from Zurich to Oslo at FL 310, where will your cruising altitude be?",
    "feedback": "Constantly in the stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the diagram, which figure represents a cold occlusion?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a sunny spring day and a cloudless night, you depart from an inland airport with calm winds. Soon after takeoff, the wind veers sharply and increases in speed, and a low-level wind shear warning in the cockpit is observed. What meterorological phenomena can be the cause?",
    "feedback": "Nocturnal Jet"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are in the process of planning a flight from Brussels (50°55'N 004°30'E) to Deauville (49°00'N 000°00'E) on 12th March 2017, departing at 20:00 UTC and with a flight time of approximately 3 hours. The route will follow the line from B to D on the chart, and the minimum altitude that can be flown is 3200 feet.\nWhat would be the lowest cloud base en route?",
    "feedback": "300 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following situations is an aircraft most susceptible to icing ?",
    "feedback": "Level flight below a rain producing cloud when OAT is below zero degrees C."
  },
  {
    "question": "TAF LSZH 1322 22018G35KT 9999 SCT012 BKN030 BECMG 1315 25025G45KT BECMG 1820 4000 RA BKN025 BECMG 2022 25015KT T1815Z T1618Z = \n\nWhich statement is true at 15 UTC?",
    "feedback": "met. vis. 10 km or more, ceiling 3000 ft, wind from 250 degrees, temperature 18°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the most important conditions for the formation of significant lee waves within a mountain range:",
    "feedback": "A strong large-scale wind increases up to high levels and blows approximately perpendicular towards the mountain range under a stable thermal stratification"
  },
  {
    "question": "The formation of a Foehn is represented by:(arrows indicate wind direction)",
    "feedback": "Figure 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following regions does polar maritime air originate ?",
    "feedback": "East of Greenland"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which of the following routes would you not have to worry about moderate and/or severe turbulence on the cruising level?",
    "feedback": "Rome to Vienna at FL 220"
  },
  {
    "question": "A METAR reads : SA1430 35002KT 7000 SKC 21/03 Q1024 =\nWhich of the following information is contained in this METAR ?",
    "feedback": "temperature/dewpoint"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight Zurich - Warsaw, ETD 1130 UTC.\n\nAt what flight level would you first expect to encounter clear air turbulence on the climb out from Zurich?",
    "feedback": "FL 200"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a high level commercial air transport flight across the North Atlantic, the weather forecast indicated cloud and occasional moderate turbulence below the planned cruising level. However, some time into the flight the aircraft received a SIGMET broadcast indicating that a small area of moderate to severe clear air turbulence exists in a location close to the planned route. This information about the previously unexpected turbulence provides the flight crew with valuable advance warning, allowing them to make an early change to their track. \nWhat is the most likely basis of this SIGMET?",
    "feedback": "The turbulence reported in the SIGMET, issued by the Meteorological Watch Office, is most likely to have been based on pilot reports"
  },
  {
    "question": "The typical heights of the Tropopause and Stratopause can be, respectively:",
    "feedback": "11 km, 50 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "To which type of message does the following text belong?\n\t\n… MBST APCH RWY26 REP AT 1510 B747 30KT ASPEEDL 2NM FNA=",
    "feedback": "Wind shear warning"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 250, OAT = ISA +5°C. The QNH, given by a meteorological station with an elevation of 3000 ft is 1000 hPa. Use 1hPa = 30 ft.  Calculate the True Altitude (rounded to 100 ft)",
    "feedback": "25100 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are the properties and conditions of a sandstorm? Select two options:\n1) Presence of a low-level jet stream2) Sand grains smaller than 0.8 mm3) Wind speeds exceeding 20 kt4) Visibility less than 1000 m",
    "feedback": "3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average wind for the route Athens-Geneva, FL 160:",
    "feedback": "23040KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pressure distribution located mainly at point B is a",
    "feedback": "col"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of a frontal system corresponds to the following description, and is the air within this part stable or unstable?\n\nWind: abrupt change in direction from SW to NW\nAtmospheric pressure: decreasing first, followed by a rapid increase\nClouds: nimbostratus, stratocumulus in precipitation areas\nPrecipitation: heavy, extensive\nVisibility: significant improvement behind the precipitation area",
    "feedback": "Cold front in stable atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term METAR signify?",
    "feedback": "A METAR signifies the actual weather report at an aerodrome and is generally issued in half-hourly intervals."
  },
  {
    "question": "What should be expected during an approach to a runway located in a valley, if a surface-based temperature inversion is reported?",
    "feedback": "Visibility reduction"
  },
  {
    "question": "When compared to icing in stratiform clouds, icing in cumuliform clouds is generally:",
    "feedback": "more severe due to the higher supercooled water content of cumuliform cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "You have landed at an airport, local QNH 993 hPa. After landing, you notice, that your altimeter subscale is still set to 1013,2 hPa. Your altimeter indicates 1200 ft. What is the airport elevation?(assume 1hPa = 27 ft)",
    "feedback": "660 ft AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is true about the St. Elmo's fire weather phenomenon?",
    "feedback": "The St. Elmo's fire is a permanent electrical discharge in the air"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can a pilot do to avoid Ice Crystal Icing (ICI)?",
    "feedback": "Avoid CBs on the upwind side and stay above the tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "What information is given on a Significant Weather Chart?",
    "feedback": "The significant weather forecast for the time given on the chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which airport, is the following weather development taking place? (Chart 0600 UTC)\nTAF 060716 25006KT 8000 BKN240 BECMG 0710 OVC200 BECMG 1013 23010KT 8000 OVC100 BECMG 1316 23014KT 6000 RA SCT030 OVC050 =",
    "feedback": "EDDL"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the lowest cloud base forecast for arrival at Geneva (ETA 1200 UTC)?\nTAF LSGG 020900Z 021019 18007KT 9999 SCT020 BKN100 BECMG 1114 8000 RA SCT010 OVC020 PROB30 TEMPO 1018 VRB10G25KT TSRA SCT005 BKN015CB=",
    "feedback": "500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of these temperature bands is ice most likely to form on the aircraft's surface?",
    "feedback": "0°C to -10°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the pressure in surface weather charts called?",
    "feedback": "QFF"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can meteorologists accurately forecast the movement of a tropical revolving storm (TRS)?",
    "feedback": "They cannot, it is very difficult to predict the movement of a TRS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mountain waves create rotors in the air, the height of which when compared to the mountain top means that the centre of the first rotor is usually:",
    "feedback": "at the same height or just below the top of the mountain on the leeward side"
  },
  {
    "question": "The airfield from which you depart at sunset is covered in haze. Which runway would be the worst to be used?",
    "feedback": "27"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a high pressure system, stratiform cloud development is limited aloft by (1) .... , resulting from adiabatic (2) ....",
    "feedback": "(1) subsidence, (2) warming"
  },
  {
    "question": "By what visual indicators can a flight crew determine that a tropical squall line is approaching the destination aerodrome, and which associated hazard should they anticipate on final approach?",
    "feedback": "A distinct roll cloud , followed by a sudden, rapid increase in wind speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Bergeron Theory:",
    "feedback": "presumes that at high levels in a cloud, some water droplets turn to ice and grow by sublimation."
  },
  {
    "question": "In what situation is Ice Crystal Icing formed?",
    "feedback": "By lifting high concentrations of moisture, mostly in the upper part of a Cumulonimbus cloud, freezing into very small ice crystals"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an approach to land an aircraft experiences a headwind at 4000 ft followed by an increasing crosswind component from the right in the friction layer.\n\nThe wind shift:",
    "feedback": "Is typical in the southern hemisphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "A given volume of 1 m3 of air is saturated with water vapour. With decreasing air temperature the",
    "feedback": "vapour pressure will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "At FL050, in which following atmospheric conditions would you expect the value on the aircraft altimeter to be lower than the value of the true altitude?",
    "feedback": "High pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cold-air drop in the Northern Hemisphere is formed by the....",
    "feedback": "advection of cold air in the upper levels to the south of the normal polar front"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is the early afternoon on a sunny day in summer, and you are flying over the west coast of the Netherlands. If there is a non-frontal environment with a slack pressure gradient, the wind direction at the surface is likely to be...",
    "feedback": "westerly"
  },
  {
    "question": "The W/V (°/kt) at 50°N 015°W is:",
    "feedback": "290/45"
  },
  {
    "question": "Diagram (1) ..... shows a cold-core anticyclone and diagram (2) .... depicts a warm-core anticyclone.",
    "feedback": "(1) 1, (2) 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "Fog can be supercooled and can also contain ice crystals."
  },
  {
    "question": "How many tropical cyclones form west of Darwin in the southwest Pacific on average per year?",
    "feedback": "5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Strongly developed cumulus clouds are an indication of",
    "feedback": "instability in the atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "From the TAF you can assume that visibility at 2055Z in Birmingham (EGBB) will be:  EGBB 261000Z 2618/2712 28015G25KT 9999 SCT025 TEMPO 2618/2622 29018G35KT 5000 SHRASN BKN010CB PROB30 TEMPO 2618/2621 1500 TSGR BKN008CB BECMG 2622/2624 26010 KT=",
    "feedback": "not less than 1,5 km but could be in excess of 10 km."
  },
  {
    "question": "The geostrophic wind speed is directly proportional to the",
    "feedback": "horizontal pressure gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "Foehn effects in mountainous areas occur:",
    "feedback": "on the lee side of the mountain range when precipitation is falling on the upwind side of the mountain range"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following options is the best recommendation to avoid dangerous icing for a pilot of an aircraft, in temperate latitudes, if the planned route of the flight would take the aircraft along a warm front on the cold air side?\nAdditional information:The ceiling of the Nimbostratus clouds is at 1400 ft AGL, the freezing level on the cold air side is at 1000 ft AGL, on the warm air side 2000 ft AGL. The front is weak and the width of the precipitation band is 20 NM. The aircraft is equipped with serviceable anti-icing and de-icing systems. The pilot does not have a valid instrument rating, therefore the flight has to be made in VMC.",
    "feedback": "Traverse (follow) the warm front perpendicular to its direction of movement and fly below the freezing level"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the North Atlantic route from the Azores to Bermuda, the mean height of the tropical tropopause during summer is approximately:",
    "feedback": "47000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A blocking anticyclone in the northern hemisphere is",
    "feedback": "a warm anticyclone/quasi stationary/situated between 50°N and 70°N"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following 1850 UTC METAR reports, is the probability of fog formation, in the coming night, the highest?",
    "feedback": "VRB01KT 8000 SCT250 11/10 Q1028 BECMG 3000 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "In which direction does the pressure gradient force act? (The chart is centred around 67°N 010°E)",
    "feedback": "Arrow 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Based on the VOLMET, where is the wind coming from relative to the direction of runway 34?\n\"WIND 350 DEGREES 12 KNOTS, VISIBILITY & KILOMETRES, LIGHT RAIN, CLOUD, BROKEN 800 HUNDRED FEET, OVERCAST 1/ THOUSAND FEET, TEMPERATURE 6, DEW POINT 4, ONH 999 HECTOPASCALS\"",
    "feedback": "30° from the right"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the weather conditions illustrated?",
    "feedback": "FG"
  },
  {
    "question": "An inversion is a layer of air in which the temperature",
    "feedback": "increases with height"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wind speed in case of gradient wind is",
    "feedback": "depending on curvature of the isobars"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are flying from Zurich to Stockholm at FL 240, what conditions can you expect at cruising altitude?",
    "feedback": "Largely free of cloud; moderate icing half way along the route"
  },
  {
    "question": "What change in pressure, will occur at point A, during the next hour?",
    "feedback": "A rise in pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Divergence over a uniform surface is caused by",
    "feedback": "frictional force together with anti-cyclonic curvature of the isobars"
  },
  {
    "question": "During summer in the centre of a warm anticyclone over land, what are cloudiness and visibility like?",
    "feedback": "The sky is clear or bears few clouds; visibility is moderate to poor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are advantages of choosing a cruising level in the lower stratosphere?\n1) Economic fuel consumption2) Better TAS3) Emissions have less environmental impact4) Mountain wave systems remain well below5) Very few clouds6) Less wear on the engines7) Less turbulence",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 5, 7"
  },
  {
    "question": "The meteorological diagram contains adiabats and lines of constant mixing ratio (dew point lines).\n\nWhich sequence of points describes the change of temperature of an air parcel that rises from the ground, reaches the cloud base at point 4 and continues to rise inside the cloud?",
    "feedback": "3, 4, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Humidity is measured by means of a psychrometer. It compares dry bulb temperature with:",
    "feedback": "The lowest temperature to which air is cooled by the evaporation of water."
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature is -15°C on an airport 3000' above mean sea level.\nWhich of the following is true?",
    "feedback": "QFF > QNH"
  },
  {
    "question": "Similar climatic conditions can be found in many regions across the Earth. An example of a geographical area with an equatorial climate is (1) ....... and an example of an area with a temperate climate is (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) the Brazilian rainforest, (2) the South Island of New Zealand"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of low pressure area is associated with a surface front?",
    "feedback": "Polar front low."
  },
  {
    "question": "At the same latitude the geostrophic wind is greater than the gradient wind around a low pressure system with equal pressure gradient because the",
    "feedback": "centrifugal force opposes the pressure gradient"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an airfield located in the British Isles, the passage of a warm front will usually be indicated by",
    "feedback": "a rise in temperature, a rise in dew point temperature, wind veers and decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "To what extent is Zagreb (LDZA) covered by clouds?",
    "feedback": "3 to 7 oktas"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what hPa range is an upper weather chart for FL 340 situated?",
    "feedback": "300 - 200 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Clear ice forms as a result of",
    "feedback": "supercooled water droplets spreading during the freezing process"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: State the height of the freezing level over Tunis, considering the common vertical temperature gradient:",
    "feedback": "FL 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hoar frost forms on an aircraft as a result of",
    "feedback": "water vapour turning directly into ice crystals on the aircraft surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Advection of very cold air over a warm sea current can cause:",
    "feedback": "steam fog."
  },
  {
    "question": "You are planning an IFR flight eastbound and find that the highest obstacle along the route has an elevation of 5400 ft. The ISA deviation is -20°C and the QNH is 990 hPa. What is the lowest usable flight level on this flight in a non-mountainous area?",
    "feedback": "FL090"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a sunny day, followed by a long clear night, you take-off from an airfield at mid-latitudes in the northern hemisphere an hour before sunrise. The field is not situated close to the coast. Though the pressure gradient is rather large, the easterly surface wind is weak and makes ...",
    "feedback": "a sudden strong increase in wind speed and strong veering of the wind a short time after take-off."
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at FL 160. Outside air temperature is -27°C, and the pressure at sea level is 1003 hPa. What is the true altitude?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "15060 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the meteorological situation immediately to the north of location W (49°N 017°W)?",
    "feedback": "An occluded front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements:\n1) The maximum water vapour pressure is higher over ice than over water with the same temperature\n2) For unsaturated air the dew-point temperature is lower than the temperature",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the ICAO qualifying term for the described intensity of turbulence:\n„Conditions in which abrupt changes in aircraft attitude and/or altitude occur; aircraft may be out of control for short periods\"?",
    "feedback": "Severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements:\n1) Fog only occurs in air with cold air mass properties\n2) Both mist and haze are formed by water droplets and/or ice crystals in the atmosphere",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what areas has a pilot to be cautious and mindful of severe clear air turbulence when planning a route?",
    "feedback": "In the vicinity of a jet stream"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average width of the precipitation zone of a warm front?",
    "feedback": "150 - 300 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "Friction between the air and the ground results in the northern hemisphere in:",
    "feedback": "backing of the wind and decrease of wind speed at the surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a ceilometer used for?",
    "feedback": "It is used for measuring the cloud ceiling height or cloud base"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pilot of a small single-engined piston aircraft is preparing for a departure in winter conditions, and is performing the outside check. The pilot should be aware that the greatest risk of ice forming on an airframe is, if there is .....",
    "feedback": "water in a liquid state, with an ambient air temperature and airframe temperature below 0°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft passes the transition altitude on a SID out of Dimapur, India. Determine the approximate reading expected on the altimeter if the pilot changes the subscale setting at the transition altitude. Given:\nTransition altitude: 11000 ftTransition level: FL105QNH: 1041 hPa(assume 27 ft = 1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "10240 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The geostrophic wind is 36060KT over point N. What is the corresponding surface wind at point N?",
    "feedback": "35042KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "At 40°N 70°W, the forecast wind is",
    "feedback": "270°/95 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tropical revolving storms are NOT formed in:",
    "feedback": "South Atlantic Ocean."
  },
  {
    "question": "What amount and type of cloud is forecast to affect the route overhead Charleston?",
    "feedback": "Well separated cumulonimbus contained in layers of other cloud."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which best describes the significant cloud, if any, forecast for the area southwest of BODO (67°N 014°E)",
    "feedback": "5 to 7 oktas CU and CB, base below FL100, tops FL180"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the process of cyclogenesis, arrange the following stages of a polar front depression in the correct order of development:\n1) Mature stage2) Initial stage (Frontogenesis)3) Dying stage4) Occluded stage",
    "feedback": "2, 1, 4, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass affecting position \"P\" is most likely to be",
    "feedback": "Continental polar"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 180 in the northern hemisphere with a crosswind from the left. Which of the following is correct concerning its true altitude ?",
    "feedback": "It decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which average height can the 200 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "feedback": "12,0 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "DALR: Dry Adiabatic Lapse RateELR: Environmental Lapse RateSALR: Saturated Adiabatic Lapse Rate\nAn isothermal layer may exist when in that layer ......",
    "feedback": "ELR is lower than SALR"
  },
  {
    "question": "In wintertime stratus is often formed when warm maritime air moves over cold land. How can such clouds be classified?",
    "feedback": "Turbulence clouds."
  },
  {
    "question": "The Runway Visual Range (RVR) is measured along the runway and reported in increments depending on the horizontal visiblity. It is reported in steps of (1) ..... if the RVR is less than 400 m, in steps of (2) ..... if the RVR is between 400 m and 800 m, and in steps of (3) .... if the RVR is more than 800 m.",
    "feedback": "(1) 25 m, (2) 50 m, (3) 100 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the latitudes and tracks in the North Atlantic Ocean where tropical revolving storms move as they develop and mature?",
    "feedback": "10°N to 15°N moving from east to west, turning into northerly directions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fog (FG) is defined as being a:",
    "feedback": "visibility < 1000 m due to liquid particles or ice crystals suspended in the atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "Examining the pictures, on which one of the tracks (dashed lines) is this cross-section to be expected?",
    "feedback": "Track B-D"
  },
  {
    "question": "The schematic view of the earth shows some isobars (short black lines) and the corresponding areas of lower and higher pressure at the surface.\n\nWhat are the approximate wind directions aloft between 2000 and 3000 ft above ground at the two red points shown on the diagram?",
    "feedback": "1: SW, 2: NE"
  },
  {
    "question": "Up to what altitude and in what increments is the vertical visibility reported in a METAR?",
    "feedback": "30's m (100's ft) up to 2000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "To which aerodrome is the following TAF most applicable ?\nTAF 231019 24014KT 6000 SCT030 BKN100 TEMPO 1113 25020G38KT 2500 +TSRA SCT008 BKN025CB BECMG 1315 28012KT 9999 SCT025 TEMPO 5000 SHRA BKN020 BECMG 1719 27008KT 9999 SCT030",
    "feedback": "LOWW"
  },
  {
    "question": "A blocking high is a:",
    "feedback": "warm anticyclone, almost stationary"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the correct general description of turbulence.",
    "feedback": "Irregular and instantaneous motions of air, which can be made up of a number of small eddies that travel in the general air current"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dew point is defined as",
    "feedback": "the temperature to which moist air must be cooled to become saturated at a given pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is favourable for the lifting of air and the formation of clouds and precipitation?",
    "feedback": "Convergence near the ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following best describes Zone B?",
    "feedback": "Col"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot of a small single-engined piston aircraft is en route in icing conditions. The pilot has been periodically checking the wings for ice accretion. Initially he/she notices some slight translucent ice and the formation of white horns followed shortly thereafter by the ice changing to an opaque (white) colour with a uniform thickness and some remaining horn formation. These observations are typical characteristics of ....",
    "feedback": "mixed ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "What visibility is most likely to be experienced at 1400 UTC ?\nEDDF 272200Z 280624 VRB05KT 4000 BR SCT005 OVC013 BECMG 1314 9000 SHRA OVC015 PROB40 TEMPO 1416 VRB15G25KT 1600 TSRA OVC010CB BECMG 1618 26010KT BKN030 BECMG 2122 CAVOK=",
    "feedback": "9000 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather in the horse latitudes is generally ....",
    "feedback": "dry and stable with light winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "From indications shown on the chart, when front \"S\" passes position \"V\" the surface wind should",
    "feedback": "veer and remain more or less at the same speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the red, bold line overhead Italy during summer. If such a line appears on a surface chart at the same location, and represents a trough, what kind of weather is to be expected during the afternoon?",
    "feedback": "Convergence, convection, and the formation of clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does freezing rain develop?",
    "feedback": "Rain falls through a layer where temperatures are below 0°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "An OAT of -30°C at the 300 hPa pressure level:",
    "feedback": "is high"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 300, OAT = ISA +15°C. The QNH, given by a meteorological station with an elevation of 3000 ft is 1020 hPa. Use 1hPa = 30 ft.  Calculate the True Altitude (rounded to 100 ft)",
    "feedback": "31900 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the expression \"Broken (BKN)\" mean?",
    "feedback": "5-7 Eights of the sky is cloud covered"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather most likely to be experienced at position \"S\" is",
    "feedback": "frequent heavy showers of rain or snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud genera are shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Cumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What name is given to the low level wind system between the subtropical high pressure belt and the equatorial trough of low pressure (ITCZ) ?",
    "feedback": "Trade winds."
  },
  {
    "question": "The isohypse 5700 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "feedback": "500 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather reports  is a warning of conditions that could be potentially hazardous to aircraft in flight ?",
    "feedback": "SIGMET."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which FL corresponds with the 150 hPa pressure level?",
    "feedback": "FL 450"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which form of precipitation from clouds containing only water is most likely to fall in mid-latitudes?",
    "feedback": "Drizzle."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are the correct coordinates for a high pressure system?",
    "feedback": "56°N 20°W"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is warned of severe icing at certain flight levels by information supplied in",
    "feedback": "SWC and SIGMET"
  },
  {
    "question": "During summer, the trade winds over the Atlantic Ocean will be found in the latitude band indicated by letter (1) ..... and the typical conditions are (2) ....",
    "feedback": "(1) U, (2) fair weather cumulus or stratocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the surface wind usually westerly in a Northern Hemisphere polar front depression?",
    "feedback": "In front of the cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature at the surface is given as + 15°C and at 4000 ft above the surface it is + 9°C, the state of this layer is said to be",
    "feedback": "stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under which conditions would you expect the heaviest clear ice accretion to occur in a CB?",
    "feedback": "Between -2°C and -15°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what type of cloud is a Cumulonimbus classified?",
    "feedback": "Low level"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average temperature for the route Zurich-Lisboa at FL 200:",
    "feedback": "-33°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Solar radiation is the primary source of all weather processes. When it interacts with the atmosphere and the earth:",
    "feedback": "One part is absorbed in the ozone layer, another part is reflected by clouds and the surface of the earth, the major part is absorbed by the surface of the earth"
  },
  {
    "question": "The region of the globe where the greatest number of tropical revolving storms occur is",
    "feedback": "the north-west Pacific, affecting Japan, Formosa, Korea and the Chinese coastline."
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nAir temperature + 30°C, dew point + 21°C\nCalculate the approximate Relative Humidity (RH):",
    "feedback": "55 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "What pressure does an observer at point B encounter in the next hour?",
    "feedback": "No substantial pressure change"
  },
  {
    "question": "In July in the northern hemisphere, the relationship between surface type, surface temperature and surface pressure is best described as:",
    "feedback": "Land - high temperature - low pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following METAR reports is the probability of fog formation in the coming night the highest?",
    "feedback": "201850Z 15003KT 6000 SCT120 05/04 Q1032 BECMG 1600 BR="
  },
  {
    "question": "Between which latitudes are you most likely to find the subtropical high-pressure belt ?",
    "feedback": "25° - 35°."
  },
  {
    "question": "The difference between temperature and dewpoint is greater in",
    "feedback": "dry air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following instruments is used for measuring atmospheric pressure?",
    "feedback": "Aneroid barometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying over the sea at FL 120, with a true altitude of 12000 feet; local QNH is 1013 hPa. What assumption, if any, can be made about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying ?",
    "feedback": "Its average temperature is the same as ISA"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate speed of a 40-knot wind, expressed in m/sec?",
    "feedback": "20 m/sec"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud type (genus) is described by the following definition? \n\"Greyish or bluish cloud sheet or layer of striated, fibrous or uniform appearance, totally or partly covering the sky, and having parts thin enough to reveal the sun at least vaguely, as through ground glass. This genus does not show halo phenomena.\"",
    "feedback": "Altostratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "In mature CB's the probability of severe icing, according to meteorological rules, is greatest in the following temperature range:",
    "feedback": "0°C to -23°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud species is described by the following definition?\n\"Clouds which present, in at least some portion of their upper part, cumuliform protuberances in the form of turrets which generally give the clouds a crenellated appearance. The turrets, some of which are taller than they are wide, are connected by a common base and seem to be arranged in lines. The typical character is especially evident when the clouds are seen from the side.\"",
    "feedback": "Castellanus"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air mass containing St and Sc is cooling as it is lifted over high ground. What happens to the concentration of water droplets or ice particles? They will ....",
    "feedback": "increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "When surface winds are moderate or strong, conditions that can be expected in mountainous areas are:",
    "feedback": "Up- and downdrafts, turbulence, and wind shear with changes of wind speed and wind direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is a clear night and there is a moderate, warm wind blowing across a steep valley. What is a likely result from these conditions?",
    "feedback": "An inversion forms as still air in the valley cools"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the tropopause are correct or incorrect? 1) In the real atmosphere the tropopause is a continuous levelled surface 2) Above the tropopause the temperature decrease per 100 m is 0.65°C",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather conditions are prevalent during the summer, over the North Sea, approximately 300 km behind a quickly moving cold front?",
    "feedback": "Cloud cover mostly scattered, isolated showers."
  },
  {
    "question": "Judging from the provided image, what kind of weather conditions would you anticipate at an airport situated within the marked area?",
    "feedback": "Strong to very strong precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assume that an aircraft is flying in the northern hemisphere at the 500 hPa pressure surface on a heading of 270 degrees.  Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "If in this pressure surface the wind comes from the direction 360 degrees, then true altitude is increasing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Read the following SIGMET:\nEGJJ SIGMET 03 VALID 2291130/291530 EGJJ-\nLOC SEV TURB AND WS FCST BLW 3000FT OVER THE CHANNEL ISLANDS AREA INTSF=\n\nWhich statement about this SIGMET is best?",
    "feedback": "Over the Channel Islands area severe turbulence and wind shear are forecasted which will increase during the forecast period"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over Palma de Mallorca at what flight level would you expect to find the tropopause according to the map?",
    "feedback": "FL 440"
  },
  {
    "question": "An isothermal layer is a layer of air in which the temperature",
    "feedback": "remains constant with height"
  },
  {
    "question": "What characterizes a stationary front ?",
    "feedback": "The surface wind usually has its direction parallel to the front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements: 1) The summer monsoon in India is a SW monsoon 2) Hurricanes occur usually in winter",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "By volume, what percentage of the air in the lower troposphere consists of water vapour?",
    "feedback": "0-5 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "Supercooled droplets can occur in",
    "feedback": "clouds, fog and precipitation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given a 0°C isotherm layer at FL060 and NS at FL070: What is the lowest FL with severe icing hazard?",
    "feedback": "FL070"
  },
  {
    "question": "Near a quasi-stationary front, the precipitation area is ......",
    "feedback": "a wide area on the cold air side and sometimes patchy along the line of the front itself"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 200 hPa pressure altitude level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "feedback": "FL 390."
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the Earth warmed up?",
    "feedback": "From above with insolation"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying at FL 340 in the northern hemisphere. The wind is geostrophic and there is a cross wind from the right all the time. Your true altitude will",
    "feedback": "increase"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 850 hPa pressure level can vary in height. In temperate regions which of the following average heights is applicable ?",
    "feedback": "FL 50"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cold front has the highest speed of displacement?",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main purpose of a Volcanic Ash Advisory Centre (VAAC)?",
    "feedback": "A VAAC is responsible for coordinating and disseminating information on volcanic ash clouds in the atmosphere that may endanger aviation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are medium level clouds? State the most complete answer:",
    "feedback": "AS, AC"
  },
  {
    "question": "In CAVOK conditions, an aircraft is descending on a glide slope and suddenly, within a few seconds, a 6 kt tailwind changes to a 22 kt headwind. What weather phenomenon did the pilots just encounter?",
    "feedback": "Vertical wind shear"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the International Standard Atmosphere the decrease in temperature with height below 11 km is",
    "feedback": "0.65°C per 100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the lowest visibility forecast at ETA Zurich 1430 UTC?\n\nLSZH 260900Z 261019 20018G30KT 9999 -RA SCT050 BKN080 TEMPO 23012KT 6000 -DZ BKN015 BKN030 BECMG 1518 23020G35KT 4000 RA OVC010=",
    "feedback": "6 km."
  },
  {
    "question": "You have landed on an airport (elevation 1240 ft, QNH 1008 hPa). Your altimeter subscale is erroneously set to 1013 hPa. Therefore, the indication will be:(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "1390 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "All pilots encountering Clear Air Turbulence are requested to report it. You experience CAT which causes passengers and crew to feel definite strain against their seat belt or shoulders straps. Unsecured objects are dislodged. Food service and walking are difficult. This intensity of CAT should be reported as",
    "feedback": "moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the theoretical development of the geostrophic wind in the Northern Hemisphere?",
    "feedback": "As the air starts to move and is accelerated by the pressure gradient force, it is increasingly deflected to the right by the Coriolis force until both forces are balanced and opposite to each other"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is a ridge formed?",
    "feedback": "An extension of a high pressure system between two cyclonic systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "If embedded CBs are reported in the vicinity of an airfield, the pilot can ....",
    "feedback": "use a stormscope to locate and avoid the cells"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass type advected from a direction indicated by arrow number 4 is designated",
    "feedback": "maritime tropical"
  },
  {
    "question": "Define a \"High\":",
    "feedback": "an area with higher pressure than that of the horizontal environments"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fair weather cumulus often is an indication of",
    "feedback": "turbulence at and below the cloud level"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the final temperature of unsaturated surface air at 12° C, which rises to 6000 ft?",
    "feedback": "-06°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the direction and speed of upper winds described in forecasts ?",
    "feedback": "The direction is relative to true north and the speed is in knots."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the meteorological prerequisites, at low level, for thunderstorms formed by lifting processes, over land?",
    "feedback": "High temperatures, high humidity."
  },
  {
    "question": "In a mountainous area, the most hazardous flying conditions associated with standing waves are likely to be experienced",
    "feedback": "in the vicinity of the \"roll\" cloud or rotor zone beneath the first wave on the leeward side"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is correct regarding an anabatic wind? In can be described as a wind that blows.....",
    "feedback": "upslope due to warming of air in a valley"
  },
  {
    "question": "Clear ice forms on an aircraft by the freezing of :",
    "feedback": "large supercooled water drops"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the case of blowing snow, visibility may be reduced to a minimum value of ....",
    "feedback": "1 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Foehn wind occurs on the",
    "feedback": "leeward side of a mountain range and is caused by significant moisture loss by precipitation from cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you have a column of air limited by two isobaric surfaces at a pressure difference of 100 hPa, the distance between the pressure surfaces will change if mean temperature and mean pressure of the column of air change. In which of the following alternatives will the change of temperature and pressure interact to shorten the distance as much as possible?",
    "feedback": "Temperature decreases and pressure increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight Rome to Zurich:\n\nWhat is the direction and speed of the jet stream affecting the route between Rome and Zurich at FL 310?",
    "feedback": "220°/100 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average wind for the route Shannon - Lisboa at FL 290.",
    "feedback": "360/80"
  },
  {
    "question": "You depart Munich in a Northerly direction. If you continue flying North while experiencing an Easterly drift and maintaining level flight, the altimeter of your aircraft will progressively:",
    "feedback": "over-read"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 80. The local QNH is 1000 hPa. After the second altimeter has been adjusted to the local QNH, the reading will be approximately:(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "7610 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following areas is the highest frequency of thunderstorms encountered ?",
    "feedback": "Tropical"
  },
  {
    "question": "What positions are connected by isobars on the surface weather chart?",
    "feedback": "Positions with the same air pressure at a given level"
  },
  {
    "question": "The synoptic chart depicts a region in the Southern Hemisphere. A warm front is to be found ....",
    "feedback": "between positions K and L"
  },
  {
    "question": "The freezing nuclei in a mass of air with supercooled water droplets .... the formation of ice crystals.",
    "feedback": "will enable"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the Mediterranean climate best described?",
    "feedback": "Anticyclonic and hot in summer, frontal depressions in winter."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aerodrome warning message gives information, among other things, about",
    "feedback": "TS; SN including the expected or observed snow accumulation; hoar frost"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air mass is:",
    "feedback": "an extensive body of air within which the temperature and humidity in horizontal planes are practically uniform."
  },
  {
    "question": "Mark the statement most reasonable regarding a valley inversion.",
    "feedback": "Over night, cool dense air as a result of radiation cooling will descend along the mountain slopes into the basin and lead to the development of a valley inversion."
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aircraft making an approach to an airfield which is not situated near high ground, in the vicinity of the active front in square 3B, a potential hazard exists in the form of...",
    "feedback": "low level wind shear"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the forecasted wind at position 40°N 70°W for a flight from Valencia to Charleston at FL 340?",
    "feedback": "270°/95 KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which temperature range does clear ice most commonly occur in NS clouds?",
    "feedback": "0°C to -10°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over Central Europe what type of cloud cover is typical of the warm sector of a depression during winter?",
    "feedback": "ST with drizzle."
  },
  {
    "question": "On a Low Level Significant Weather Chart, we see the following for the area where a VFR flight will take place:\n\nIf the flight is planned at FL85, we can estimate that:",
    "feedback": "we will probably have to divert around some cumulus tops."
  },
  {
    "question": "On the equatorial side of the subtropical high pressure belt, the outflow of air produces ....",
    "feedback": "north-easterly trade winds in the Northern Hemisphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "The track of an aircraft passes over a mountain range, which has a maximum elevation of 4920 ft. Given that the correct QNH is set and the ambient temperature is ISA -10°C, what is the minimum altitude required to achieve a terrain clearance of 1000 ft?",
    "feedback": "6160 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is correct regarding a cold high pressure area?",
    "feedback": "It will decrease in intensity with increasing altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is the wind in the METAR different from the wind broadcasted by the ATIS?",
    "feedback": "In the METAR, the surface wind is the average of the last 10 minutes, in the ATIS, it is the average of the last 2 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the following ATIS, and referring to the document, what would be the corresponding pilot report of braking action for runway 04?\nRUNWAY CONDITION REPORT RUNWAY ZERO FOUR AT ONE FOUR ONE FIVE:\nRUNWAY CONDITION CODES FIVE FIVE FIVEFIRST PART ONE HUNDRED PERCENT FROST.SECOND PART ONE HUNDRED PERCENT FROST.THIRD PART ONE HUNDRED PERCENT FROST.RUNWAY WIDTH FOUR ZERO METRES.",
    "feedback": "Good"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which instrument is used for measuring atmospheric humidity?",
    "feedback": "Psychrometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the following information and assuming no instrument errors, what is the approximate true height of the aircraft above airport elevation?\nOAT: ISA -15°CPressure Altitude: 3300 ftIndicated height: 3300 ft, with the airport QFE set in the altimeter subscale",
    "feedback": "3102 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Supercooled droplets can be encountered",
    "feedback": "at any time of the year"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of lightning is represented in the picture?",
    "feedback": "Intra cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "How may the correct wind speed be found, for a level, which is between two upper air chart levels? (e.g. wind at FL 250, when the 500 hPa and the 300 hPa chart are available).",
    "feedback": "By interpolation of the wind information available from the two charts, while also considering the maximum wind information found on the Significant Weather Chart."
  },
  {
    "question": "Where on the aircraft does ice crystal icing form?",
    "feedback": "Inside the jet engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions are most favourable to the formation of mountain waves ?",
    "feedback": "Stable air at mountain top altitude and a wind at least 20 knots blowing across the mountain ridge."
  },
  {
    "question": "The main components of an altostratus are",
    "feedback": "ice crystals and water droplets."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: State the average wind for the route Frankfurt-Rome, FL 170:",
    "feedback": "23040KT"
  },
  {
    "question": "A macroburst with its damaging winds at the surface:",
    "feedback": "Has a diameter of more than 4 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "During descent, Transition Level given by ATC is FL55. True altitude is 6000 ft, temperature is on average ISA + 10°C. \nCalculate the local QNH.(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "1021 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud genera is shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Stratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the abbreviation \"nosig\" mean?",
    "feedback": "No significant changes"
  },
  {
    "question": "With what type of clouds are showers most likely associated?",
    "feedback": "Cumulonimbus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming clear skies and minimal to no wind, what surface conditions are most conductive for the development of a radiation inversion?",
    "feedback": "Desert"
  },
  {
    "question": "A parcel of unsaturated air is lifted to just below the condensation level and then returned to its original level. What is the final temperature of the parcel of air?",
    "feedback": "The same as the starting temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "At area C in January, the ..... blowing over the .... current will give ....",
    "feedback": "harmattan; canaries; sea fog"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cold-air drop can be best identified by means of",
    "feedback": "the isohypses on an upper air chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "The figure shows a cross-section of a polar front. Which of the points does the following METAR suit best?\n24006KT 5000 -DZ BR OVC006 07/06 Q0999 NOSIG =",
    "feedback": "Point 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The METAR at a coastal aerodrome reports a temperature and dew point temperature of 10/05. An air mass enters the area from the ocean. Which set of surface temperature/surface dew point values of this air mass will most likely cause advection fog at the aerodrome?",
    "feedback": "20/15"
  },
  {
    "question": "What information is required to calculate a lowest usable flight level from a given minimum safe altitude?",
    "feedback": "Lowest value of QNH and the highest negative temperature deviation from ISA."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL300 when it enters a cirrostratus cloud. Is ice crystal icing likely to occur on the airframe and engines?",
    "feedback": "Unlikely, as cirrostratus are mainly formed by ice crystals which won't affect the airframe or engines"
  },
  {
    "question": "Advection is :",
    "feedback": "horizontal motion of air"
  },
  {
    "question": "The horizontal visibility given for VFR flight planning by a MET Office is:",
    "feedback": "Meteorological visibility on ground."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following local winds is a Foehn wind?",
    "feedback": "Chinook"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the meaning of the abbreviation \"BKN\"?",
    "feedback": "5 - 7 octas."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from Seville Airport in Spain (LEZL) to Johannesburg O.R. Tambo Airport in South Africa (FAOR) at FL390. The flight will cross the ITCZ.\nWhat effect might the ITCZ have on the operation of the flight?",
    "feedback": "Thunderstorms might reach altitudes greater than 40000 feet, requiring the flight to deviate around the thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of cloud is being described ?\nA generally grey cloud layer with fairly uniform base and uniform appearance, which may give drizzle or snow grains. When the sun is visible through the cloud, the outline is clearly discernible. Sometimes it appears in the form of ragged patches.",
    "feedback": "Stratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight is to depart from an airport with runways 09 and 27. Surface wind is 270/05; an inversion is reported at 300 feet with turbulence and wind shear. The wind just above the inversion is 090/30. What is the safest departure procedure ?",
    "feedback": "Depart on runway 09 with a tailwind."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the lowest flight level that is forecast to be subject to clear air turbulence on the route from Valencia to Charleston?",
    "feedback": "FL 250"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aerodrome on the coast (Faro, Portugal) reported the following METAR:\nLPFR 070650Z 26010KT 0100 FG VV/// 05/05 Q1006 =\nWhat change is likely, on its own, to produce an improvement in visibility above the limits stated for fog?",
    "feedback": "Diurnal solar heating"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the benefits of flying in the lower Stratosphere?\n1) Low fuel consumption2) Less drag3) Less turbulence4) Fewer clouds5) Wind is not as strong",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term \"TN11/2106Z TX21/2113Z\" in a TAF means:",
    "feedback": "The forecasted maximum temperature is 21° C at 13 UTC on the 21th of the month"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft cruises at FL 100 in an airmass, which is 10°C warmer than the Standard Atmosphere. The OAT is therefore....",
    "feedback": "+5°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which best describes the maximum intensity of icing, if any, at FL160 in the vicinity of Berlin (53°N 013°E) ?",
    "feedback": "moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "In relation to the wind speed and direction at the top of the friction layer, which change in wind will a pilot normally experience during descent to the surface over land in the northern hemisphere?",
    "feedback": "Backing ca. 30 degrees, speed is reduced by ca. 50%."
  },
  {
    "question": "Cumulus clouds are an indication for",
    "feedback": "up and downdrafts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions is most likely to cause airframe icing ?",
    "feedback": "+FZRA"
  },
  {
    "question": "The isobars drawn on a surface weather chart represent lines of equal pressure",
    "feedback": "reduced to sea level"
  },
  {
    "question": "In Geneva, the local QNH is 994 hPa. The elevation of Geneva is 1411 FT. The QFE adjustment in Geneva is:(barometric lapse rate 27 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "942 hPa."
  },
  {
    "question": "How is wind measured?",
    "feedback": "8-10 m above the ground on a mast with an anemometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "An airplane encounters clear icing during flight. What happens to the stalling angle?",
    "feedback": "The stalling angle will be lower"
  },
  {
    "question": "The weather forecast for a low-level route includes a warning of possible moderate to severe turbulence. While in flight along this route, which of the following sources would provide the most up-to-date information to help the pilot avoid the worst turbulence?",
    "feedback": "Pilot reports (PIREPs) offer real-time information on weather hazards, including turbulence, and are particularly useful for pilots approaching the same area."
  },
  {
    "question": "The navigation display radar on an aircraft shows an upcoming green-marked area. What kind of hazard could the aircraft potentially face upon entering this zone?",
    "feedback": "Light to moderate turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure. What is the airmass at the surface at location L?",
    "feedback": "Cold air mass ahead of a warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft has just flown for 5 hours at FL410 and is performing a fast turnaround to depart again shortly. The fuel temperature gauge shows -11°C, while the OAT is +2°C. A warm front is approaching the airfield and the aircraft is expected to depart through drizzle. What does the pilot observe during the walk-around and what risks of icing should be discussed during the briefing?",
    "feedback": "Fuel frost may be observed on the ground due to the cold soaked wings, and DZ may freeze to the wings on departure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following weather phenomena is most pronounced in the cloud which is shown in the picture?",
    "feedback": "SHRA and GR"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a flight operating from Brussels to Paris, planned for the afternoon 2nd of July 2018, cruising at 6000 ft AMSL. What type of turbulence and icing can be expected?",
    "feedback": "Moderate icing and turbulence with clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the lowest visibility forecast for Birmingham at 280800Z?",
    "feedback": "5000 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather condition would you expect at a squall line?",
    "feedback": "Thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "The percentage concentration of gases in the atmosphere is constant from the surface of the earth to a certain altitude with the exception of:",
    "feedback": "Water vapour"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the displayed cloud forms is representative of a cumulonimbus capillatus?",
    "feedback": "4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot receives the METAR for the destination aerodrome, which reports low drifting sand. Which of the statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Visibility above eye level is not reduced, as the sand should reach a maximum height of 6 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the pre-flight checks, both altimeters, primary altimeter and standby altimeter, are set to the local QNH of 1018 hPa. The elevation of the airfield is 254 ft AMSL. The standby altimeter has just been in maintenance for calibration and indicates an altitude of 173 ft.\nWhen the incaited altitude of this instrument is set to the airfield elevation, what is the pressure indication of the standby altimeter?\n(assume 1 hPa = 27 ft)",
    "feedback": "1021 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight Shannon to London. What is forecast for the eastern sector of the route between Shannon and London at FL 220 ?",
    "feedback": "Moderate or severe turbulence and icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Your destination aerodrome in Western Europe lies on the crest of a ridge, inland, with an elevation of 700 feet AMSL. Before take-off, the METAR for your destination is: \"0850Z  27015KT  0100  R29/0650  FG  VV///  03/03  Q1005\"\nThere is another aerodrome a few miles west of the destination aerodrome at an elevation of 200 feet AMSL. The METAR for this aerodrome is: \"0850Z  26011KT  9999  SCT050  05/03  Q1005\".\nConsidering this situation, what type of fog is present at the destination aerodrome and which of these statements correctly describes the dissipation of this fog?",
    "feedback": "Orographic fog; and as the temperature rises with diurnal heating, the fog is likely to lift into cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a SPECI?",
    "feedback": "A selected special aerodrome weather report, issued when a significant change of the weather conditions have been observed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight Munich to London. What is the direction and maximum speed of the jet stream affecting the route between Munich and London ?",
    "feedback": "230° / 120 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The figure presents schematic views of some of the cloud genera according to the World Meteorological Cloud Atlas.\n\nWhich two cloud genera are marked with the numbers 1 and 2 and 6 and 7?",
    "feedback": "Cumulus, altocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "A CB with thunderstorm has reached the mature stage. Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "In temperatures lower than -23°C icing is still possible."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements concerning the use of airborne weather radar in the vicinity of thunderstorms is true?",
    "feedback": "Accurate assessment of the weather ahead of the aircraft might be hampered due to the attenuation of the radar echoes by heavy rain."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which forces are balanced with geostrophic winds?",
    "feedback": "Pressure gradient force, Coriolis force."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the surface visibility most likely to be, in a warm sector of  tropical maritime air, during the summer?",
    "feedback": "Moderate (several km)."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the best approximation for the wind speed at flight level 250?",
    "feedback": "By interpolation of the wind information available from the 500 and 300 hPa charts, while also considering the maximum wind information found on the Significant Weather Chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ice accretion to the airframe is likely to be most hazardous at temperatures",
    "feedback": "between 0°C and -23°C in large CU"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft performs a rapid (expedited) descent from FL420 down to clear warmer air below. What phenomenon may develop on the airframe?",
    "feedback": "Hoar frost due to the sublimation of water vapour onto the aircraft skin, which is at sub-zero temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate height of the tropopause between London and Berlin?",
    "feedback": "FL 400"
  },
  {
    "question": "The diurnal variation in temperature is largest when the sky is",
    "feedback": "clear and winds are weak"
  },
  {
    "question": "Earth heating by solar radiation is referred to as:",
    "feedback": "Insolation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following types of clouds are evidence of unstable air conditions?",
    "feedback": "CU, CB."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at Fl 150, with an outside air temperature of -30° C, above an airport where the elevation is 1660 ft and the QNH is 993 hPa. Calculate the true altitude. (assume 27 ft = 1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "13690 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a parcel of air which is moved upwards in the surrounding air by an external force. Which one of the following situations describes instability?",
    "feedback": "The parcel tends to gain altitude after being released."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is in level flight at FL100 over a mountain range, which extends up to 2400 metres AMSL. Determine the approximate terrain clearance, if the regional QNH is 998 hPa:",
    "feedback": "1700 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "The thickness of the troposphere varies with",
    "feedback": "latitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Subsidence is :",
    "feedback": "vertically downwards motion of air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the strongest headwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The environmental lapse rate (ELR) is less than 0.65°C/100 m:",
    "feedback": "True altitude will be higher than indicated altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "In addition to the same start conditions as are necessary for an ordinary thunderstorm, what does a supercell thunderstorm require to form?",
    "feedback": "Very moist air at low level and wind shear that increases with height"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term \"horizontal pressure gradient\" describes ....",
    "feedback": "in which direction and at what rate the pressure changes most around a particular location"
  },
  {
    "question": "Clouds, classified as being low level are considered to have bases from",
    "feedback": "the surface to 6500 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying from east to west in the northern hemisphere at the 500 hPa pressure surface. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "If the wind is from the north you are gaining altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flies from London to South France and experiences a strong wind from the left. Which of the following is correct?",
    "feedback": "The true altitude will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "You intend to overfly a mountain range. The recommended minimum flight altitude is, according to the aviation chart, 15000 FT/AMSL. The air mass that you will fly through is on average 15°C warmer than the standard atmosphere. The altimeter is set to QNH (1023 hPa). At what altimeter reading will you effectively be at the recommended minimum flight altitude?",
    "feedback": "14100 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "Why does the green line represent the Dry Adiabatic Lapse Rate (DALR) on the tephigram?",
    "feedback": "The DALR is a linear decrease in air temperature with altitude at a constant rate"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following thunderstorms can be referred to as stationary thunderstorms?",
    "feedback": "Air mass thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements describes a microburst ?",
    "feedback": "A high speed downburst of air with a generally lower temperature than its surroundings"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a snow shower, the small amount of dry snow on the ground is being lifted by rather strong winds. The snow restricts horizontal visibility to 2000 metres between the ground a a height of about 50 ft. \nIn a METAR, this should be reported as ......",
    "feedback": "Blowing snow (BLSN)"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which average height can the 850 hPa pressure level in moderate latitudes be expected?",
    "feedback": "1,5 km AMSL"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements:\n1) In a mixed cloud the ice crystals grow at the expense of supercooled water droplets\n2) In the mid latitudes heavy rain showers are formed by the coalescence process",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aircraft is approaching an airport located in strong wind conditions. The visual approach procedure requires to fly into this wind through a valley on the final approach at 1500 ft.\nWhen flying through the valley, the wind speed will (1)....... due to convergence and the true altitude will be (2).......... than the indicated altitude.",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) lower"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a westerly situation, the mean time interval between polar frontal waves in Western Europe is",
    "feedback": "one to two days"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pre-flight weather briefing must be prepared, and information is needed on the expected weather at the destination for an arrival approximately 3 hours later. Which of the following, available from meteorological services during flight planning, can provide this information?\n1) The TAF covering the estimated time of arrival2) The current ATIS message promulgated by the destination airport3) NOTAMS in force at the estimated time of arrival4) The latest METAR (giving particular scrutiny to any trend information)5) Aerodrome warnings in force at the estimated time of arrival6) The current VOLMET information promulgated by the destination airport7) The Significant Weather Chart covering the area of the destination airport valid at the estimated time of arrival8) Relevant SIGMET information valid at the estimated time of arrival",
    "feedback": "1, 4, 5, 7, and 8"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass affecting position \"S\" is most likely to be",
    "feedback": "Maritime tropical and stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "By the time the front \"D\" has passed point \"C\" the surface wind will have:",
    "feedback": "veered and increased."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud genera is shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Stratocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following instruments is used to measure the stability of the atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "Radiosonde"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the best way in dealing with thunderstorms associated with a cold front?",
    "feedback": "Avoidance of embedded CBs by using airborne weather radar."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following symbols show a hazard for IFR flights, according to ICAO?",
    "feedback": "D"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following instruments is used for measuring the velocity of the surface wind?",
    "feedback": "Anemometer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stable layer at some height in the low troposphere of an older high pressure area in the mid-latitudes is called",
    "feedback": "subsidence inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "Significant curves (changes in direction) are a common occurrence of the (1) .... jet stream in the (2) .... hemisphere.",
    "feedback": "(1) polar, (2) northern"
  },
  {
    "question": "During flight planning for a low level flight, clear air turbulence can be expected when the route crosses ....",
    "feedback": "a squall line near a cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following describes a warm occlusion?",
    "feedback": "The coldest air mass is ahead of the original warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart:\nWhich airport has the biggest probability for rain at 12.00 UTC?",
    "feedback": "LFPO"
  },
  {
    "question": "What causes low level cloud ahead of the warm front?",
    "feedback": "Rain dragging warm air into the cold air and condensing it"
  },
  {
    "question": "When planning a flight at FL 60, which upper wind and temperature chart would be nearest your flight level ?",
    "feedback": "850 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the weather briefing room during the pre-flight phase of a passenger flight from Zurich to Rome, you examine the following weather reports of pressing importance at the time:\n\nEISN SIGMET 2 VALID 140800/141100-EINN SHANNON FIR LOC SEV TURB FCST BLW FL050 S OF N43 WKN\n\nLIMM SIGMET 2 VALID 140900/141300 LIMM-MILANO UIR MOD TO SEV CAT FCST FL250/430 STNR NC\n\nEGTT SIGMET 1 VALID 140800/14122 EGRB-LONDON FIR/UIR EMBD TS FCST BTN N52 AND N54 E OF E002 TOP FL300 MOV E WKN\n\nWhich decision is correct?",
    "feedback": "Because of the expected turbulence you select a flight level below FL 250."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the tracks (dashed lines) is represented by the cross-section shown on the right?",
    "feedback": "D - A"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the answer which you consider will complete correctly the following statement in relation to the main pressure systems affecting the North Atlantic region between 30°N and 65°N. During winter the predominant mean low pressure system at the surface is usually centred over",
    "feedback": "Iceland / Greenland"
  },
  {
    "question": "The amount of water vapor which air can hold largely depends on:",
    "feedback": "Air temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "Visibility is reduced by haze when",
    "feedback": "dust particles are trapped below an inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "A stationary front is a front in which:",
    "feedback": "there is no horizontal motion perpendicular to the front."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main hazards associated with ICI (Ice Crystal Icing)?",
    "feedback": "Engine malfunction and air data probes' obstruction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Advection fog is most likely to form when",
    "feedback": "a mild moist airstream flows over snow covered ground and the wind speed is less than 10 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a normal vertical temperature gradient, at what altitude will the freezing level above Tunis be found?",
    "feedback": "FL 100"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft on the approach to an aerodrome experiences an increase in tailwind due to a microburst located behind the aircraft. In the absence of any pilot intervention, the aircraft will:",
    "feedback": "Descend. The indicated airspeed will decrease"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where does the frontal depression move in the direction of the 2000 ft wind?",
    "feedback": "In the warm sector"
  },
  {
    "question": "The sketch indicates a single-cell thunderstorm in the mature stage which is travelling in the direction of the wind arrow. Which of the following statements correctly identifies the likely locations of various weather phenomena?",
    "feedback": "Severe icing in area E, gust front in area F, and microbursts in area H"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct or incorrect?\n1) The actual temperature of an air mass is higher than the dew point temperature if the air mass is unsaturated\n2) For a saturated air mass, the dew point temperature over ice is lower than the dew point temperature over water",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a clear summer day, turbulence caused by solar heating is most pronounced",
    "feedback": "during the early afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most frequent wind direction in a valley  caused by thermal effects is toward the :",
    "feedback": "mountain during daylight hours."
  },
  {
    "question": "If radiation fog forms on a clear night with light winds, the increase in wind speed from 5 kt to 13 kt will most likely",
    "feedback": "cause the fog to lift and become low stratus."
  },
  {
    "question": "A vertical temperature profile indicates the possibility of severe icing when the temperature profile",
    "feedback": "intersects the 0°C isotherm twice"
  },
  {
    "question": "What significant weather would be expected when passing overhead Rome LIRA (41°N 012°E) at Fl320 at 12:00Z?",
    "feedback": "Moderate clear air turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which type of cloud is most typical evidence of stable air conditions?",
    "feedback": "Cirrostratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true with regards to the forecasting and detection of Clear Air Turbulence (CAT)?",
    "feedback": "Satellite sensors are unable to detect CAT, therefore precise forecasting of such a phenomenon is difficult"
  },
  {
    "question": "While planning an IFR flight, the pilot observes a warm front along the intended route. It cannot be avoided laterally, and the aircraft’s performance does not permit climbing above it. How should the pilot plan the route in this situation?",
    "feedback": "Plan the route through the warm front the shortest way possible"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a summer day, the following observations are made in Zurich:\n0450Z 24009 KT 7000 SCT040 SCT120 15/12 Q1014 NOSIG =\n0650Z 24010KT 6000 SCT040 SCT120 17/13 Q1012 NOSIG =\n0850Z 23014KT 8000 BKN100 19/13 Q1009 BECMG 26020G35KT TS =\n1050Z 28022G33KT 4000 TSRA SCT015 SCT050CB OVC080 16/14 Q1006 BECMG NSW =\n1250Z 31016KT 9999 SCT025TCU BKN030 13/09 Q1009 NOSIG =\n1450Z 30012KT 9999 SHRA BKN020TCU 14/10 Q1011 NOSIG =\n1650Z 30009KT SCT025 BKN035 13/10 Q1013 RESHRA NOSIG =\n1850Z 28006KT 9999 SCT040 11/09 Q1014 NOSIG =\n2050Z 26004KT CAVOK 10/08 Q1015 NOSIG =\nYou conclude, that...",
    "feedback": "a cold front has passed the station in the morning, and rear side weather prevailed in the afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of clouds are associated with rain showers ?",
    "feedback": "Towering cumulus and cumulonimbus."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about lightnings and lightning strikes is correct?",
    "feedback": "The aircraft is temporarily part of the lightning trajectory"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is an interpretation of the METAR ?\n25020G38KT 1200 +TSGR BKN006 BKN015CB 23/18 Q1016 BECMG NSW=",
    "feedback": "Gusts of 38 knots, thunderstorm with heavy hail, dew point 18°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following formulas is incorrect?",
    "feedback": "K = °F + 273"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lowest cloud type observed is Stratus fractus, and there is moderate continuous rain. The area  in which you are at this moment is most likely situated",
    "feedback": "in the main body of a warm or cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a station at the surface the significant weather with a warm front will come:",
    "feedback": "mostly before the front passes."
  },
  {
    "question": "What can result in the appearance of supercooled water droplets in the form of freezing rain?",
    "feedback": "A temperature inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a low level flight at 2000 ft over the sea, an aircraft approaches an area of intense high pressure. What is correct regarding the aircraft's altitude with a QNH of 1014 hPa set in the subscale?",
    "feedback": "The aircraft's true altitude will be increasing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Rising air cools because",
    "feedback": "it expands"
  },
  {
    "question": "An inversion is",
    "feedback": "an absolutely stable layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are flying from Zurich to London at FL 220, what conditions can you expect at cruising altitude?",
    "feedback": "Scattered thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "At high altitudes, the presence of ice crystals can pose which potential hazards to an aircraft?",
    "feedback": "Ice crystals may form inside the engine, caused by clouds containing supercooled water droplets, leading to surges or power loss."
  },
  {
    "question": "Mark the correct statement concerning the flight through an inversion caused by subsidence.",
    "feedback": "During climb, the reduced air density above the inversion layer will cause a certain decrease in the aircraft performance (i.e. lift and thrust) and the pilot will experience a sudden improvement of visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "What change in temperature will occur at point B during the next hour?",
    "feedback": "Approximately constant temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what time of day, or night, is radiation fog most likely to occur?",
    "feedback": "Shortly after sunrise."
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum wind velocity (°/kt) shown in the vicinity of MUNICH (48°N 012°E) is :",
    "feedback": "300/140"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name the weather phenomena to be stated in a special air report:",
    "feedback": "volcanic ash cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option completes the following sentence correctly?\nGustiness is ....",
    "feedback": "a measure of the frequency and strength of gusts and lulls about a mean value"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a parcel of air being forced upwards in the atmosphere. The lapse rate of the surrounding air is less than the saturated adiabatic lapse rate. After the initial force is no longer effective, the parcel of air",
    "feedback": "will tend to descend to its original altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "You intend to carry out a VFR flight over the Alps, on a hot summer day, when the weather is unstable. What is the best time of day to conduct this flight?",
    "feedback": "Morning."
  },
  {
    "question": "The figure shows four vertical cross sections of pressure surfaces, where the lower is near to MSL and the other at an upper level. Consider the positions marked with a cross: Which diagram represents low pressure at MSL with high pressure at the upper level and what is the correct description?",
    "feedback": "Diagram A, thermal low pressure system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct for the southern hemisphere?",
    "feedback": "In the friction layer the wind backs with increasing height."
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering gridded forecast products, what does having gridded data on CBs and turbulence allow?",
    "feedback": "The data can be displayed in a variety of forms to aid crews in visualising flight hazards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: Which route is free of turbulence at FL 340?",
    "feedback": "Shannon-Hamburg"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Harmattan is:",
    "feedback": "A northeasterly wind flowing out from a high pressure area over the Sahara which brings a lot of haze to cities in northwest Africa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying in freezing rain a hard, partly transparent layer of ice rapidly forms on the aircraft and in response the pilot decides to make an immediate change of altitude and/or heading.\n1) How is this type of icing referred to?2) With regard to the intensity of ice accretion and the need for pilot action, how would the above situation be classified by ICAO?",
    "feedback": "1) Clear ice/coating of clear ice, 2)Severe icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which describes the intensity of icing, if any, at FL 180 in the vicinity of the Canary Islands (29°N 015°W)?",
    "feedback": "Moderate or severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "What runway is the most likely to be affected by a reduction of visibility during a landing at sunset, particularly in hazy conditions?",
    "feedback": "27"
  },
  {
    "question": "The SW monsoon starts in the month of",
    "feedback": "June in Southern India to reach Pakistan in July."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena can produce a risk of aquaplaning?",
    "feedback": "+RA"
  },
  {
    "question": "The basic outline of the electric field in the atmosphere may give a potential difference between the Earth's surface and the ionosphere of up to 500 kV caused by...",
    "feedback": "the global distribution of thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the vicinity of PARIS (49°N 003°E) the tropopause is at about",
    "feedback": "FL400"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which of these routes would you not need to worry about icing at FL 180?",
    "feedback": "Bordeaux - Zurich"
  },
  {
    "question": "Imagine an aircraft during approach to an airfield which is located in a basin within mountainous area under the influence of a blocking anticyclone in winter.\n\nMark the most reasonable statement given below.",
    "feedback": "While approaching the airfield in the early morning, after a short period of bumpiness the engines of the aircraft will deliver more thrust after breaking through the inversion layer if the pilot does not intervene."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the optimum flight level between Shannon and Keflavik according to the significant weather chart?",
    "feedback": "FL 240"
  },
  {
    "question": "Radiation fog most frequently occurs in:",
    "feedback": "high pressure systems over land."
  },
  {
    "question": "When otherwise calm and clear conditions exist a station on the shore of a large body of water will experience wind",
    "feedback": "from the water in daytime and from the land at night"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following zones is it most likely to encounter little or no precipitation?",
    "feedback": "Over flat terrain in the centre of a high pressure area in stable atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the speed of the cold front located over Poland?",
    "feedback": "60 kts"
  },
  {
    "question": "State in which type of front supercooled raindrops most frequently occur:",
    "feedback": "Warm front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average temperature for the route Geneva-Stockholm at FL 260:",
    "feedback": "-47°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which meteorological forecast chart is information about CAT regions found?",
    "feedback": "Significant Weather Chart."
  },
  {
    "question": "Find the altitude of the condensation level, when an air pacel is lifted from MSL to 20000 ft. Static air temperature at MSL + 20°C, dew point at MSL +5°C. \nGiven:\nBrown dashed line: Constant saturation mixing ratioGreen line: Dry adiabaticMagenta line: Saturated adiabatic",
    "feedback": "6100 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying on a constant heading with left drift in the northern hemisphere while maintaining a constant indicated pressure altitude. Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "The aircraft is likely to be climbing relative to the surface."
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following changes of state is latent heat released ?",
    "feedback": "Gas to liquid"
  },
  {
    "question": "The environmental lapse rate in an actual atmosphere",
    "feedback": "varies with time"
  },
  {
    "question": "What units are used to report vertical wind shear?",
    "feedback": "kt/100 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "What  causes surface winds to flow across the isobars at an angle rather than parallel to the isobars ?",
    "feedback": "Surface friction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wind is caused by",
    "feedback": "horizontal pressure differences"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the speed of the front located over France?",
    "feedback": "15 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which conditions result in the worst ice build-up?",
    "feedback": "Thin planform and large drops"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a flight operating from Zone D and expected to end in Zone A, planned for the afternoon of 26th July 2017, flying at 3000 ft AMSL. \nWhat conditions can you expect at cruising altitude?",
    "feedback": "Mainly in clouds, moderate turbulence expected within clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the cloud seen on the picture, you can expect (1) turbulence, and (2) icing.",
    "feedback": "(1) moderate to severe; (2) moderate to severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cold front is indicated with a number at position:",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a flight operating from Zone D and expected to end in Zone A, planned for the afternoon of 26th July 2017, flying at 3000 ft AMSL. \nWhat amount and general type of cloud can you expect halfway along your route at 3000 ft AMSL?",
    "feedback": "Mainly 5-8 oktas CU/SC"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is prevailing visibility defined?",
    "feedback": "Greatest visibility value observed over at least half of the horizon circle, not necessarily continuous"
  },
  {
    "question": "In Central Europe when is the greatest likelihood for thunderstorms due to warm updrafts?",
    "feedback": "Mid - afternoon."
  },
  {
    "question": "An outside air temperature of -35°C is measured while cruising at FL 200. What is the temperature deviation from the ISA at this level?",
    "feedback": "10°C colder than ISA."
  },
  {
    "question": "A significant inversion at low height is a characteristic of",
    "feedback": "nocturnal radiation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of icing that occurs in dense clouds with large supercooled drops that have a temperature of -5°C is most likely to be",
    "feedback": "clear ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following METARs is the probability the biggest for the formation of fog the following night?",
    "feedback": "1850Z 15003KT 6000 SCT120 05/04 Q1032 BECMG 1600 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "What can contribute to the dissipation of orographic fog?",
    "feedback": "A downslope wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the northern hemisphere a pilot flying at 1000 FT/AGL directly towards the centre of a low pressure area, will find the wind blowing from",
    "feedback": "left and behind"
  },
  {
    "question": "While mountain flying on a cold winter day, under fair weather conditions (QNH 1013 hPa), you circle a mountain of known height at peak elevation. Comparing to the elevation of the mountain, the aneroid altimeter of your aircraft will therefore indicate.....",
    "feedback": "a higher altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "The occurrence of freezing rain at FL 60 is most likely in square",
    "feedback": "3C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is an interpretation of the METAR?\n00000KT 0200 R14/0800U R16/P1500U FZFG VV001 M03/M03 Q1022 BECMG 0800 =",
    "feedback": "RVR for runway 14 800 metres, vertical visibility 100 feet, calm, meteorological visibility improving to 800 metres in the next 2 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QNH at an airfield located 200 metres above sea level is 1022 hPa. The air temperature is not available. What is the QFF?",
    "feedback": "It is not possible to give a definitive answer"
  },
  {
    "question": "On an infrared meteorological satellite image, a large, bright-white area is clearly noted. On a visible satellite image of the same area, at the same time, a translucent whitish layer is observed. The most likely conclusion from both images is that there is...",
    "feedback": "a thin layer of cirrostratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What threats are associated with ICI?",
    "feedback": "Erroneous reading from heated probes and the possibility of a loss of engine performance or severe engine malfunction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an aerodrome warning ?",
    "feedback": "A message issued by a meteorological office concerning the meteorological conditions which could adversely affect aircraft on ground, including parked aircraft, and the aerodrome facilities and services."
  },
  {
    "question": "The dry adiabatic lapse rate",
    "feedback": "has a constant fixed value"
  },
  {
    "question": "The diameter of drizzle droplets is less than....",
    "feedback": "0.5 mm"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 9882 FT pressure level (FL 100) ?",
    "feedback": "700 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the METAR code the abbreviation VC indicates:",
    "feedback": "present weather within a range of between approximately 8 and 16 km of the aerodrome reference point"
  },
  {
    "question": "A layer in which the temperature increases with height is",
    "feedback": "absolutely stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight crew is preparing for departure from Rabat-Sale airport (GMME), Morocco on 13th October and the following message is included in their briefing pack:\nGMME AD WRNG 2 VALID 131500/131700 SS FCST=\nWhat information does this provide about the weather at Rabat-Sale airport?",
    "feedback": "There is a forecast of a sandstorm that afternoon between 15:00 UTC and 17:00 UTC"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B at the flight level corresponding to the pressure surface of the constant pressure chart. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "The true altitude will be higher over B than over A"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding thermodynamic stability and ground visibility, what are the differences between a warm air mass and a cold air mass in Central Europe during summer?",
    "feedback": "The cold air mass is unstable and the visibility is better than in the warm air mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "With what type of cloud is \"GR\" precipitation most commonly associated?",
    "feedback": "CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an appropriate temperature at the tropopause, located at a height of approximately 20 km?",
    "feedback": "-100°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would you characterise the seasonal weather on the southern side of the Sahara desert over West Africa?",
    "feedback": "Moist, warm SW monsoon brings the wet season with CBs, heavy rain showers and thunderstorms. In the winter, the dry, dusty NE trade winds dominate the weather"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do you understand by \"gustiness\"?",
    "feedback": "It is based on an assessment of strength of variation in measured wind speed and direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "The horizontal and vertical distances that should be kept from CB clouds are approximately:",
    "feedback": "10 NM horizontal, 5000 ft vertical"
  },
  {
    "question": "The mean height of the tropical tropopause is",
    "feedback": "54000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is approaching an airport located on the eastern coast of the Adriatic Sea in strong north-westerly wind conditions. The visual approach procedure requires the aircraft to fly through a valley on the final approach at 1500 ft.\nWhen flying through the valley, the wind speed will (1) ...... due to the venturi effect and the true altitude will be (2) ....... than the indicated altitude.",
    "feedback": "(1) increase, (2) lower"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a microburst?",
    "feedback": "A concentrated downdraft with high speeds and a lower temperature than the surrounding air."
  },
  {
    "question": "What do you expect with fair weather Cumulus clouds?",
    "feedback": "Turbulence at and below the cloud level"
  },
  {
    "question": "The base of the stratosphere is situated where heating by conduction from above and convection from below balance out. It is...",
    "feedback": "lower near the poles because of lower ground temperatures"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which of these routes would you not need to worry about icing at FL 220?",
    "feedback": "Hamburg - Stockholm"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the passage of a front in the northern hemisphere the wind veers. \nThis statement is:",
    "feedback": "true."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: Which weather situation do you expect for EGLL at 1150 UTC?",
    "feedback": "17016G28KT 2500 +RA BKN009 OVC 018 12/10 Q0994 BECMG 8000 ="
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following METARs reflect the weather conditions expected at Brussels airport (EBBR) at 1200 UTC?",
    "feedback": "21014KT 5000 RA BKN015 OVC030 15/12 Q1011 NOSIG="
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft has to fly over a mountain ridge. The highest obstacle, indicated in the navigation chart, has an elevation of 10290 ft. The QNH, given by a meteorological station at an elevation of 5200 ft, is 1013 hPa. The OAT = ISA - 20°C. Calculate the approximate indicated altitude, respectively flight level, ot obtain a clearance of 2000 ft.",
    "feedback": "FL130"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the navigation display, how should the pilot alter the aircraft's heading?",
    "feedback": "Turn left to avoid the storm"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the relationship between meteorological visibility (met.vis.) and RVR in homogeneous fog?",
    "feedback": "The met. vis. is generally less than the RVR."
  },
  {
    "question": "An airport at sea level situated near to a mountainous area has a relatively high Decision Altitude (DA) due to the proximity of terrain.\nThis DA (the point at which a missed approach must be initiated if the required visual reference to continue the approach has not been established) cannot be below the minimum altitude of 3500 ft because of the obstacles.\nIn accordance with the aerodrome procedures, this altitude must be temperature corrected if the OAT is below - 5°C. What should the lowest indication on the altimeter be at the DA if the OAT at the airport is -10°C?",
    "feedback": "3850 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following METAR for Cairo (departure aerodrome)  is distributed:\nHECA 030900Z 34005KT 6000 NSC 37/17 Q1005 NOSIG=\nComplete the following sentence wird regards to the expected cloud cover at Cairo at this time.\n\"No (1) .... with a base below (2) .... above aerodrome level or below the highest minimum sector altitude whichever is the greater, and no (3) .... at any (4) .... \"",
    "feedback": "(1) cloud, (2) 5000 ft, (3) CB or TCU, (4) height"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which process in an air mass leads to NS-AS-ST clouds?",
    "feedback": "Lifting"
  },
  {
    "question": "When low clouds cover the surface during the passage of a front, which is more commonly over hills than over low ground, frontal fog can be formed, but it may also develop when ......",
    "feedback": "the air becomes saturated by continuous rain, which is falling from warm air above a frontal surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "Clouds will mainly consist of supercooled water droplets when the temperature is:",
    "feedback": "between 0° C and -15° C."
  },
  {
    "question": "Icing in a venturi carburettor most likely occurs at temperatures .....",
    "feedback": "between -10°C and +30°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the extract of the surface isobar map, the surface wind direction over the sea is approximately",
    "feedback": "140°"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight is due to depart from London Heathrow (EGLL) at 00:15 local time. The pilot wishes to watch satellite imagery to determine the weather situation on the route. What type of imagery should be used?",
    "feedback": "Infrared (IR) with a polar orbit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Steaming fog (arctic sea smoke) occurs in air",
    "feedback": "with cold mass properties"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct for a warm occlusion?",
    "feedback": "The cold front becomes a front aloft."
  },
  {
    "question": "By the time the front \"Z\" has passed point \"Q\", the surface wind will have:",
    "feedback": "veered and increased"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a generalised zonal system of world wind circulation, the SE trade winds are applicable to zone",
    "feedback": "w"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about warm occlusions is true?",
    "feedback": "A warm occlusion is a combination of a warm- and a cold front. At the surface, it resembles a warm front, with embedded CBs. The precipitation falls ahead of the surface position of the front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which degree of aircraft turbulence is determined by the following ICAO description?\n\"There may be moderate changes in aircraft attitude and/or altitude but the aircraft remains in positive control at all times. Usually, small variations in air speed. Changes in accelerometer readings of 0.5 to 1.0 g at the aircraft's center of gravity. Occupants feel strain against seat belts. Loose objects move about. Food service and walking are difficult.\"",
    "feedback": "Moderate."
  },
  {
    "question": "The highest concentration of ice crystals (HAIC) are most likely to occur within the....",
    "feedback": "anvil overhead the core of an oceanic mesoscale convective system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements:\n1) Outside clouds no severe aircraft icing can occur\n2) Hoar frost consists of ice crystals formed on a surface by sublimation",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "The presence of altocumulus lenticularis is an indication of the",
    "feedback": "presence of mountain waves"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following scenarios would you be likely to find the worst airframe icing?",
    "feedback": "In a CB cloud over Thailand, OAT -6°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate height of the tropopause between Munich and Helsinki?",
    "feedback": "FL 340"
  },
  {
    "question": "Adiabatic cooling is the decrease in temperature.....",
    "feedback": "of an expanding volume of air without heat exchange with its surroundings"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a warm occlusion",
    "feedback": "the warm air is lifted"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "FG is reported only when visibility is reduced by water droplets or ice crystals to less than 1000 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the provided Significant Weather Chart, just south of mainland France, at 40°N 005°E, there is a scalloped area of significant weather associated with cumulonimbus clouds. Which of the following options correctly describes this area? Isolated, embedded CBs from .....",
    "feedback": "below FL250 to FL260"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of precipitation would you expect at an active unstable cold front?",
    "feedback": "Showers associated with thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "Using the satellite image, it can be concluded that above the North Sea (the extent of water to the right of the land mass of Great Britain) the clouds are of the type:",
    "feedback": "Cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which clouds are commonly associated to ice pellets?",
    "feedback": "AS, NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is typical for the snow (tundra) climate?",
    "feedback": "High pressure weather dominates in winter, with the sub-soil being frozen."
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is crossing a mountain ridge, from left to right, in strong wind and ISA + 8° C conditions. A constant indicated altitude is maintained during the crossing of the mountain ridge.\nWhich of the figures represents the actual flight path?",
    "feedback": "Figure 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why does the red line represent the Saturated Adiabatic Lapse Rate (SALR) on the tephigram?",
    "feedback": "The SALR is not linear as latent heat is released, and this is represented accordingly on the tephigram as a curved line away from the Dry Adiabatic Lapse Rate (DALR)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Upon encountering freezing rain during a cruise flight, one of the possible actions to minimize the ice accretion would be to:",
    "feedback": "climb to the warmer air above"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which air mass and cloud depiction matches the routing A-B?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does a pilot react to heavy freezing rain at 2000 FT/AGL, when he is unable to deice, nor land?",
    "feedback": "He turns back before the aircraft loses manoeuvrability."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about the tropopause are correct or incorrect? 1) In the real atmosphere the tropopause is a continuous levelled surface 2) The height of the tropopause in the ISA is 11 km",
    "feedback": "1) is not correct, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "When an aircraft approaches an airport west of a mountain range amid cold and stable air conditions, with clouds forming just below the mountain tops due to a westerly wind, the critical question arises: at what location is the most severe airframe icing anticipated, given that the zero-degree isotherm aligns with the height of the ridge?",
    "feedback": "On the west side of the mountains, just above the ridge"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are planning a flight and observe a discrepancy between weather information sources. The METAR shows a thunderstorm moving away from the aerodrome, while a weather app indicates the storm is travelling towards the aerodrome. Should the weather app be used to make decisions about the flight?",
    "feedback": "Use a combination of METAR and app data for a better understanding"
  },
  {
    "question": "The QFF at an airfield located 400 metres above sea level is 1016 hPa. The air temperature is 10°C lower than a standard atmosphere. What is the QNH?",
    "feedback": "Less than 1016 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tropical revolving storms do not occur in the southeast Pacific and the south Atlantic because",
    "feedback": "of the low water temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "During a cross-country flight at FL 50, you observe the following sequence of clouds:\nNimbostratus, Altostratus, Cirrostratus, Cirrus.\nWhich of the following are you most likely to encounter ?",
    "feedback": "Decreasing temperatures."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the northerly, cold and strong wind, that sometimes blows over a certain part of Europe?",
    "feedback": "Mistral."
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass at position A is most likely to be:",
    "feedback": "Maritime tropical."
  },
  {
    "question": "Judging by the chart, on which of these routes can you expect to encounter moderate CAT at FL 210?",
    "feedback": "Oslo - Paris"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying through the Alps on a warm summer's day. The weather is fine, and there is a high pressure system in the area. During the flight, a mountain is passed at an altitude of its summit. What reading will the aneroid altimeter give, compared to the summit's elevation?",
    "feedback": "A lower altitude than the elevation of the summit"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying over the sea at FL 90; the true altitude is 9100 feet; local QNH is unknown. What assumption, if any, can be made about the air mass in which the aircraft is flying ?",
    "feedback": "There is insufficient information to make any assumption"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cloud type most applicable to square 1E is",
    "feedback": "CS"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is the coldest air to be found, in an occlusion with cold front characteristics?",
    "feedback": "Behind the front."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is \"ice water content\" (IWC)?",
    "feedback": "Ice mass per unit volume of air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Convergence over a uniform surface is caused by",
    "feedback": "frictional force together with cyclonic curvature of the isobars"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are planning a flight from Barcelona to Castres in Southern France. The planned route will take you over the eastern end of the Pyrenees with a maximum terrain elevation of 8000 feet. Your flight is planned at 9500 feet. As you approach the Pyrenees from the south you notice small lens shaped clouds on your track ahead. What is your best course of action?",
    "feedback": "Divert to the east and go around the mountains"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the lowest cloud base forecast at ETA Zurich 1200 UTC?  LSZH 060900Z 061019 20018G30KT 9999 -RA SCT050 BKN080 TEMPO 061114 23012KT 6000 -DZ BKN015 BKN030 BECMG 061518 23020G35KT 4000 RA OVC010=",
    "feedback": "1500 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following weather reports could, in accordance with the regulations, the abbreviation \"CAVOK\" be used?",
    "feedback": "15003KT 9999 BKN100 17/11 Q1024 NOSIG="
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aircraft at FL 40, approaching the front (square 3C) from the direction of square 3D, a potentional hazard exists before reaching the front in the form of...",
    "feedback": "clear ice accretion to the airframe"
  },
  {
    "question": "The length, width and vertical extent of a typical mid-latitude jet stream are respectively",
    "feedback": "1000 nautical miles, 150 nautical miles, 18000 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what degree of icing should ICAO's \"Change course and/or altitude immediately\" instruction be followed?",
    "feedback": "Severe"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the flight route that shows the greatest variation in the height of the tropopause:",
    "feedback": "Route 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Before departing from Gander International Airport (CYQX) in Canada on the 15th, a flight crew receives the following meteorological information:\nCYQX AD WRNG 2 VALID 151430/151800 HVY SN 20CM OBS INTSF\nWhich of the following correctly describes the meaning of the message?",
    "feedback": "Heavy snow has been observed and is expected to intensify, with an expected snowfall of 20 cm"
  },
  {
    "question": "The W/V (°/kt) at 40°N 020°W is",
    "feedback": "005/65"
  },
  {
    "question": "The international standard atmosphere (ISA)is defined for mean sea level as :",
    "feedback": "1013.25 hPa, 15°C, a temperature lapse rate of 1.98°C per 1000 ft. and a density of 1.225 kg/m3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement concerning the cold front and warm front of a frontal depression in the northern hemisphere is correct?",
    "feedback": "The risk of fog is greater ahead of and behind the warm front than ahead of and behind the cold front."
  },
  {
    "question": "A layer in which the temperature remains constant with height is",
    "feedback": "absolutely stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what flight level can we expect to encounter a core of the jet stream situated over northern Scandinavia?",
    "feedback": "FL280"
  },
  {
    "question": "What creates Ice Crystal Icing?",
    "feedback": "Sublimation of ice mostly in the top part of a CB cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "Prior to arriving at an airport after sunset, the ATIS reports calm surface winds, temperature -18°C, dew point -24°C, and a 15°C inversion at 300 ft above aerodrome level. What flight safety risk is to be expected, based on the ATIS?",
    "feedback": "The possibility for low-altitude wind shear"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you are flying from Zurich to Shannon at FL 340, where will your cruising altitude be?",
    "feedback": "Constantly in the stratosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "What words must be used to complete the statement below? \nA wing, contaminated with ice, will typically stall at (1).... Angle of Attack (AOA) and at (2) ..... airspeed, with small amounts of ice having already an effect, whereby the effect (3) .... if the ice is rough.",
    "feedback": "1) a lower, 2) a higher, 3) is greater"
  },
  {
    "question": "The geostrophic wind depends on",
    "feedback": "density, earth's rotation, geographic latitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which weather conditions is the vertical visibility (VV) reported in a METAR?",
    "feedback": "When it is not possible to determine the height of the cloud base"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does this picture depict?",
    "feedback": "South foehn"
  },
  {
    "question": "In mixed clouds composed of both supercooled water droplets and ice crystals, most precipitation starts out as ....",
    "feedback": "snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "In July the weather at D is probably:",
    "feedback": "CU and CB, SW monsoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following situations are you most likely to encounter hoar frost?",
    "feedback": "climbing through an inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the seasonal differences in the weather at warm fronts in Northern Europe?",
    "feedback": "In winter, the warm front is often accompanied by dense fog, a low cloud ceiling, and freezing drizzle at the surface. In summer, the warm front can sometimes produce heavy thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot plans a flight to Malmo, Sweden (ESMS) to arrive at 12:00 UTC on 29th November.\nThe METAR states:ESMS 290610Z 30006KT 0100 FG NSC M02/M02 Q1025 NOSIG\nThe TAF states:ESMS 2906/2918 31008KT 0300 FG NSC BCMG 2909/2912 1800 BR BCMG 2912/2915 3500 HZ BECMG 2915/2918 2000 BR\nDuring the flight, the pilot is advised of the following METAR for Malmo:ESMS 290910Z 32008KT 0400 FG OVC040 M01/M01 Q1025 NOSIG\nConsidering the information available on departure, what weather should the pilot expect on arrival, and should that change after receiving the 09:10 UTC METAR?\nThe pilot could have expected the fog to have cleared to:",
    "feedback": "Mist at worst for the arrival, but the cloud cover reported at 09:10 UTC might mean that fog conditions persist for longer than originally forecast"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B at the flight level corresponding to the pressure surface of the constant pressure chart. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "The true altitude will be higher over B than over A"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct or incorrect?\n1) Ice crystal icing occurs when snowflakes and supercooled droplets mix2) Ice crystal icing is a threat for the airframe when cruising at high altitudes",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Relative humidity at a given temperature is the relation between",
    "feedback": "actual water vapour content and saturated water vapour content"
  },
  {
    "question": "The radiosonde can directly measure:",
    "feedback": "atmospheric pressure, air temperature, humidity."
  },
  {
    "question": "Various types of lightning are associated with cumulonimbus clouds. Which of the following best describes intra-cloud lightning?",
    "feedback": "Lightning embedded within a cloud that lights up as a sheet of luminosity during the flash"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why is the Gulf Stream considered essential to the Earth's climate system?",
    "feedback": "It drives global ocean currents, helping to stabilize temperatures by transferring heat from the tropics to cooler northern regions, which supports diverse marine ecosystems and moderates climate conditions in Europe and North America."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a VOLMET broadcast?",
    "feedback": "Provision, as appropriate, of current METAR, SPECI, TAF and SIGMET by means of continuous and repetitive voice broadcast."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the movements of tropical revolving storms overhead of the North Atlantic and overhead of the Pacific, west of America?",
    "feedback": "10-15 degrees north, from east to west, later turning into a northerly direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "You intend to land at London City Airport one hour before sunset, when ATC notifies you, that runway 27 is in use.\nReferring to the METAR, what visibility can be expected?\nMETAR EGLC 231720Z 26010KT 3000 HZ NSW=",
    "feedback": "Less than 3000 metres, but not less than 1500 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: For which route of flight do you expect icing?",
    "feedback": "Rome-Frankfurt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line of the graph renders the behaviour of the dew point of unsaturated air parcels in vertical motions?",
    "feedback": "The dashed brown lines"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a low level flight at 1000 ft over the sea, an aircraft approaches an area of intense low pressure. A QNH of 1012 hPa is set in the subscale. Which of the following statements correctly describes the situation regarding the aircraft's altitude?",
    "feedback": "The aircraft's true altitude will be decreasing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Vienna (LOWW) to Cologne (EDDK):\n\nWhat amount and type of cloud is forecast at FL 180?",
    "feedback": "Locally broken altocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Stratus formed by turbulence will occur when",
    "feedback": "in the friction layer mixing occurs by turbulence and the condensation level is situated below the top of the turbulent layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "A temperature inversion indicates a state of the atmosphere which is",
    "feedback": "absolutely stable"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the source of moisture in easterly waves?",
    "feedback": "The tropical belt over the Atlantic Ocean during the summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the most favourable conditions for the formation of haze?",
    "feedback": "Dry small particles from an industrial area within a high pressure region"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which weather development has to be expected by a pilot who flies from the East towards a stable warm front which is approaching from the West?",
    "feedback": "At approximately 800 km ahead of the surface front there is overcast cirrostratus; the cloud base lowers to become a typical overcast altostratus and finally a nimbostratus. At approximately 300 km ahead of the surface front, the aircraft encounters rain which intensifies"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the North Atlantic, you can often see a series of depressions located in a row and travelling from west to east. These depressions",
    "feedback": "are normally generated at the polar front."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is correct about forecasts of en-route turbulence?",
    "feedback": "The accurate forecasting of the severity, extent, and levels affected by turbulence is based on modelling; because forecast documentation also covers a fixed time period it is often not reliable, therefore, pilot reports of turbulence are of great value"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what degree of icing should ICAO's \"Change of course and/or altitude desirable\" recommendation be followed?",
    "feedback": "Moderate"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate vertical interval which is equal to a pressure change of 1 hPa at an altitude of 5500 m ?",
    "feedback": "15 m (50 FT)."
  },
  {
    "question": "The meteorological term \"ceiling\" is defined as the height of the base of the lowest clouds:",
    "feedback": "That cover more than half the sky"
  },
  {
    "question": "The upper wind and temperature chart of 250 hPa corresponds, in a standard atmosphere, to about",
    "feedback": "34 000 FT"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which position are you near a warm front?",
    "feedback": "T"
  },
  {
    "question": "Check the correctness of the following statements:\n1) The cooling of air by advection over a cooler surface is the result of an adiabatic process\n2) The change of temperature in rising and sinking air is the result of an adiabatic process",
    "feedback": "1) is incorrect, 2) is correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "How do the elements of a stationary front move?",
    "feedback": "The frontal boundary does not move, but the air masses may move parallel to the boundary"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two aircraft, one with a sharp wing profile (S), and the other with a thick profile (T), are flying through the same cloud with the same true airspeed. The cloud consists of small supercooled droplets. Which of the following statements is most correct concerning ice accretion ?",
    "feedback": "Aircraft S experiences more icing than T."
  },
  {
    "question": "A plain in Western Europe with an average elevation of 500 m (1600 FT) above sea level is covered with a uniform AC layer of cloud during the summer months. At what height above the ground is the base of this cloud to be expected?",
    "feedback": "7000 - 15000 FT above the terrain."
  },
  {
    "question": "During flight, a pilot took an interesting cloud picture from the cockpit. What type of cloud is depicted?",
    "feedback": "Lenticular clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the four radio soundings, select the one that indicates ground fog:",
    "feedback": "b)"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are approaching an aerodrome located west of a mountain ridge. Cumuliform clouds are observed at the ridge-top level above the aerodrome, and the wind is blowing from the west. In which area would you expect the greatest risk of airframe icing?",
    "feedback": "On the western side of the ridge, at the same height as the ridge"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the optimum flight level between Rome and Paris according to the significant weather chart?",
    "feedback": "FL 200"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the chart: State the height of the freezing level over Shannon by applying the common vertical temperature gradient:",
    "feedback": "FL 60"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct? The Ferrel Cell...",
    "feedback": "is the connecting cell between the tropical Hadley Cell and the Polar Cell"
  },
  {
    "question": "You have two pressure systems. System A is an anticyclone, system B is a cyclone. What happens to the True Altitude when you fly from B to A?",
    "feedback": "It increases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement regarding aircraft and lightning is correct?",
    "feedback": "Aircraft made by composite material may get severe damage, the crew may be blinded and temporarily lose the hearing."
  },
  {
    "question": "The troposphere is the",
    "feedback": "part of the atmosphere below the tropopause"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "At the equator horizontal motions do not induce any horizontal Coriolis force"
  },
  {
    "question": "Isolated thunderstorms of a local nature are generally caused by",
    "feedback": "thermal triggering."
  },
  {
    "question": "While using the airborne weather radar in order to circumnavigate thunderstorms, the radar scope is clear between heavy echoes. \nWhich of the following interpretations of the scope is correct?",
    "feedback": "The clear area indicates an area from which no echoes are received. However, this radar scope provides no assurance of being in VMC while flying in this area."
  },
  {
    "question": "The decrease in temperature, per 100 metres, in an unsaturated rising parcel of air is",
    "feedback": "1°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a low-level VFR flight over the sea at an indicated altitude of 2500 ft, you notice the serviceable radio altimeter is showing a constantly decreasing altitude. Which of the following options best explains this phenomenon?",
    "feedback": "A decreasing synoptic surface pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Determine the forecast mean temperature at FL340 for the route from Frankfurt EDDF to New York KJFK:",
    "feedback": "-45°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "A METAR message is valid",
    "feedback": "at the time of observation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The coriolis force is proportional to (1) ...... and it acts at a 90° to (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) wind speed, (2) the actual wind direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight Lisbon to Bordeaux,  ETA 1800 UTC. What type of precipitation is forecast on the approach to Bordeaux ?\n\nTAF LFBD 281400Z 281524 26015KT 9999 SHRA BKN020 TEMPO 1620 26020G30KT 8000 +SHRA BKN015CB PROB30 TSRA =",
    "feedback": "Heavy rain showers"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which line of the graph renders the behaviour of the dew point of unsaturated air parcels in vertical motions?",
    "feedback": "The dashed lines"
  },
  {
    "question": "With which of the following types of cloud is \"+RA\" precipitation most commonly associated?",
    "feedback": "NS"
  },
  {
    "question": "In July, the doldrums over the Atlantic Ocean are located in the region marked by letter (1) ...., and the typical weather conditions in this area include (2) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) V, (2) calm or light winds"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of thunderstorm is solely caused by convective currents coming off of the earth's surface?",
    "feedback": "Air mass thunderstorms"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 100, OAT = ISA -10°C. The QNH, given by a meteorological station with an elevation of 2000 ft is 1020 hPa. Use 1hPa = 30 ft.  Calculate the True Altitude (rounded to 100 ft)",
    "feedback": "9900 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the following aerodrome warnings, a pilot on approach to land at (1) ...... airport has reported (2) .......\nLDRI WS WRNG 1 160520 VALID 160520/161200 WS ALL RWY FCST=LGTS WS WRNG 1 160520 MBST APCH RWY 16 REP AT 0500 A320 35KT LOSS 1 NM FNA=LGAV WS WRNG 1 160520 MBST IN CLIMB OUT REP AT 0500 A320=EDDF WS WRNG 1 160520 VALID 160520/161200 WS RWY18 FCST=",
    "feedback": "(1) LGTS, (2) a microburst"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does the seasonal shift of the ITCZ over the oceans differ from its shift over land?",
    "feedback": "The shift is smaller because the ocean temperatures vary less than the land temperatures"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying at FL 180 in the Northern Hemisphere you experience a right drift:",
    "feedback": "Your TA decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Around Paris on January 3rd at 1800 UTC, the surface temperature, under shelter, is 3°C. The sky is covered by 8 oktas of stratus. QNH is 1033 hPa. If the sky is covered all night, the minimum temperature of the night of January 3rd to January 4th should be",
    "feedback": "slightly below +3°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct ?",
    "feedback": "The Wegener-Bergeron-Findeisen process is mainly based on the difference of maximum vapour pressure over water and over ice of the same temperature."
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud cover is typical for a wide warm sector of a polar front depression over Central Europe in the summer ?",
    "feedback": "Fair weather CU"
  },
  {
    "question": "What altitude does the altimeter show in the resetting procedure while at the transition level?\nTransition level: FL190Transition Altitude: 18000 ftQNH: 989 hPa\n(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "18280 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is true of a land breeze?",
    "feedback": "It blows from land to water"
  },
  {
    "question": "The development of lightning may be described as...",
    "feedback": "a discharge of electricity due to the high electric potential between clouds and the Earth's surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "What relationship exists between the wind at 3000 feet and the surface wind in the Northern Hemisphere?",
    "feedback": "The wind at 3000 feet is parallel to the isohypses and the surface wind direction is across the isobars toward the low pressure and the surface wind is weaker."
  },
  {
    "question": "In the lower part of the stratosphere the temperature",
    "feedback": "is almost constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flies from London to Thessaloniki at FL300 during the winter. Which of the following weather phenomena will form on the route whenever the flight path traverses a strong jet stream in the vicinity of montainous terrain?",
    "feedback": "CAT"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over Madrid, what intensity of  turbulence and icing is forecast at FL 200 ?",
    "feedback": "Moderate turbulence and icing"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is an interpretation of the SIGMET?\nLSGG SIGMET 3 VALID 121420/121820 LGAT-\nATHINAI FIR EMBD TS FCST IN W PART MOV E NC",
    "feedback": "Thunderstorms must be expected in the western part of the Athens FIR. The thunderstorm zone is moving east. Intensity is constant"
  },
  {
    "question": "What will be the effect on the reading of an altimeter of an aircraft parked on the ground during the period following the passage of an active cold front ?",
    "feedback": "It will have decreased."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the four figures represents the vertical cross section of a warm occlusion?\n\nWarm air is rendered in red, cold air in light blue and the coldest air in dark blue. Black arrows point toward the direction of migration",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "The turbulence which occurs at high flight levels (above FL250) is mainly of the type clear air turbulence. In which way can moderate to severe clear air turbulence affect an aircraft, the flight and the passengers?",
    "feedback": "The turbulence is a small scale event and can cause damage. The manoeuvring of the aircraft will be more difficult or even impossible. For the passengers the flight will be unpleasant"
  },
  {
    "question": "The trade winds blow ....",
    "feedback": "from east to west, typically moving towards the equator"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are the pilot flying an aircraft currently established over a holding fix when you observe that you are about to enter an area of heavy rain. How should you respond proactively to this situation?",
    "feedback": "Increase holding speed and thrust to account for additional drag caused by a film of water on the airframe."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which occurences are least for CB development?",
    "feedback": "Ground radiation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate value of atmospheric pressure at 11000 m AMSL in comparison to the atmospheric pressure at mean sea level?",
    "feedback": "One fourth"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature at FL 140 is -12°C. What will the temperature be at FL 110 if the ICAO standard lapse rate is applied ?",
    "feedback": "-6°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true regarding occlusions in Europe?\n1) A cold occlusion is followed by a rapid clearance in the weather and a drop in temperature2) A warm occlusion is followed by a rapid clearance in the weather and a significant increase in temperature3) Cold occlusions primarily affect Europe during the summer and most of the associated precipitation occurs behind the surface position4) Warm occlusions primarily affect Europe during the summer and most of the associated precipitation occurs behind the surface position",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "A layer is conditionally unstable if the air",
    "feedback": "is unstable for saturated air and stable for dry air."
  },
  {
    "question": "The crew are preparing for a flight to a destination in southern India in late August. What additional monsoon-related elements should be mentioned in the arrival briefing?",
    "feedback": "The possibility of moderate to severe turbulence and heavy precipitation from convective clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "The formation of clear ice on the leading edges of an aircraft is most likely to be caused by the",
    "feedback": "relatively slow freezing of large supercooled water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following conditions is most likely to lead to the formation of advection fog ?",
    "feedback": "Moist warm air moving over a cold surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the temperature is at (1) ...... and the water vapour changes from (2) ......, the process is called (3) ......",
    "feedback": "(1) 0° C or below, (2) ice to gas, (3) sublimation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What aviation hazard is most likely to be associated with downbursts?",
    "feedback": "Wind shear"
  },
  {
    "question": "The formation of a lee low may happen if a current of air flows towards...",
    "feedback": "the east, perpendicular to a north-south-oriented mountain range that forms a barrier"
  },
  {
    "question": "What information could you find in a gridded dataset?",
    "feedback": "Flight level and temperature of the tropopause, CB turbulence, icing W/V"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud genera or phenomenon is shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Altocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following meteorological phenomena can rapidly change the braking action of a runway?",
    "feedback": "+FZRA"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which figure best illustrates the vertical cross-section and the average slope of a warm front?",
    "feedback": "Figure 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which conditions are favourable for ice crystal icing?",
    "feedback": "Convective clouds with large vertical extent, such as CB, containing a high cloud ice water content (IWC)"
  },
  {
    "question": "ATIS information contains",
    "feedback": "meteorological and operational information"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight from Perth (31°57'S 115°51'E) to Hanoi (21°2'N 105°51'E): What significant weather conditions are to be expected along this route?",
    "feedback": "Potential moderate to severe turbulence, embedded CB clouds, volcanic ash near Indonesia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following areas experience the most marked ground inversion?",
    "feedback": "Desert"
  },
  {
    "question": "The extent of the vertical development of the jet stream located at 43°N 090°W is ....",
    "feedback": "39000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a mountain-valley wind circulation, the mountain wind blows",
    "feedback": "at night down from the mountains"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of a frontal system do thunderstorms occur most frequently?",
    "feedback": "At the cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Freezing precipitation occurs",
    "feedback": "mainly in the form of freezing rain or freezing drizzle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Define a \"Low\":",
    "feedback": "an area with lower pressure than that of the horizontal environments"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying from Brussels (50°55'N 004°30'E) to Deauville (49°00'N 000°00'E) at FL060. The route will follow the line from B to D on the chart-\nWhat type of clouds and dangers are to be expected during the descent towards Deauville?",
    "feedback": "Mostly cloudy with a risk of moderate turbulence and moderate icing above 4000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A cloud layer (1) ..... solar radiation leading to cooler maximum surface temperatures during the day. At night, clouds (2) ..... terrestrial (3) ..... radiation and re-radiate it back towards the surface.",
    "feedback": "(1) reflects, (2) absorb, (3) infrared"
  },
  {
    "question": "Low level jet streams at relatively low altitudes may form:",
    "feedback": "At night just above the inversion created by the cooling of the air closest to the surface in the atmosphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a height of 5 km above ground level there is a high pressure system above position A and a low pressure system above position B. The horizontal distance between positions A and B is 1000 km. The barometric air pressure at the Earth's surface in positions A and B is...",
    "feedback": "higher or lower in A than in B, or the same in A and B, depending on the air temperature above A and B"
  },
  {
    "question": "What conditions are required for the development of mixed ice in a cloud?",
    "feedback": "Ice crystals and supercooled water droplets of various sizes with a temperature suitable for both clear and rime ice"
  },
  {
    "question": "The stability in a layer is increasing if",
    "feedback": "warm air is advected in the upper part and cold air in the lower part"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following temperature ranges would be most conductive for the forming of carburettor ice?",
    "feedback": "Between 0° C and 15°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Ascension of air is promoted by",
    "feedback": "the presence of cold air above warm terrain"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind direction in a METAR is measured relative to",
    "feedback": "true north"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is an interpretation of the SIGMET?\nLSAS SIGMET 2 VALID 030700/031100 LSZH-\nSWITZERLAND FIR/UIR MOD TO SEV CAT FCST N OF ALPS BTN FL 260/380 STNR INTSF",
    "feedback": "Moderate to severe clear air turbulence to be expected north of the Alps. Intensity increasing. Danger zone between FL 260 and FL 380"
  },
  {
    "question": "The tropopause is a level at which",
    "feedback": "temperature ceases to fall with increasing height"
  },
  {
    "question": "The trade winds over the Atlantic Ocean in July will be found in the latitude band indicated by the letter (1) ..... and the typical conditions are (2) ...... :",
    "feedback": "(1) V, (2) fair weather Cumulus or Stratocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "An inversion is characterized by:",
    "feedback": "Increasing temperature with increasing altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the colour with which a cold front is shown on a surface chart?",
    "feedback": "Blue"
  },
  {
    "question": "What pressure does an observer at point C encounter in the next hour?",
    "feedback": "Falling pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "You observe the altimeter in a parked aircraft while a cold front passes the airport. What does the altimeter indicate?",
    "feedback": "It first increases and then decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the normal and official sources of meteorological information for an aircraft in flight?",
    "feedback": "VOLMET broadcast; ATIS; all ATS-units"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the units of measurement used for RVR?",
    "feedback": "Metres or feet, at the discretion of the State concerned"
  },
  {
    "question": "Amongst others, what has to be expected when a cold and moist air mass covers a warm surface?",
    "feedback": "A gradual increase of air temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dewpoint temperature",
    "feedback": "can be equal to the air temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a pilot reports a potential lightning strike, which of the following effects can be commonly associated with such incidents?\n1) Aircraft damage2) Erratic compass reading3) Failure of some avionic instruments4) St. Elmo's Fire5) The smell of Sulphur Dioxide6) Temporary blindness",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which description best describes the effect of a lightning strike on an aircraft and the consequences?",
    "feedback": "Most aircraft are considered to be \"Faraday's cages\" and the impact of lightning strikes is minor, but in some cases structural damages may occur. The bright flash may also blind the pilot for 30 seconds or more."
  },
  {
    "question": "The following weather message\nEDDM 241200Z 241322 VRB03KT 1500 HZ OVC004 BECMG 1517 00000KT 0500 FG VV002 TEMPO 2022 0400 FG VV001=\nis a :",
    "feedback": "9 hour TAF."
  },
  {
    "question": "State the code used to indicate moderate precipitation in the form of snow flakes from a cumulonimbus cloud:",
    "feedback": "SHSN"
  },
  {
    "question": "A microburst with its damaging winds at the surface",
    "feedback": "has a diameter up to 4 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which main direction does a polar front depression move?",
    "feedback": "Along the front towards the east"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aircraft what are the meteorological dangers associated with a Harmattan wind?",
    "feedback": "Dust and poor visibility."
  },
  {
    "question": "What change in pressure will occur at point B during the next hour?",
    "feedback": "Approximately constant pressure"
  },
  {
    "question": "With a uniform pressure pattern and no thunderstorms around, what will the indication of the aneroid altimeter of an aircraft parked on the ground do over a period of about ten minutes?",
    "feedback": "Apparently nothing, because any changes would be small."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is characteristic of the pamperos?",
    "feedback": "A marked advance of cold air in South America"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which arrow indicates the most probable track of the triple point (occlusion point)?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what approximate flight level is the tropopause over Frankfurt?",
    "feedback": "FL 330"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cloud genera is shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Cirrocumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Clear ice is dangerous mainly because it",
    "feedback": "is heavy and is difficult to remove from the aircraft surfaces"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement regarding turbulence or gusts is true?",
    "feedback": "Gusts refer to a change of wind velocity above a prevailing strength within a 1 minute time limit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which condition is necessary for the formation of clear ice instead of rime ice?",
    "feedback": "In Cumulonimbus clouds, the impact of supercooled water drops that will spread out due to latent heat release"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which typical weather condition is shown by the design for the area of Central Europe ?",
    "feedback": "Westerly waves"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from Point A to Point B on the upper level contour chart. The altimeter setting is 1013,2 hPa. Which of these statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "The true altitude will be higher at A than at B"
  },
  {
    "question": "Troughs are extensions of",
    "feedback": "low pressure areas and generally have large amounts of cloud"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the seasonal weather differences at warm fronts in Northern Europe?",
    "feedback": "In winter, the warm front is often accompanied by dense fog, a low cloud ceiling, and freezing drizzle at the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air mass is called stable when",
    "feedback": "the vertical motion of rising air tends to become weaker and disappears"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following situations favours the formation of heavy thunderstorms?",
    "feedback": "A cold front approaching a mountain range in the evening."
  },
  {
    "question": "After a clear night cumuliform clouds are formed in the morning. Why can the base of these clouds become higher during the day?",
    "feedback": "Because the surface temperature increases."
  },
  {
    "question": "The two most important methods for the transfer of heat from the surface to the higher level of the troposphere are:",
    "feedback": "formation of convective clouds and long-wave radiation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider grid point forecasts provided by World Area Forecast Centres (WAFCs). According to ICAO Annex 3, which of the following are included in these forecasts?\n1) Wind and temperature data for various flight levels from FL050 to FL530 2) Flight level and temperature of the tropopause 3) Horizontal and vertical extent of precipitation 4) Density for various flight levels 5) Humidity for various flight levels",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "In Zurich during a summer day the following weather observations were taken:\n160450Z 23015KT 3000 +RA SCT008 SCT020 OVC030 13/12 Q1010 NOSIG =\n160650Z 25008KT 6000 SCT040 BKN090 18/14 Q1010 RERA NOSIG =\n160850Z 25006KT 8000 SCT040 SCT100 19/15 Q1009 NOSIG =\n161050Z 24008KT 9999 SCT040 SCT100 21/15 Q1008 NOSIG =\n161250Z 23012KT CAVOK 23/16 Q1005 NOSIG =\n161450Z 23016KT 9999 SCT040 BKN090 24/17 Q1003 BECMG 25020G40KT TS =\n161650Z 24018G35KT 3000 +TSRA SCT006 BKN015CB 18/16 Q1002 NOSIG =\n161850Z 28012KT 9999 SCT030 SCT100 13/11 Q1005 NOSIG =\nWhat do you conclude based on these observations?",
    "feedback": "A warm front passed the station early in the morning and a cold front during late afternoon"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena causes a reduction in visibility and is defined as obscuration?",
    "feedback": "Widespread dust in the air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Overhead Palermo LICJ (38°N 013°E) significant weather related to Cumulonimbus clouds can be observed. Which of the following statement correctly describes this weather?",
    "feedback": "Individual CBs embedded in layers of other clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average wind for the route Frankfurt - Rome at FL 170.",
    "feedback": "230/40"
  },
  {
    "question": "If you fly into rain which freezes on impact:",
    "feedback": "Temperatures are above freezing at some higher altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Convective weather phenomena include",
    "feedback": "thunderstorms, hail, tornadoes, wind gusts, heavy showers, lightning strikes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The process by which water vapour is transformed directly into ice is known as",
    "feedback": "sublimation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather phenomena may be observed close to Madagascar?",
    "feedback": "Cyclone, Indian Ocean"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft lands at an airport (airport elevation 600 ft, QNH 993 hPa) with the altimeter set to 1013 hPa. What will it indicate?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "1200 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A primary way for clouds to dissipate is by adiabatic (1) ...... of the air through (2) ..... .",
    "feedback": "(1) warming, (2) subsidence"
  },
  {
    "question": "The mean wind that may be expected to affect the route from Copenhagen to Munich at FL 270 is:",
    "feedback": "260/100"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the cross section below:\nThe cloud type most applicable to most of square 3B is",
    "feedback": "SC"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is expected to clear a terrain by 2000 ft. The elevation of the mountain is 6254 ft and the local QNH at an airport (elevation 3100 ft) is 991 hPa, OAT ISA + 24°C. Calculate the flight level in order to clear the mountain range by the specified clearance.\n(use 1 hPa=30 ft)",
    "feedback": "FL85"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying through the Alps on a very cold winter's day. The regional QNH is 1013 hPa. During the flight, you circle around a mountain at an altitude of its summit. What reading will the aneroid altimeter give, compared to the elevation of the summit?",
    "feedback": "A higher altitude than the elevation of the summit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following layers of fog above land is coded as MIFG?",
    "feedback": "A layer of 5 feet deep."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the typical weather conditions in a westerly situation?",
    "feedback": "Very changeable"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft lands at an airport (airport elevation 1240 FT, QNH 1008 hPa). The altimeter is set to 1013 hPa. The altimeter will indicate:(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "1390 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements is correct regarding the tropopause in the ISA?",
    "feedback": "The average height is 11 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the cruise in an active convective area, the air traffic controller passes a report from an aeroplane ahead that they have recently passed through a zone of intense ice crystal concentrations. The reporting aeroplane is at a similar flight level and following the same route as the aeroplane behind. What possible hazard might this pose for the crew of the jet aeroplane behind as they are half way through the same area?",
    "feedback": "Unusual engine indications"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of turbulence is caused by the friction of air flowing over the earth's surface?",
    "feedback": "Mechanical turbulence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What lowest cloud conditions (oktas/ft) are forecast for JOHANNESBURG at 0300 UTC?",
    "feedback": "5 to 7 at 400"
  },
  {
    "question": "Precipitation of transparent particles of ice which are spherical or irregular, rarely conical, and which have a diameter of 5 mm or less is a definition of ....",
    "feedback": "ice pellets"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the evening an aircraft is approaching an aerodrome. The wind blows from the west and the air close to the ground is very hazy.\n\nWhich of the following visibility conditions have to be expected for the last phase of the approach?",
    "feedback": "The visibility may be significantly reduced due to the low position of the sun and the corresponding blinding effect, which is enhanced by the haze."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which thunderstorms move forward the fastest?",
    "feedback": "Frontal thunderstorms."
  },
  {
    "question": "At a cold front:",
    "feedback": "warm air is lifted as cooler air pushes under it."
  },
  {
    "question": "A Polar Maritime air flow moves south over the UK. What cloud type would you expect?",
    "feedback": "Cumulus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following circumstances most favour the development of radiation fog?",
    "feedback": "Moist air over land during clear night with little wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "Shortly after take-off in an area with local storms, a pilot observes a thunderstorm drawing air into its base cloud, and a narrow funnel-shaped cloud extending downwards from the cloud, touch the Earth' surface. By observing the plants close to the ground, and the dust and debris drifted and carried away, he/she concludes that the local wind velocity is extremely high. The phenomenon disappears within a few minutes. \nThe pilot reports to ATC that he/she has observed a....",
    "feedback": "tornado"
  },
  {
    "question": "A polar front depression is approaching Western Europe over the Atlantic Ocean during winter. In terms of the air masses surrounding the depression:\n1) The warm sector will contain (1) ...... air2) The air to the east of the depression will be (2) ...... air3) The air to the west of the depression will be (3) ...... air4) The air north of the depression may be (4) ...... air",
    "feedback": "(1) tropical, (2) polar, (3) polar, (4) arctic"
  },
  {
    "question": "The lines on a contour chart join points of:",
    "feedback": "equal height."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the most common characteristics of a cold air mass moving over a warm surface?",
    "feedback": "Cumuliform clouds, turbulence, and good visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which information should always be delivered by ATIS?",
    "feedback": "Visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the pressure surfaces bulge upwards in all levels then the pressure system is a",
    "feedback": "warm high"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at 3000 ft indicated altitude with an outside air temperature of ISA + 20°C and with the QNH of 998 hPa set in the altimeter subscale, measured by a nearby airport at sea level.\nWhat is the approximate true altitude of the aircraft?",
    "feedback": "3240 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What temperature does an observer at point A encounter in the next hour?",
    "feedback": "The temperature decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the image, which of the following answers correctly states what may be happening in that area?",
    "feedback": "(3) severe windshear, (5) windshear"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average width of the precipitation zone of a cold front?",
    "feedback": "50 - 100 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "To build a hurricane, the following conditions, among others, must be fulfilled:",
    "feedback": "The surface temperature at least +27°C, and the building area  8 - 15° away from the equator."
  },
  {
    "question": "The arrows labelled \"u\" represent the mean tracks of tropical revolving storms which occur mainly from",
    "feedback": "July to October and are called typhoons"
  },
  {
    "question": "On an aerodrome, when a warm front is approaching",
    "feedback": "QFE and QNH decrease."
  },
  {
    "question": "In which approximate direction does the centre of a frontal depression move?",
    "feedback": "In the direction of the warm sector isobars."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which constant pressure chart is standard for FL 450?",
    "feedback": "150 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the wind speed given in a METAR report based on?",
    "feedback": "The average speed of the previous 10 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which environment is aircraft structural ice most likely to have the highest rate of accretion ?",
    "feedback": "Freezing rain."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying at FL 100, OAT = ISA -15°C. The QNH, given by a meteorological station with an elevation of 100 ft below MSL is 1032 hPa.\nCalculate the approximate true altitude of this aircraft (1 hPa = 27 ft):",
    "feedback": "9900 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "When struck by lightning, an aircraft may sustain significant damage, and its manoeuvrability may be temporarily impaired. Select the correct statement regarding lightning.",
    "feedback": "Aircraft constructed from composite materials may suffer severe damage, and the crew may experience temporary blindness or hearing loss."
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of activity is a part of a Meteorological Watch Office's (MWO) responsibilities?",
    "feedback": "Preparing and disseminating SIGMET's and other information relating to a specific Flight Information Region (FIR)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the impact of wind on the cooling and warming of the air near the surface inland. When the wind is moderate or strong, the maximum surface temperature by day will be (1) .... and the minimum surface temperature by night will be (2) .... , compared to calm winds.",
    "feedback": "(1) cooler, (2) warmer"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wind is 25009KT. It is autumn and the sea water temperature is 18°C. What is a condition for the possible formation of advection fog on the western shoreline of a continent?",
    "feedback": "The ground surface ashore being cool"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these four METAR reports suggests that a thunderstorm is likely in the next few hours?",
    "feedback": "201350Z 21005KT 9999 SCT040CB SCT100 26/18 Q1016 TEMPO 24018G30KT TS="
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the average vertical extent of radiation fog?",
    "feedback": "500 FT."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct for an absolutely unstable atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "Visibility is good between showers"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the essential conditions required for the development of tropical revolving storms?\n1) At least 5° latitude for effective Coriolis force2) Clockwise spin in the northern latitudes3) Energy from latent heat due to evaporation in the core4) ITCZ located between 15° and 30° latitude5) Sea water temperature above 26°C",
    "feedback": "1, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "You have been flying for some time in dense layered cloud. The outside air temperature is -25°C. Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "Severe airframe icing is unlikely under these conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "A valley has filled with relatively cold air during the night, topped by an inversion. On the next day, a warm air mass is advected into the area of the valley at upper levels.\n\nWhich development has to be expected within the next few hours?",
    "feedback": "The inversion will become stronger"
  },
  {
    "question": "When established on the final approach path, and after passing below a cloud associated with a microburst, an aircraft can experience ....",
    "feedback": "pitch changes without pilot intervention"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements is true regarding hail?",
    "feedback": "Flying through hail can inflict significant damage on the airframe because of the size to which the hailstones can grow"
  },
  {
    "question": "At sea level, the pressure of the atmosphere on a standard day will cause the mercury in the column to rise to:",
    "feedback": "29.92 inches"
  },
  {
    "question": "What wind conditions, occuring just before dawn, favour the formation of fog at an airport where the temperature is 15°C and the dew point is 14°C?",
    "feedback": "Calm."
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you encounter the lowest headwind (Northern Hemisphere)?",
    "feedback": "At position 1"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does relative humidity and the dewpoint in an unsaturated airmass change with varying temperature?",
    "feedback": "When temperature increases, the relative humidity decreases, and the dewpoint remains constant."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO, which symbol indicates a tropical revolving storm?",
    "feedback": "Symbol d)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The indicated clouds overhead the central and southern parts of Sweden are moste likely an indication of a(n) ....",
    "feedback": "cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are approaching an aerdrome at sunset for RWY 18. There is haze up to 500 ft and the minimum descent altitude for that approach is 600 ft. The visibility is reduced because of the ......",
    "feedback": "reflection of the suns' rays from the top of the haze layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What weather conditions are associated with the summer Monsoon on the Indian sub-continent?",
    "feedback": "Strong convective activity created by the moist onshore airflow that heats up from below as it encounters the warmer continental land mass"
  },
  {
    "question": "Isobars on a surface chart are lines of equal",
    "feedback": "QFF"
  },
  {
    "question": "An operator wants to fly a new route heading Eastbound in a mountainous area with the highest nearby obstacle at 12500 ft. According to a historical report, the lowest temperature ever recorded in the region was ISA -25°C. The QNH is 980 hPa.\nWhat is the lowest usable flight level the operator can select with a clearance margin of 2000 ft, assuming ISA temperature conditions?",
    "feedback": "FL170"
  },
  {
    "question": "What affects the visibility for 1330 UTC at TUNIS (DTTA)?",
    "feedback": "Smoke"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flying near which type of weather front carries the greatest risk of encountering thunderstorms, cumulonimbus clouds, and intense convective activity?",
    "feedback": "Slow-moving cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud type (genus) is described by the following definition? \n\"Detached clouds in the form of white, delicate filaments or white or mostly white patches or narrow bands. These clouds have fibrous (hair-like) appearance, or a silky sheen, or both.\"",
    "feedback": "Cirrus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider water as a substance. The energy released or absorbed during a change of state of water is ....",
    "feedback": "called latent heat"
  },
  {
    "question": "You have departed Brussels (EBBR) at 09:40Z on a flight to Glasgow (EGPF). During cruise at FL180 you receive the following message relating to an aera the flight is expected to pass through:\nEGTT SIGMET 2 VALID 041000/041400 EGRR-EGTT LONDON FIR SEV MTW FCST WI N5300 W00130 - N5300 W00300 - N5500 W00200 FL070/200 STNR WKN\nWhat hazard is to be expected?",
    "feedback": "Severe mountain waves with downdrafts exceeding 600 ft per minute"
  },
  {
    "question": "The following METAR is in force:\nEGBB 251450Z 30029G39KT 8000 2000W SCT010CB BKN020 09/06 Q1005=\nSuddenly, lightning is observed from one of the CB clouds just over the airfield and a loud rumble follows. What is the correct action to be performed by the ATS unit?",
    "feedback": "Issue a SPECI"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cross-section of air mass and cloud presentation is applicable to the straight line A-B?",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most hazardous type of cloud that may be encountered on a cross country flight is",
    "feedback": "cumulonimbus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Describe the main role of the World Meteorological Organisation (WMO) with regard to aviation.",
    "feedback": "Establish and implement, together with ICAO, a global regulatory framework for aviation meteorological services"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following combinations is most characteristic of unstable air behind a cold front?",
    "feedback": "Good visibility between showers, showery precipitation, cumuliform clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to temperature, which of the following is correct for the polar climates?",
    "feedback": "The mean temperature of all months is below plus 10°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "In warm, anticyclonic conditions during the summer months in Europe, the following can be expected:",
    "feedback": "Clear skies with few or no clouds, visibility reduced in haze"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following best describes the development of a cold high pressure system?",
    "feedback": "Due to cooling of the source from below in a continental area"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct combination of statements regarding to occlusions in Western Europe:\n1) Warm occlusions are most common in summer2) Warm occlusions are most common in winter3) Cold occlusions are most common in summer4) Cold occlusions are most common in winter",
    "feedback": "2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "What change in the height of the cloud base will be observed when flying in VMC from the cold air side towards a warm front?",
    "feedback": "The cloud base descends gradually"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which abbreviations fill in the gaps correctly?\n(1) ....... is a cold, dry air mass(2) ....... is a moderately cold, moist air mass(3) ....... is a warm, moist air mass(4) ....... is a warm, dry air mass",
    "feedback": "(1) cP, (2) mP, (3) mT, (4) cT"
  },
  {
    "question": "The air mass affecting position \"A\" is most likely to be",
    "feedback": "Maritime polar"
  },
  {
    "question": "The isohypse 2960 m can be expected at the constant pressure chart for the following pressure level:",
    "feedback": "700 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whilst flying at FL 180 on the northern hemisphere an aircraft experiences right drift. What effect, if any, will this have on the aircraft's true altitude ?",
    "feedback": "It decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the boundary layer between troposphere and stratosphere called?",
    "feedback": "Tropopause."
  },
  {
    "question": "Where are you likely to find the strongest winds close to the ground?",
    "feedback": "In the transition zone between two air masses"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of activity is a part of an Aeronautical Meteorological Station's (AMS) responsibilities?",
    "feedback": "Performing the actual weather observation at aerodromes and offshore structures"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the statements is true concerning squall lines ?",
    "feedback": "For severe squall lines a SIGMET is issued"
  },
  {
    "question": "A layer in which the temperature decreases with 1°C per 100m is",
    "feedback": "neutral for dry air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which air masses do most often contribute to the weather situation in Western Europe?",
    "feedback": "Maritime tropical air, maritime polar air"
  },
  {
    "question": "While approaching your target aerodrome you receive the following message:\nRVR runway 23: 400m\nThis information indicates the",
    "feedback": "length of runway which a pilot in an aircraft on the ground would see, on the threshold of runway 23."
  },
  {
    "question": "Average seasonal tropopause heights are approximately:",
    "feedback": "latitude 55°N: FL250 in winter, FL350 in summer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is correct with regard to an indifferent stratification?",
    "feedback": "The temperature change of an air parcel during vertical movements is exactly the same as that of its surrounding air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements about thunderstorms are correct or incorrect?\n1) If a trough is situated behind a cold front thunderstorms may occur in it\n2) Prefrontal thunderstorms can occur ahead of cold fronts",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a visual clue which may help to locate and therefore avoid a windshear area?",
    "feedback": "Virga"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nPressure altitude: 3000 ftIndicated altitude: 2500 ft with local QNH of the nearby airport at 500 ftTemperature: ISA + 21°C\nWhat is the true altitude?",
    "feedback": "2710 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is depicted on the radar picture overhead EFVA airport?",
    "feedback": "Heavy precipitation and most likely a CB"
  },
  {
    "question": "What surface weather is associated with a stationary high pressure region over land in the winter?",
    "feedback": "A tendency for fog and low ST."
  },
  {
    "question": "In general, the meteorological visibility during rainfall compared to during drizzle is",
    "feedback": "greater"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which of the following routes can you expect icing to occur, on the basis of the chart?",
    "feedback": "Moscow - Berlin, FL 220"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do you know about the correctness of the following statements?\n1) Prefrontal thunderstorms can occur ahead of cold fronts\n2) A warm front passing a mountain range may become a front aloft",
    "feedback": "1) and 2) are correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following changes of state is latent heat released?",
    "feedback": "Liquid to solid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Clouds in patches, sheets or grey or whitish layers made up of elements resembling large pebbles or rollers, together or not, and always clear of the ground are:",
    "feedback": "Stratocumulus."
  },
  {
    "question": "You must make an emergency landing at sea. The QNH of a field on a nearby island with an elevation of 4000 FT is 1025 hPa and the temperature is -20°C. What is your pressure altimeter reading when landing if 1025 hPa is set in the subscale?(barometric lapse rate 30 ft/1 hPa)",
    "feedback": "Less than 0 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is true concerning an aircraft that is flying at FL180 in the northern hemisphere, where wind is geostrophic and the true altitude remains constant ?",
    "feedback": "There is no cross wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "A trough is an area of (1) ...., causing widespread (2) .... with (3) .... along the line of the trough.",
    "feedback": "(1) convergence, (2) lifting, (3) cumuliform clouds or squalls"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is signified if an occlusion is described as \"cold\"?",
    "feedback": "The air ahead of the associated warm front is less cold than the air behind the associated cold front"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who produces the gridded area forecast?",
    "feedback": "World Area Forecast Centres"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the colour with which a cold occlusion is shown on a surface chart?",
    "feedback": "Violet"
  },
  {
    "question": "Hoar frost is most likely to form when ......",
    "feedback": "an aircraft is parked outside on an airfield with a significant ground inversion and clear sky"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a flight at FL050, using the following data from a nearby airport at an elevation of 1600 ft, determine the approximate minimum terrain separation:\nQNH 979 hPaTemperature -10°CHighest terrain: 2320 ft(assume 1 hPa = 30 ft)",
    "feedback": "1470 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Amongst others, what method is used by meteorological services in order to perform periodical measurements of temperature and humidity aloft?",
    "feedback": "Measurements using radiosondes"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a parcel of humid air is forced to rise from the ground during summer, (1) .... occurs and favourable conditions for (2) ..... are created.",
    "feedback": "(1) condensation, (2) cloud formation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the lapse rates listed below, the air is absolutely stable when 1) Dry Adiabatic Lapse Rate DALR 2) Saturated Adiabatic Lapse Rate SALR and 3) Environmental Lapse Rate ELR:",
    "feedback": "ELR < SALR and DALR"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average wind for the route Zurich - Hamburg at FL 240.",
    "feedback": "230/15"
  },
  {
    "question": "A night in January has been cold and clear. In the forenoon of the next day an airfield is in IMC due to fog which extends to a height of 700 ft. A heavily laden aircraft departs and, when breaking through the top of the fog, experiences temporary bumpiness and a sudden decrease in climb rate.\n\nMark the answer that states the most probable reason for the altered aircraft performance.",
    "feedback": "The aircraft suffers reduced lift and thrust due to a temperature inversion at the top of the fog."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which cloud genera is shown on the picture?",
    "feedback": "Altostratus"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many tropical cyclones form east of Darwin in the southwest Pacific on average per year?",
    "feedback": "9"
  },
  {
    "question": "Cold-air drops.....",
    "feedback": "are most evident in the temperature and wind fields of the upper levels"
  },
  {
    "question": "How can areas with a high concentration of ice crystals be avoided?",
    "feedback": "Considering the areas where ICI (Ice Crystal Icing) can be expected and avoiding thunderstorms in the upwind direction"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying through cirriform cloud at FL300. Ice accreation in the engines and on the airframe is .....",
    "feedback": "possible because these clouds are composed of ice crystals, however, anti-icing equipment is not effective. Crews should request heading changes to avoid dense cirriform cloud."
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight with a jet aeroplane from Munich to London is planned with a departure time of 2250 local time. Which type of satellite imagery available with observation time close to ETD is best to locate the clouds and the exact position of a cold front forecast for this night over Western Europe?",
    "feedback": "Infrared (IR), polar orbiting"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following clouds are classified as medium level clouds in temperate regions ?",
    "feedback": "AS, AC."
  },
  {
    "question": "The cloud base in a METAR of a land station is reported as:",
    "feedback": "Hectofeet above aerodrome elevation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true regarding the relationship between moisture content, precipitation type and the resultant effects on visibility?",
    "feedback": "Visibility in precipitation with large snow flakes is worse than in rain"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the most common characteristics of a warm airmass, moving over a cold surface?",
    "feedback": "Stratiform clouds, smooth air, and poor visibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "Compare the following TAF and VOLMET reports for Nice:\nTAF 240716 VRB02KT CAVOK =\n0920Z 13012KT 8000 SCT040CB BKN100 20/18 Q1015 TEMPO TS =\nWhat  can be concluded from the differences between the two reports ?",
    "feedback": "That the weather at Nice is clearly more volatile than the TAF could have predicted earlier in the morning"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the reason for the seasonal movement of the Intertropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ)?",
    "feedback": "The yearly movement of the Earth around the Sun"
  },
  {
    "question": "Over Prague (50°N014°E), the lowest FL listed which is unaffected by CAT is:",
    "feedback": "260"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding tropical revolving storms in the Northern hemisphere, where do we find the most severe weather conditions?",
    "feedback": "In the quadrant to the right of the track of the storm"
  },
  {
    "question": "To what extent is Munich covered by clouds ?",
    "feedback": "5 to 8 oktas"
  },
  {
    "question": "When planning a flight at FL 110, which upper wind and temperature chart would be nearest your flight level ?",
    "feedback": "700 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the surface chart:\nWhich weather situation can be expected during the day at Geneva airport?",
    "feedback": "TAF LSGG 0716 23016KT 8000 -RA BKN030 OVC070 BECMG 0810 5000 RA BKN020 OVC050 TEMPO 3000 +RA BKN 010 OVC030 BECMG 1215 25014KT 8000 SCT 030 BKN090="
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the wind for the route Zurich - London at FL 280.",
    "feedback": "220 / 50"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the route between Frankfurt EDDF and New York KJFK at FL340. Determine the approximate forecast wind direction at position 55°N 20°W:",
    "feedback": "280°"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the following TAF extract:\nBECMG 1821 2000 BKN004 PROB30 BECMG 2124 0500 FG VV001\nWhat visibility is forecast for 2400 UTC?",
    "feedback": "500 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the vertical temperature lapse rate, up to 11 km, in the standard ICAO atmosphere ?",
    "feedback": "6.5°C per 1000 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is dynamic pressure?",
    "feedback": "Pressure caused by movement."
  },
  {
    "question": "By volume, which of the following elements makes up the largest part of the atmosphere?",
    "feedback": "Nitrogen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select from the map the average temperature for the route Athens-Geneva, FL 150:",
    "feedback": "-14°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "What can be said if you encounter +FZRA during flight?",
    "feedback": "Icing will most probably occur"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is typical for the passage of a cold front in the summer ?",
    "feedback": "Mainly towering clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of fog is most likely to form over flat land during a clear night, with calm or light wind conditions ?",
    "feedback": "Radiation."
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the characteristics of the Bora ?",
    "feedback": "It is a cold and very strong wind that blows mainly in winter from a tableland downwards to the Adriatic"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the images of satellites provided daily by the  Weather Service used for?",
    "feedback": "To locate fronts in areas with few observation stations"
  },
  {
    "question": "Absolute instability is said to exist whenever the environmental lapse rate",
    "feedback": "exceeds the dry adiabatic lapse rate."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from Bratislava, Slovakia to Hamburg, Germany and there is a warm front lying across the route.\nWhere around the front is freezing rain (FZRA) most likely to be encountered?",
    "feedback": "Below the front, in the cold sector, above the 0°C isotherm"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the barometric subscale of the altimeter is adjusted to 1013,2 hPa, what type of altitude is being measured?",
    "feedback": "Pressure altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 4781 FT pressure level (FL50)?",
    "feedback": "850 hPa."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the 2000 ft wind direction at positions 1 and 2?",
    "feedback": "1) SW, 2) NE"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements are conditions that must be in place in order for mountain waves to form?\n1) The wind blows within 30° of a right angle to the mountain range2) The wind speed abeam the top of the mountain exceeds 20 kt3) The wind speed decreases with altitude but the direction remains fairly constant4) The atmosphere is unstable on the windward side of the mountain top",
    "feedback": "1 and 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "A parcel of rising air stays unsaturated. Which of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "Relative humidity increases, temperature decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following are conditions that can result in freezing precipitation at the surface?\n1) an inversion2) a warm front3) a warm occlusion4) convection",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pilot of a small single-engined piston aircraft certified for flight into known icing is en-route on an IFR flight. The latest meteorology reports indicate snow, rain, or ice on all of the available routes. In order to have the lowest risk of ice formation, the pilot should choose the route forecast with .....",
    "feedback": "dry snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under which of the following circumstances will turbulence at a height of 500 m/AGL be greatest around noon?",
    "feedback": "Wind speed 25 KT, hilly terrain, 2/8 CU"
  },
  {
    "question": "It is 17:30 UTC on a day in March. You are listening to the ATIS for an aerodrome with a single runway near London. The following is reported:\n\"Visibility 3000 metres in haze, sky clear\".\nWhen about to land on runway 27, the runway in use,what flight visibility would you expect (no RVR information is given in the ATIS message)?",
    "feedback": "Considerably less than 3000 metres, but more than 1500 metres when flying into the sun"
  },
  {
    "question": "Runway visual range is calculated from values derived from",
    "feedback": "forward-scatter meters"
  },
  {
    "question": "Low level vertical wind shear can be expected during the night",
    "feedback": "in association with radiation inversions"
  },
  {
    "question": "A layer is absolutely unstable if the temperature decrease with height is",
    "feedback": "more than 1°C per 100m"
  },
  {
    "question": "Half the mass of the atmosphere is found in the first",
    "feedback": "5 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct or incorrect?\n1) Ice crystal icing forms at high altitudes and is usually associated with the anvil of a Cb. A high accumulation of ice crystals can damage the engine and even cause engine failure2) Ice crystal icing forms at low altitudes and can affect all aircraft",
    "feedback": "1) is correct, 2) is not correct"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following correctly describes the sustained wind speeds of a tropical storm that has not yet reached the severe stage?",
    "feedback": "34-47 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is true about the relationship between the water content of different types of winter precipitation and the associated visibility?",
    "feedback": "Snowflakes, due to their open structure, obscure more than water droplets"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where is a squall line to be expected?",
    "feedback": "In front of an active cold front."
  },
  {
    "question": "In which figure would you expect the location marked with a cross to have the poorest visibility and lowest cloud ceiling?",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which squares are conditions most likely to cause the occurrence of low level wind shear?",
    "feedback": "3 A and 3 C"
  },
  {
    "question": "An isothermal layer is a layer of air",
    "feedback": "in which the lapse rate is zero"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying from Munich to Amsterdam. Which of the following flight levels would you choose in order to avoid turbulence and icing?",
    "feedback": "FL 260"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the northern hemisphere with an anticyclonic pressure system the geostrophic wind at 2000 FT over the sea is 060/15. At the same position the surface wind is most likely to be",
    "feedback": "045/12"
  },
  {
    "question": "The mean top of a thunderstorm cluster in the tropics is up to",
    "feedback": "50000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these statements is correct regarding the difference between atmospheric turbulence and wind shear?",
    "feedback": "Atmospheric turbulence is the result of short duration and irregular movements of air from the undisturbed wind flow, whereas wind shear is caused by sudden and sustained changes in the wind direction and/or speed within a short distance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements about the weather at a stationary front is true?",
    "feedback": "Stationary fronts are accompanied by a cloud band and precipitation of varying intensity"
  },
  {
    "question": "At the preflight planning stage of an IFR flight, the pilot notes a warm front is located between the aerodrome of departure and the destination. Of the options below, which is the best way to navigate in order to minimise any ice accretion associated with the front? (It is not possible to fly over the front for performance reasons)",
    "feedback": "Fly the shortest route through the front"
  },
  {
    "question": "What should you do if all official aviation met sources indicate clear skies and good flying weather, but a commercial app on your phone suggests heavy thunderstorms for the area?",
    "feedback": "Proceed with your flight, but excercise extreme caution"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the most likely temperature at the tropical tropopause?",
    "feedback": "-75°C."
  },
  {
    "question": "When a cumulonimbus cloud reaches its mature stage and rain begins falling from its base, the temperature in its core (1) ______, causing the air to become (2) ______ dense than its surroundings.",
    "feedback": "(1) decreases, (2) more"
  },
  {
    "question": "The temperature deviation from ISA (to the nearest °C) overhead Charleston at FL 340 is",
    "feedback": "+5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the TAF:\n\nFT LSZH 151425Z 1515/1621 VRB03KT 4000 BR SCT007 BKN028 TX05/1515Z TN02/1606Z TX11/1613Z TEMPO 1515/1524 BKN008 BECMG 1515/1518 RA BECMG 1521/1524 NSW SCT008 BKN015 BECMG 1609/1612 7000 SCT015=\n\nWhich is correct?",
    "feedback": "The forecasted maximum temperature is 11° C at 13 UTC on the 16th of the month"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the approximate maximum diameter of the area affected by damaging winds at the surface caused by a microburst?",
    "feedback": "4 km"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a generalised zonal system of world climatic and wind circulation, zone \"y\" is an area of",
    "feedback": "travelling low pressure systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the vicinity of industrial areas, smoke is most likely to affect surface visibility when",
    "feedback": "there is a low level inversion"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would you characterise the seasonal weather on the southern side of the Sahara desert over west Africa?\nIn summer, the,,,,",
    "feedback": "moist, warm SW monsoon brings the wet season with CB's, heavy rain showers and thunderstorms. In the winter, the dry, dusty NE trade winds dominate the weather"
  },
  {
    "question": "The synoptic chart depicts a region in the Southern Hemisphere. Which type of pressure system is located at position L?",
    "feedback": "Ridge"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is determined by a transmissometer?",
    "feedback": "Visibility, runway visual range."
  },
  {
    "question": "On the route shown on the SWC extract from Lomé (L) to Nairobi (N), the highest coverage of CB to be expected is:",
    "feedback": "50-75%"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about the relationship between temperature and dew point?",
    "feedback": "An increase in air temperature has no effect on the dew point"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what degree of icing can ICAO's \"No change of course and altitude necessary\" recommendation be followed?",
    "feedback": "Light"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight at FL 100 from Marseille (QNH 1012 hPa) to Palma de Mallorca (QNH 1015 hPa), an aircraft remains at a constant true altitude. The reason for this is that :",
    "feedback": "the air at Marseille is warmer than that at Palma de Mallorca."
  },
  {
    "question": "The physical quantity measured by a thermometer in a(n) (1) .... is called (2) .... .",
    "feedback": "(1) shaded area, (2) air temperature"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider a flight operating from Zone D and expected to end in Zone A, planned for the afternoon of 26th July 2017, flying at 3000 ft AMSL. \nWhat will be the freezing level overhead the destination in Zone A?",
    "feedback": "Above 10000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Relative humidity",
    "feedback": "changes when water vapour is added, even though the temperature remains constant."
  },
  {
    "question": "The following temperatures have been observed over a station at 1200 UTC. Assume the station is at MSL. Height in feet. Temperature in degrees C.\n 20000.-12  18000.-11  16000.-10  14000.-10  12000.-6  10000.-2  8000. +2  6000. +6  4000. +12  2000. +15  surface+15.",
    "feedback": "Assuming that the MSL pressure is 1013.25 hPa the true altitude of an aircraft would actually be higher than the indicated altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "The picture shows four sections of the 700 hPa wind chart. The diagram representing most accurately wind direction and speed is",
    "feedback": "030/30 (diagram A)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is mixed ice/opaque ice and where can it be found?",
    "feedback": "Mixed ice consists of clear ice and rime ice and can be found in NS clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Extensive cloud and precipitation is often associated with a non frontal thermal depression because of :",
    "feedback": "surface convergence and upper level divergence causing widespread ascent of air in the depression"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the vicinity of Shannon (52°N 009°W) the tropopause is at about FL",
    "feedback": "360"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a polar front depression, an occlusion is called a warm occlusion when the cold air",
    "feedback": "behind is less cold than the cold air in front, with the warm air at a high altitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following gridded forecasts do the World Area Forecast Centres (WAFC) prepare for flight planning purposes?",
    "feedback": "Upper wind and temperature data, and humidity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct concerning a mountain ridge where a marked mountain wave has been reported ?",
    "feedback": "Ragged altocumulus lenticularis are an indication for the presence of moderate/severe turbulence at the level of these clouds"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which constant pressure altitude chart is standard for a 30065 FT pressure level (FL 300)?",
    "feedback": "300 hPa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is true for the lifting of an air parcel?",
    "feedback": "Unsaturated parcels cool more rapidly than saturated"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does dewpoint mean?",
    "feedback": "The temperature to which a mass of air must be cooled in order to reach saturation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following thunderstorms can be referred to as stationary thunderstorms?",
    "feedback": "Orographic thunderstorms"
  }
]